<div type="section" n="10">
  <head>“The Brothers” &amp; the English Comte de Gabalis</head>
<pb n="330"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 1.</head>
  <figDesc>Emblem of The Brothers.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<p><lb/>The printer was the Old Bourne Press, a private press founded in London in<lb/>
1902 by W. Herbert Broome that produced illustrated books in limited editions.<lb/>
Comte de Gabalis fits the profile of a private commission, using the resources of<lb/>
Broome’s workshop. It is richly illustrated in line, sepia, and photogravure. The<lb/>
unsigned decorations are typical of the Symbolist period of the late nineteenth<lb/>
century, such as the chapter heading (figure 2) which shows the four types of<lb/>
elementals gathered around a philosophical family. The initial letter on page<lb/>
274 (figure 3) is copied, line by line, from Elihu Vedder’s famous painting The<lb/>
Questioner of the Sphinx (the lesser-known version of 1875, in semi-profile). Other<lb/>
illustrations are taken with due acknowledgment from museums.<lb/></p>
<p><lb/>There is only one reference to The Brothers in the body of the book, and it is<lb/>
a teasing one. The photograph opposite p. 297 of a half-length, turbaned figure<lb/>
is captioned: “Portrait of a Master. Painted by R. Owned by The Brothers.” It is<lb/>
visibly an “old master” oil painting with a crackled surface. Since Rembrandt’s<lb/>
Polish Rider (now in the Frick Collection, New York) is the only other painting<lb/>
reproduced in the book, and the artist was known for his love of Oriental cos-<lb/>
tume, the reader is free—perhaps even invited—to imagine The Brothers as<lb/>
custodians of priceless art treasures.<lb/></p>
<p><lb/>Examples of this edition are sometimes seen with the imprint of William<lb/>
Rider &amp; Son, the London publisher of much occult literature, and the date 1922.<lb/>
A new title page has been pasted in, reading: “Comte de Gabalis. Discourses on<lb/>
the Secret Sciences and Mysteries, in accordance with the principles of the Ancient Magi and<lb/>
the Wisdom of the Kabalistic Philosophers. By the Abbé N. de Montfaucon de Villars.<lb/>
Newly rendered into English with Commentary and Annotations.” A catalogue<lb/>
entry of Weiser Antiquarian Books comments: “We can only presume that Rider<lb/>
took over the already bound stock of books from ‘The Brothers’ and had a new<lb/>
title-page printed and inserted, and (perhaps later) a dust jacket printed.”<hi rend="sup">4</hi><lb/>
This<lb/></p>
<p><lb/><hi rend="sup">4</hi>. I am grateful to Keith Richmond of Weiser Antiquarian Books from bringing this to<lb/>
my attention.<lb/></p>
<pb n="331"/>
<figure>
  <figDesc>figure 2. <hi rend="italic">Comte de Gabalis</hi> (1913), p. 115.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<figure>
  <figDesc>figure 3. <hi rend="italic">Comte de Gabalis</hi> (1913), p. 274.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<p>variant is identical to the 1913 edition in every respect except that there is no<lb/>
copyright line.<lb/>
The true second edition appeared in New York, 1914, identical to the first in<lb/>
binding, format, font, and design. However, the text has been reset, so that the<lb/>
pagination differs by a few lines, and the italics and capitals are different. The<lb/>
commentaries lack the London edition’s identifying letters, from A to HHH. A<lb/>
few footnotes are added. If there was a dust jacket, I have not seen it. The obverse<lb/>
of the half-title names “New York / Harry B. Haines, 527 West 110th Street / London<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="332"/>
<p>
<lb/>/ W. H. Broome, 15 Holborn, E. C. / Copyright, The Brothers, 1914.” On the title
<lb/>page: “Published by The Brothers,” and on the obverse: “Copyright 1914,
<lb/>/ By The Brothers. / [symbol] / the news printing company / paterson n.j.” Harry B.
<lb/>Haines (1882–1972) was editor and publisher of the <hi rend="italic">Morning</hi>/<hi rend="italic">Evening News</hi>
<lb/>of Paterson, New Jersey. Evidently this edition was another private
<lb/>commission, executed by Haines’s printer.
</p>
<p>
<lb/>The third edition (New York, 1922) contains a real surprise. It was issued by a
<lb/>commercial house, the well-known Masonic publisher Macoy. The dust jacket
<lb/>carries advertisements for books by Theosophical authors (William Q. Judge,
<lb/>Anna Kingsford, Mabel Collins, Franz Hartmann), and the spine shows the
<lb/>Masonic square and compass in place of The Brothers’ emblem, which now occurs
<lb/>only on the copyright page. The quality of production is hardly inferior to the
<lb/>preceding editions, except that the photographs and half-tone illustrations are
<lb/>in gray, not sepia, and without tissue guards. The text has again been reset and
<lb/>the footnotes numbered, rather than identified by symbols. The portrait by
<lb/>“R” is no longer said to be owned by The Brothers. The surprise is that the
<lb/>translation is now described as “Rendered out of French into English with a
<lb/>Commentary by Lotus Dudley,” and “Copyright 1914, 1922 Sarah Emery
<lb/>Dudley.” Lotus Dudley also signs a new Foreword, inserted on a formerly blank
<lb/>page. All this is confirmed in the U.S. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Copyright Entries</hi>.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Lotus and Sarah Dudley were in fact the same person, and quite conspicuous in
<lb/>certain circles. Sarah Lotta Emery Dudley (1878–1954) was a daughter of George
<lb/>Daniel Emery (1833–1909), a wealthy industrialist in Buffalo, New York.<hi rend="sup">6</hi>
<lb/>She was educated at the Cambridge School for Girls and at Bryn Mawr College.<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
<lb/>In 1904 she married Charles Tarbell Dudley, a Harvard graduate and mining
<lb/>engineer. They settled in San Francisco and had two children, but their marriage
<lb/>was short-lived, for in 1908 Charles died of tuberculosis.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> According to the
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bryn Mawr</hi> alumnae newsletter, Sarah went to England the following year,
<lb/>1909.<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>The same newsletter announces in June 1914 that “Lotta Emery Dudley (Mrs.
<lb/>Charles Tarbell Dudley), has been spending several months in America. She came
<lb/>over to supervise the publication of her book <hi rend="italic">[my italics]</hi>.”<hi rend="sup">10</hi> This explains
<lb/>how the second edition of <hi rend="italic">Comte de Gabalis</hi> appeared from its American
<lb/>
</p>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>5. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Copyright Entries</hi>, New Series, 1922, entry no. 8317 for <hi rend="italic">Comte de Gabalis</hi>
<lb/>dated May 3, 1922, under the number A 674197 and the name of “Sarah Emery
<lb/>Dudley, c/o Macoy Publishing &amp; Masonic Supply Co.” It adds “Copyright is
<lb/>claimed on the foreword, by Lotus Dudley.”
</note>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>6. The career of George Emery, known as the “Mahogany King,” is documented in
<lb/>Samuel A. Eliot, <hi rend="italic">Biographical History of Massachusetts</hi>, vol. 4 (Boston: Massachusetts
<lb/>Biographical Society, 1913), 114–17.
</note>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>7. Information from ancestry.com.
</note>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>8. Obituary of Charles Tarbell Dudley ’00 in <hi rend="italic">Yale Alumni Weekly</hi>, XVIII/7
<lb/>(Nov. 11, 1908): 183.
</note>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>9. “Mrs. C. T. Dudley is visiting Mary Converse ’98 before sailing to England where
<lb/>she will spend the summer.” <hi rend="italic">Bryn Mawr Alumnae Quarterly</hi>, April 1909.
</note>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>10. <hi rend="italic">Bryn Mawr Alumnae Quarterly</hi>, July 1914. “News from the Classes. 1900.” The
<lb/>quotation continues: “She has been the guest of the Sorosis Club, the New York
<lb/>Women’s Press Club, and has addressed other organizations in New York and in
<lb/>the Middle West.”
</note>
<pb n="333"/>
<p>
press so soon, and so faithfully to the original design. It also staked a claim for<lb/>
Dudley to <hi rend="italic">The Brother’s</hi> production, if only among her collegiate friends.<lb/>
From July&amp;nbsp;1915 until&amp;nbsp;1919, Dudley directed a small private school in Green-<lb/>
wich, Connecticut. It was called the Wabanaki School, after the indigenous tribe<lb/>
of the region, and was situated next to the estate of Ernest Thompson Seton<lb/>
(1860-1946). He had been instrumental in founding the Boy Scouts of America<lb/>
and other movements favoring the free, outdoor education of the young, and had<lb/>
a particular admiration for the Native Americans and their culture.<lb/>
So did Dudley. After she retired from the school she became a psychic or<lb/>
spiritual adviser, notably of the socialite and diarist Mabel Dodge Luhan (1879-<lb/>
1962), who knew her as “Mrs.&amp;nbsp;Lotus Dudley.”<hi rend="sup">11</hi> In&amp;nbsp;1919 Mabel was considering<lb/>
settling in Taos, New&amp;nbsp;Mexico, and marrying Tony Luhan, an Indian of the Tiwa<lb/>
tribe. Dudley assured “Mrs.&amp;nbsp;Sterne” (as Mabel then was) that she (Mabel) was<lb/>
destined to build a bridge between Indian wisdom and the West. Taos was to<lb/>
be a great spiritual center, indeed the “heart of the world.”<hi rend="sup">12</hi> Due to Mabel’s<lb/>
magnetism and wealth, the town would soon become a meeting-point of cultural<lb/>
celebrities.<lb/>
Dudley’s later career included international conferencing with influential<lb/>
connections.<hi rend="sup">13</hi> On one occasion her sense of entitlement went too far, and she<lb/>
spent two days in detention by the Paris police.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> In&amp;nbsp;1935 she contributed a long<lb/>
introduction to excerpts from the <hi rend="italic">Ramayana</hi>, published by the London oriental-<lb/>
ist house of Luzac.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> By&amp;nbsp;1937 she appears to have become a Muslim.<hi rend="sup">16</hi> She was<lb/>
evidently a complex woman, whose biography would reward further research.<lb/>
But was the <hi rend="italic">Comte de Gabalis</hi> really her work?<lb/>
</p>
<p>
No such idea was current on the other side of the Atlantic, where the clues<lb/>
converged on a character known only as M.&amp;nbsp;In&amp;nbsp;1927, an “occult autobiography”<lb/>
titled <hi rend="italic">The White Brother</hi> appeared under the name of Michael Juste.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> It describes<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">11</hi>. Gale&amp;nbsp;M.&amp;nbsp;Harley, <hi rend="italic">Emma Curtis Hopkins: Forgotten Founder of New Thought</hi> (Syracuse:<lb/>
Syracuse University Press, 2002), 105-109, on Hopkins’ opposition to Dudley’s influence over<lb/>
Mabel Luhan. See also Lois Palken Rudnick, <hi rend="italic">Intimate Memories: The Autobiography of Mabel&amp;nbsp;Dodge<lb/>
Luhan</hi> (Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1999), 165.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">12</hi>. Seven letters from Dudley to Luhan are in the Mabel Dodge Luhan Papers, Beinecke<lb/>
Library, Yale University, YCAL&amp;nbsp;MAA&amp;nbsp;196, Box 10, folder 274. Here quoted: letter of May 29,<lb/>
1919.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">13</hi>. “I attended the International Congress of Women in Vienna in May and represented<lb/>
the United States on the Committee of Letters, and was at the preliminary meeting at Budapest<lb/>
and the later conferences elsewhere. Since the end of June I have been visiting my old friend,<lb/>
the Duchess of Somerset, at Maiden Bradley.” <hi rend="italic">Bryn Mawr Bulletin</hi>, XI/2 (Feb.&amp;nbsp;1931).<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">14</hi>. “Paris Frees New York Woman,” <hi rend="italic">New York Evening Post</hi>, July 17, 1933: “Mrs.&amp;nbsp;Charles<lb/>
Tarbell Dudley of New York, who was held by police after she insisted on seeing President<lb/>
Labrun last Friday, was released today and left for London. She had been a resident of Paris<lb/>
for three years.”<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">15</hi>. Mahatma Tulsidas, <hi rend="italic">Book of Ram, the Bible of India</hi>, trans.&amp;nbsp;Hari Prasad Shastri (London:<lb/>
Luzac, 1935), 7-22.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">16</hi>. Lotus Dudley writes on Feb.&amp;nbsp;22,&amp;nbsp;1937 from Herne Hill, London, addressing “Dear Sir<lb/>
and Brother in Islam, Assalam-o-alaikum” and expressing her “steadfastness in Islam.” <hi rend="italic">Islamic<lb/>
Review</hi> 25 (1937): 276.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">17</hi>. Michael Juste, <hi rend="italic">The White Brother: An Occult Autobiography</hi> (London: Rider &amp;&amp;nbsp;Co., n.d.<lb/>
[1927]).<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="334"/>
 a group of young aspirants living a Bohemian existence in postwar Bloomsbury.<lb/>
Their mentor, the White Brother of the title, is an older occultist called “Brother <lb/>
M” who takes them on astral journeys and other adventures.<lb/>
The book is actually a roman à clef. Michael Juste was a pseudonym of Michael <lb/>
Hurwitz (1897-1961), author, poet, playwright, and, under the name of Michael <lb/>
Houghton, founder and proprietor of the Atlantis Bookshop, which still exists <lb/>
(as of 2024) near the British Museum. His nephew, the eminent English violinist <lb/>
Emanuel Hurwitz, remembered him as “a benevolent white magician.”<hi rend="sup">18</hi><lb/>
Michael’s friend, called “David” in the book, is securely identified as Raphael Hurst <lb/>
(1898-1981), who would become a best-selling author on spirituality under the <lb/>
name of Paul Brunton.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> Brunton’s son, Kenneth Thurston Hurst (1923-2009), <lb/>
has confirmed that Brother M was a family friend and his own godfather (witness <lb/>
Kenneth’s middle name). But he only knew him as Mr. Thurston, an American <lb/>
painter living in London and specializing in lacquer work for upscale department <lb/>
stores. No one hitherto had been able to identify him.<lb/>
There are two further books authored simply by M and bearing The Brothers’ <lb/>
emblem. The first was The Dayspring of Youth (1933), advertised by the pub-<lb/>
lisher as “By One of the Brothers.”<hi rend="sup">20</hi> The reviewer in Psychic Science speculated <lb/>
that M “seems to be identical with Michael Juste, author of White Brother.”<hi rend="sup">21</hi> It <lb/>
was a good guess, but missed the mark.<lb/>
A second book by M, The Lord God of Truth Within, was compiled by Hurwitz <lb/>
and published in 1941 by the press of the esoteric entrepreneur Manly Palmer <lb/>
Hall.<hi rend="sup">22</hi> It is subtitled A Posthumous Sequel to The Dayspring of Youth, and includes <lb/>
anecdotes about sylphs and gnomes who are M’s personal friends.<lb/>
M mentions Comte de Gabalis in both books. In Dayspring he prefaces a long <lb/>
quotation with the words: “In a book previously mentioned by us, The Comte <lb/>
de Gabalis, we have written this passage about prayer . . .” (p. 326). In The Lord <lb/>
God of Truth Within, M writes: “we have spoken about [Merlin] in a former book <lb/>
[footnote] Comte de Gabalis.” (p. 159) The three books form a coherent, if idio-<lb/>
syncratic, body of doctrine.<lb/>
Yet the 1922 edition loudly claimed to be the work of Lotus Dudley. My <lb/>
first unpleasant suspicion was that she had appropriated Thurston’s work and <lb/>
republished it under her own name(s). He could have been referring to this when <lb/>
he wrote, in the Preface to The Dayspring of Youth, “as certain people in the past <lb/>
have assumed authorship of some of my writings, all publications of the Brothers <lb/>
will be issued in future under their seal and copyrighted” (p. 7). But this does <lb/>
not accord with what is known of Dudley’s character. The references to Comte de <lb/>
Gabalis in Thurston’s later books, carefully read, do not claim authorship: they <lb/>
merely say that his words have appeared in it.<lb/>
18. Riki Gerardy, Talks with Emanuel Hurwitz: 82 Years with the Violin (Edgware: Zelia, <lb/>
2006), 11.<lb/>
19. On Brunton’s connections with Michael Juste and with M, see Kenneth Thurston <lb/>
Hurst, Paul Brunton: A Personal View (Burdett, NY: Larson Publications, 1989), 44-46, 60-62.<lb/>
20. M, The Dayspring of Youth (Yoga Practice Adapted for Western Bodies) (London &amp; New <lb/>
York: Putnam, 1933).<lb/>
21. Unsigned review, Psychic Science 12/4 ( Jan. 1934): 317.<lb/>
22. M, The Lord God of Truth Within (Los Angeles: Phoenix Press, 1941).<lb/>
<pb n="335"/>
By a chance that could only have happened in the era of the Internet, I came<lb/>
across a joint application by Thurston and Dudley for a U.S. patent:<hi rend="sup">23</hi><lb/>
Patent application filed April 15, 1913. Serial no. 761,151. Book cover. Charles W.<lb/>
Thurston and Sarah Emery Dudley, United States Citizens residing at London. Patent<lb/>
issued by the United States Patent Office, July 14, 1914, no. 1,103,102.<lb/>
The application is for a book cover incorporating a slot on the inside into<lb/>
which a card can be inserted. The invention is trivial, but the technical draw-<lb/>
ing accompanying it (figure 4) shows the unmistakable emblem of The Broth-<lb/>
ers, just as it appears on the front paste-down of the 1913 edition of <hi rend="italic">Comte de<lb/>
Gabalis</hi>. And there are the signatures of Charles W. Thurston and Sarah Emery<lb/>
Dudley. Simultaneously with the first edition, they had planted this clue to The<lb/>
Brothers’ identity where no one would think of looking for it. It also revealed<lb/>
Thurston’s first name, making it possible to track him down.<hi rend="sup">24</hi> In 2021 I ac-<lb/>
quired sixteen letters written in the 1920s and 1930s to Hurwitz from Brunton,<lb/>
Thurston, and Thurston’s wife, which supplied further biographical informa-<lb/>
tion on all of them.<hi rend="sup">25</hi><lb/>
Charles Willis Thurston (1872–1937) was born near Boston into an inventor’s<lb/>
family. As a boy he “gathered mushrooms in Emerson’s front yard”<hi rend="sup">26</hi> and fre-<lb/>
quented the local Native Americans. He left a faint trail in the Boston art scene.<hi rend="sup">27</hi><lb/>
By 1908 he was among the host of American artists exhibiting in Paris. Thus<lb/>
he was almost certainly the unnamed illustrator of our edition. I do not know<lb/>
whether there were any other Brothers, nor who was Thurston’s own master. His<lb/>
teachings partly resemble those of Thomas Lake Harris (1823–1906), founder of<lb/>
the Brotherhood of the New Life, who consorted with fairies and claimed to be<lb/>
married to a queen in their realm.<lb/>
A tentative conclusion emerges from this: that Sarah or Lotus Dudley met<lb/>
Thurston in London after her husband’s death. He instructed her in psychic and<lb/>
esoteric matters, and they collaborated on the <hi rend="italic">Comte de Gabalis</hi>. While the occult<lb/>
material was Thurston’s, by page-count it is in small proportion to the excerpts<lb/>
from classical works, quotations, summaries, supplements, and comparisons that<lb/>
fill out the 377 pages, not to mention the translation itself. Dudley, with her<lb/>
Bryn Mawr education and the British Museum at hand, was easily capable of<lb/>
such work. She probably financed the 1913 London edition and the New York<lb/>
edition of the following year. In 1922, with the earlier editions impossible to find,<lb/>
<lb/>
23. The patent application was revealed in a YouTube talk of May 25, 2021, entitled<lb/>
“Who Wrote the <hi rend="italic">Dayspring of Youth</hi>?” I am grateful to the presenter, identified only as<lb/>
“MtalksX,” for this vital piece of information.<lb/>
24. On his ancestry, see the <hi rend="italic">Frost Genealogy</hi> (https://archive.org/stream/<lb/>
frostgenealogyin00fros/frostgenealogyin00fros_djvu.txt) and <hi rend="italic">Thurston Genealogies</hi>, compiled by<lb/>
Brown Thurston (Portland, Maine: Compiler, 1880), 232.<lb/>
25. Charles Thurston married Aileen Winifred Cook (1889 or 1890–1953) on April 30,<lb/>
1921. The marriage certificate describes both as “Artist and decorator.” The letters to Hur-<lb/>
witz will be made accessible on the website of the Paul Brunton Philosophic Foundation. See<lb/>
https://www.paulbrunton.org/index.php.<lb/>
26. <hi rend="italic">The Lord God of Truth Within</hi>, 198.<lb/>
27. <hi rend="italic">The Boston Arts Club: Exhibition Record, 1873–1909</hi>, compiled and edited Janice H.<lb/>
Chadbourne et al. (Madison, CT: Sound View Press, 1991), 375.<lb/>
<pb n="336"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 4.</head>
  <figDesc>Patent granted to Charles W. Thurston and Sarah Emery Dudley (July 14, 1914).</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<p>
  she arranged for its new publication by a commercial publisher. This required<lb/>
  copyrighting under an individual’s legal name, so she gave her own. Since The Brothers<lb/>
  no longer existed as a working group, there was no reason to perpetu-<lb/>
  ate their mystery. If this is correct, the joint patent of a “book cover” in which<lb/>
  names can be inserted and removed was appropriately symbolic, even prophetic.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="337"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">THREE ENDINGS: FITZGERALD,</hi><lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">HEMINGWAY, FAULKNER</hi></head><lb/>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">James L.&amp;nbsp;W.&amp;nbsp;West&amp;nbsp;III</name></byline><lb/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he original endings of three important American novels, recovered from<lb/>surviving manuscripts and typescripts, have been restored in scholarly edi-<lb/>tions. Each restoration involves two marks of punctuation. The novels are F.<lb/>Scott Fitzgerald’s <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> (1920), Ernest Hemingway’s <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also<lb/>Rises</hi> (1926), and William Faulkner’s <hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi> (1939), which Faulkner<lb/>wanted to call <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>. The punctuation marks are a period<lb/>and a one-em dash for <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, a question-mark and a period for <hi rend="italic">The<lb/>Sun Also Rises</hi>, and a two-em dash and an exclamation point for <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee,<lb/>Jerusalem</hi>. An examination of the three endings, as first published and as later<lb/>restored, will demonstrate how marks of punctuation can affect the interpretation<lb/>of literary works. The editions to which the original endings have been restored<lb/>are all “intentionalist” editions. Each of these editions attempts to capture the<lb/>intentions of the author for the text at the time it was submitted, as a fair-copy<lb/>typescript, to its publisher.</p><lb/>
<head><hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi></head><lb/>
<p>Fitzgerald began composing his first novel in the fall of 1917. He was living with<lb/>his friend John Biggs, Jr., at Princeton University, marking time until his army<lb/>officer’s commission was approved. He had decided not to continue as a student.<lb/>When the United States declared war on Germany in April&amp;nbsp;1917, he answered<lb/>the call to colors, enlisting (along with most of the rest of his class) in the armed<lb/>forces. In late July he took the test for a commission in the army. In September he<lb/>returned to the university and took up residence in a dormitory room with Biggs.<lb/>During his final few weeks on campus, Fitzgerald attended lectures in English<lb/>and history and helped with various chores on the <hi rend="italic">Nassau Literary Magazine</hi>, of<lb/>which Biggs was the editor.<lb/>Fitzgerald’s first instinct was to compose his novel entirely in verse, but he<lb/>quickly abandoned that notion and decided instead to employ a blend of prose,<lb/>poetry, and drama dialogue. His novel was to be a <hi rend="italic">bildungsroman</hi>; its working<lb/>title was “<hi rend="italic">The Romantic Egotist</hi>.” Fitzgerald meant to trace the passage from<lb/>adolescence to young manhood of his hero, a young aesthete named Stephen<lb/>Palms, who was the first-person narrator. Fitzgerald produced three chapters at<lb/>Princeton. His commission came through in late October, and he reported to<lb/>training camp at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, in November. There he resumed<lb/>work on his manuscript. Three years later he recalled the process:</p>
</div>