<div type="section" n="11">
  <head>Three Endings: Fitzgerald, Hemingway, Faulkner</head>
<pb n="337"/>
<head>THREE ENDINGS: FITZGERALD,<lb/>HEMINGWAY, FAULKNER</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">James L. W. West III</name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he original endings of three important American novels, recovered from<lb/>surviving manuscripts and typescripts, have been restored in scholarly edi-<lb/>tions. Each restoration involves two marks of punctuation. The novels are F.<lb/>Scott Fitzgerald’s <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> (1920), Ernest Hemingway’s <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also<lb/>Rises</hi> (1926), and William Faulkner’s <hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi> (1939), which Faulkner<lb/>wanted to call <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>. The punctuation marks are a period<lb/>and a one-em dash for <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, a question-mark and a period for <hi rend="italic">The<lb/>Sun Also Rises</hi>, and a two-em dash and an exclamation point for <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee,<lb/>Jerusalem</hi>. An examination of the three endings, as first published and as later<lb/>restored, will demonstrate how marks of punctuation can affect the interpretation<lb/>of literary works. The editions to which the original endings have been restored<lb/>are all “intentionalist” editions. Each of these editions attempts to capture the<lb/>intentions of the author for the text at the time it was submitted, as a fair-copy<lb/>typescript, to its publisher.</p>
<head>This Side of Paradise</head>
<p>Fitzgerald began composing his first novel in the fall of 1917. He was living with<lb/>his friend John Biggs, Jr., at Princeton University, marking time until his army<lb/>officer’s commission was approved. He had decided not to continue as a student.<lb/>When the United States declared war on Germany in April 1917, he answered<lb/>the call to colors, enlisting (along with most of the rest of his class) in the armed<lb/>forces. In late July he took the test for a commission in the army. In September he<lb/>returned to the university and took up residence in a dormitory room with Biggs.<lb/>During his final few weeks on campus, Fitzgerald attended lectures in English<lb/>and history and helped with various chores on the <hi rend="italic">Nassau Literary Magazine</hi>, of<lb/>which Biggs was the editor.<lb/>Fitzgerald’s first instinct was to compose his novel entirely in verse, but he<lb/>quickly abandoned that notion and decided instead to employ a blend of prose,<lb/>poetry, and drama dialogue. His novel was to be a <hi rend="italic">bildungsroman</hi>; its working<lb/>title was “The Romantic Egotist.” Fitzgerald meant to trace the passage from<lb/>adolescence to young manhood of his hero, a young aesthete named Stephen<lb/>Palms, who was the first-person narrator. Fitzgerald produced three chapters at<lb/>Princeton. His commission came through in late October, and he reported to<lb/>training camp at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, in November. There he resumed<lb/>work on his manuscript. Three years later he recalled the process:</p>
<pb n="338"/>
<p>Every Saturday at one o’clock when the week’s work was over I hurried to the Of-<lb/>
ficers’ Club, and there, in a corner of a roomful of smoke, conversation and rattling<lb/>
newspapers, I wrote a 120,000-word novel on the consecutive week-ends of three months.<lb/>
There was no revising; there was no time for it. As I finished each chapter I sent it to a<lb/>
typist in Princeton.<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p>
<p>By February 1918 Fitzgerald had in hand a finished typescript of “The Ro-<lb/>
mantic Egotist.”<hi rend="sup">2</hi> In March he submitted it to Charles Scribner’s Sons. There<lb/>
the novel caught the attention of a young editor named Maxwell Perkins, who<lb/>
recognized the author’s inventiveness and talent. Perkins’ enthusiasm, however,<lb/>
was not enough to carry the day. The other editors at the firm were skeptical<lb/>
about Fitzgerald’s novel; they considered it to be garrulous and immature, poorly<lb/>
structured and overburdened with detail. The rejection letter to Fitzgerald, dated<lb/>
19 August 1918, put special emphasis on the ending of “The Romantic Egotist.”<lb/>
The letter reads in part: “[T]he story does not seem to us to work up to a conclu-<lb/>
sion;—neither the hero’s career nor his character are shown to be brought to any<lb/>
stage which justifies an ending.” And the letter continues: “It seems to us in short<lb/>
that the story does not culminate in anything as it must to justify the reader’s<lb/>
interest as he follows it; and that it might be made to do so quite consistently with<lb/>
the characters and with its earlier stages.”<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Fitzgerald, now stationed at Camp<lb/>
Sheridan, Alabama, was troubled by this letter. “How could I intrigue the hero<lb/>
into a ‘philosophy of life,’” he later wrote, “when my own ideas were in much<lb/>
the state of Alice’s after the hatter’s tea-party?”<hi rend="sup">4</hi></p>
<p>The armistice that ended the war was signed on 11 November 1918. Fitzger-<lb/>
ald, who did not “make it over” to Europe, was discharged in February 1919.<lb/>
After an unsuccessful five-month stint as a copy-writer at the Barron Collier<lb/>
advertising agency in New York City, he quit his job and went home to St. Paul,<lb/>
Minnesota. There, in a third-floor room in his parents’ house, he set about re-<lb/>
writing his novel. He took the best parts of “The Romantic Egotist” and added<lb/>
freshly composed material; he also incorporated the typescripts of a short story,<lb/>
a one-act play, and several poems into the narrative—most of this material orig-<lb/>
inally written at Princeton. At Perkins’ suggestion he dropped the breathless<lb/>
first-person narration of “The Romantic Egotist” and shifted to a more mature<lb/>
third-person voice. He changed the protagonist’s name from Stephen Palms to<lb/>
Amory Blaine and altered the title to <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, a phrase taken from<lb/>
the penultimate line of Rupert Brooke’s poem “Tiare Tahiti.”<hi rend="sup">5</hi> The result was<lb/>
a fast-moving narrative, loosely unified, and crowded with characters and inci-<lb/>
</p>
<div type="footnotes">
<p><hi rend="sup">1.</hi> “Who’s Who—and Why,” <hi rend="italic">Saturday Evening Post</hi> 193 (18 September 1920): 61; collected<lb/>
in <hi rend="italic">My Lost City</hi>, ed. James&amp;nbsp;L.&amp;nbsp;W. West&amp;nbsp;III (Cambridge and New&amp;nbsp;York: Cambridge University<lb/>
Press, 2005): 4.</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">2.</hi> Typescript fragments of “The Romantic Egotist” survive in Fitzgerald’s papers at the<lb/>
Department of Special Collections, Princeton University Library.</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">3.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Correspondence of F. Scott Fitzgerald</hi>, ed. Matthew&amp;nbsp;J. Bruccoli, Margaret&amp;nbsp;M. Duggan, and<lb/>
Susan Walker (New&amp;nbsp;York: Random House, 1980): 31. The letter, signed “Charles Scribner’s<lb/>
Sons,” was probably written by Maxwell Perkins.</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">4.</hi> From Fitzgerald’s preface to <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, ed. James&amp;nbsp;L.&amp;nbsp;W.<lb/>
West&amp;nbsp;III (Cambridge and New&amp;nbsp;York: Cambridge University Press, 1995): 394.</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">5.</hi> “Tiare Tahiti,” in <hi rend="italic">1914 and Other Poems</hi> (London: Sidgwick and Jackson, 1915): 19-21.</p>
</div>
<pb n="339"/>
<p>dents. Fitzgerald was sure that this novel, now nearly complete in manuscript, had caught the mood of his post-war generation.<lb/>
Still there was the problem of the ending. <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> was a coming-of-age story: how was Fitzgerald to bring the novel to a satisfactory conclusion when his hero’s life was only getting under way? Under pressure he improvised a solution. In the last chapter of the novel, he sent Amory on a long walk from New York City to Princeton. Along the way Amory contemplates his current situation: he is penniless and unemployed but unwilling to pursue a conventional course in life. Almost his only achievement, he believes, is a hard-won self-knowledge. He arrives in Princeton long after midnight and contemplates the towers and spires of the university. “Here was a new generation, shouting the old cries, learn-<lb/>ing the old creeds, through a reverie of long days and nights,” Amory muses, “a new generation dedicated more than the last to the fear of poverty and the worship of success; grown up to find all gods dead, all wars fought, all faiths in man shaken….”<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Amory stretches out his arms to the “crystalline, radiant sky”: “I know myself,” he cried, “but that is all—”<lb/>
The dash, in Fitzgerald’s hand at the end of the manuscript, addresses the criti-<lb/>cism in the rejection letter. The dash captures the unfinished nature of the novel and makes it clear that everything in Amory’s life so far has been preliminary (see figure 1).<lb/>
Somewhere between manuscript and first print, the dash became a period. No evidence survives to reveal who made the change. The manuscript, made up of heavily revised holograph and typescript sheets, is preserved among Fitzgerald’s papers in the Department of Special Collections at Princeton.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> The document, messy and difficult to follow, is not a fair copy. A typescript made from this manu-<lb/>script served as setting copy, but that typescript does not survive, nor do galleys or page proofs. The change from dash to period might therefore have been made anywhere along the line of textual transmission: by Fitzgerald’s typist (Fitzgerald could not type), by a Scribner copy-editor, or by Perkins. Fitzgerald himself might have made the change, either on the setting copy or in proof, or he might have accepted the alteration after it was urged upon him by Perkins, though there is no letter from the editor to Fitzgerald in which this change is suggested.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> The first edition of the novel, published on 26 March 1920, ends with a period (see figure 2).<lb/>
The presence of the dash in the last line of the manuscript was first noted in my dissertation.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> In 1982 I included a discussion of the dash and period in a<lb/></p>
<note place="foot">6. Cambridge edition, 260. I have emended “Gods” to “gods” in this quotation.<lb/></note>
<note place="foot">7. The manuscript can be viewed in a full-color digital reproduction on the Special Collec-<lb/>tions website at Princeton. The manuscript of <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> and the typescript fragments of “The Romantic Egotist” are both published in black-and-white facsimile in <hi rend="italic">F. Scott Fitzgerald Manuscripts</hi>, vol. I, parts 1 and 2, ed. Matthew J. Bruccoli (New York and London: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1990).<lb/></note>
<note place="foot">8. Letters between Fitzgerald and Perkins concerning the production and proofing of <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> are published in <hi rend="italic">Dear Scott/Dear Max: The Fitzgerald–Perkins Correspondence</hi>, ed. John Kuehl and Jackson R. Bryer (New York: Scribner, 1971): 17–30.<lb/></note>
<note place="foot">9. “Materials for an Established Text of F. Scott Fitzgerald’s <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>.” Diss., University of South Carolina, 1971, p. 42.<lb/></note>
<pb n="340"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 1.</head>
  <figDesc>From final page of the manuscript, <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>. F. Scott Fitzgerald Papers, Department of Special Collections, Princeton University Library.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<figure>
  <head>figure 2.</head>
  <figDesc>From final page of the first edition, <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>. Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1920.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<p>
monograph derived from the dissertation.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> All editions of <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, however, continued to end with the period until 1995. In that year I published<lb/>
a full-dress edition of the novel with Cambridge University Press as the third<lb/>
volume in <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge Edition of the Works of F. Scott Fitzgerald</hi>. The<lb/>
text of this edition ends with a dash. The strongest evidence for the dash is the<lb/>
manuscript leaf, which is inscribed in Fitzgerald’s hand. The period, by contrast,<lb/>
could have been introduced by anyone involved in the making of the book. For<lb/>
the Cambridge edition, I chose the dash.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
The final punctuation mark has an effect on how the novel is read and inter-<lb/>
preted. With the period, the novel comes to an abrupt halt. (“I know myself,” he<lb/>
cried, “but that is all.”) Self-knowledge has been achieved. Amory’s education<lb/>
is finished; his young manhood is over; he is ready to face whatever life brings.<lb/>
With the dash the novel is open-ended and the conclusion more hesitant. (“I<lb/>
</p>
<note place="foot">
<hi rend="sup">10</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Making of This Side of Paradise</hi> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1982): 73–80.<lb/>
</note>
<pb n="341"/>
<lb/>know myself,” he cried, but that is all—”) Amory knows himself, or believes that <lb/>he does, but that is all he is confident of knowing. He is still fundamentally the <lb/>same person—idle, romantic, inquisitive, skeptical, unwilling to conform. Per<lb/>haps there is a place in society for him, but this is far from certain. Only the first <lb/>part of Amory’s life has been completed. The dash dovetails with the title—<hi rend="italic">This <lb/>Side of Paradise</hi>. The reader has followed Amory’s journey to the beginnings of <lb/>adulthood; what will come next we do not know.<lb/>
The 1995 Cambridge text, ending with the dash, was published with the ap<lb/>proval of the F. Scott Fitzgerald Literary Trust. This text was adopted by Scrib<lb/>ner as its standard text and was first reprinted as a paperback by that publisher <lb/>in 1996. The text with the dash has appeared in all Scribner editions from that <lb/>date to the present.<lb/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">The Sun Also Rises</hi></head><lb/>
Ernest Hemingway began work on his first novel in mid-July 1925, shortly after <lb/>attending, for the third time, the annual bullfighting fiesta in the Spanish town of <lb/>Pamplona. He worked steadily on the novel through July and August and finished <lb/>an autograph first draft on 21 September 1925. His working title was “Fiesta: A <lb/>Novel.” Hemingway (who, unlike Fitzgerald, could type) prepared a typescript <lb/>from his manuscript. This typescript does not survive, but it must have existed. <lb/>The differences between the holograph and the setting-copy typescript, which is <lb/>extant, are so great that at least one revised typescript (and possibly more than <lb/>one) must have intervened. Hemingway used a professional typing service for prepa<lb/>ration of the setting copy. He made a very few emendations in his own hand on the <lb/>finished sheets. The typescript, a fair copy bearing the title <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>, <lb/>was put into the transatlantic mail to Maxwell Perkins at Scribner on 24 April 1926.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> <lb/>This is the document that served as setting copy for the first edition; it survives <lb/>today in the Papers of Ernest Hemingway at the Albert and Shirley Small Special <lb/>Collections Library, University of Virginia. (The manuscript is preserved in the <lb/>Ernest Hemingway Collection, John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Muse<lb/>um.<hi rend="sup">12</hi>) The compositors at the Scribner Press added handwritten galley “takes” to <lb/>the setting copy—markings that indicate where each galley begins and ends—<lb/>but this typescript was not otherwise marked before the type was assembled. All <lb/>changes between the setting copy and the first edition must therefore have taken <lb/>place in proof. Neither galleys nor page proofs, however, are known to survive.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi> is the quintessential “lost generation” novel. It portrays the <lb/>enervation and nihilism of the generation that had lived through the Great War. <lb/>Much of the novel is presented in dialogue; the exchanges between characters <lb/>are flat and unemotional, though a great deal is happening beneath the surface.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">11</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Ernest Hemingway</hi>, vol. 3, ed. Rena Sanderson, Sandra Spanier, and <lb/>Robert W. Trogdon (Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press, 2015): 64–66. <lb/>Hemingway was living in Paris during the proofing of the novel.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">12</hi>. This manuscript has been published in facsimile: Ernest Hemingway, <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also <lb/>Rises: A Facsimile Edition</hi>, ed. Matthew J. Bruccoli. Archive of Literary Documents II. <lb/>(Detroit: Omnigraphics, 1990).<lb/>
<pb n="342"/>
<p><lb/>The protagonist and first-person narrator is Jake Barnes, a journalist who has<lb/>been wounded during the war. The wound has left him incapable of sex. He is<lb/>in love with Brett Ashley, a decadent British aristocrat who seems to return his<lb/>feelings, but they are unable to consummate their love.<lb/>At the very end of the novel, Jake and Brett are together in a taxi-cab. His<lb/>arm is around her, and she is resting her head on his shoulder. “Oh, Jake,” she<lb/>says, “we could have had such a damned good time together.” Jake’s answer in<lb/>the manuscript is ironic: “Yes,” he says. “It’s nice as hell to think so.” The sen-<lb/>tence ends with a period. At the bottom of this same manuscript page, the final<lb/>leaf of the document, Hemingway has written an alternate version of the line:<lb/>“Isn’t it nice to think so”—with no terminal punctuation. In the setting-copy<lb/>typescript, prepared by the typing service, the final line is worded differently but<lb/>still ends with a period, though the period is typed outside the quotation marks.<lb/>(“Isn’t it pretty to think so”.)<hi rend="sup">13</hi> The final line of the first edition, published by<lb/>Scribner on 22 October 1926, ends on page 259 with a question-mark. (“Isn’t it<lb/>pretty to think so?”) (See figures 3, 4, and 5).<lb/>No evidence survives to indicate who changed the period to a question-mark.<lb/>Hemingway received galley proofs from Perkins on 11 August 1926 and returned<lb/>them, with corrections, on 27 August.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> As I have mentioned, these galleys do<lb/>not survive, nor do page proofs. The extant correspondence between Perkins and<lb/>Hemingway concerns various textual matters—the use of profanity and of real<lb/>names primarily. <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi> was bowdlerized in proof. Three instances<lb/>of “bulls have no balls” in Book Two, chapter 16, were altered to “bulls have no<lb/>horns” (first edition, pp. 181-82). In the letters between Hemingway and Perkins,<lb/>however, there is no mention of the final punctuation mark.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi><lb/>was published on 22 October 1926.<lb/>It seems probable that someone at Scribner, working on a form of proof,<lb/>introduced the question-mark. Grammatically the sentence is a rhetorical ques-<lb/>tion and does not require a question-mark. Still the mark was added, perhaps<lb/>as part of a house style being imposed on the text. This interpretation is sup-<lb/>ported by twelve other rhetorical questions in the novel, all of them occurring<lb/>in passages of dialogue, and all ending with periods in Hemingway’s manuscript<lb/>and setting-copy typescript. All twelve, like the final line of the novel, end with<lb/>question-marks in the first edition.<lb/>Some examples will be helpful. In Book One, chapter 3, Jake and Brett are<lb/>drinking at a café with friends. Brett becomes tipsy. “You’re wonderfully sober,”<lb/>says Jake to Brett. She answers: “Yes. Aren’t I. And when one’s with the crowd<lb/>I’m with, one can drink in such safety, too.” In both the manuscript and the<lb/>setting copy there is a period after “Aren’t I.” In the first edition, on page 22,<lb/><hi rend="sup">13</hi>. Commas and periods are consistently typed outside the quotation marks in the type-<lb/>script, suggesting that the typist at the typing service was British, or that the typists who worked<lb/>there were accustomed to using British styling. See figure 4. Some of the typescripts of short<lb/>stories that Fitzgerald wrote in Paris in the 1920s also have British spelling and accidentals.<lb/>Perhaps he and Hemingway, who were friends during those years, used the same typing service.<lb/><hi rend="sup">14</hi>. Letters, vol. 3, pp. 106, 109.<lb/><hi rend="sup">15</hi>. Hemingway’s letters to Perkins during the production and proofing of the novel are<lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, vol. 3, pp. 39-145.<lb/></p>
<pb n="343"/>
<figure>
<!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
<figDesc>figure 3. From final page of the manuscript, <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>.<lb/>Ernest Hemingway Collection, John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure>
<!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
<figDesc>figure 4. From final page of the setting copy, <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>. Papers of Ernest Heming-<lb/>way, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure>
<!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
<figDesc>figure 5. From final page of the first edition, <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>. Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1926.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="344"/>
<p>there is a question-mark: “Aren’t I?” Another example occurs near the end of the<lb/>
novel, in Book Two, chapter 17. Here Robert Cohn, who has had a brief affair<lb/>
with Brett, asks Jake to forgive him. “So long, Jake,” says Cohn. “You’ll shake<lb/>
hands, won’t you?” In the manuscript Jake answers: “Sure. Why not.” In the<lb/>
setting copy the punctuation is the same (though the period after “not” is typed<lb/>
outside the quotation marks). On page 202 of the first edition Jake says: “Sure.<lb/>
Why not?” These two examples are typical of the other rhetorical questions to<lb/>
which question-marks have been affixed between the setting copy and the first<lb/>
edition. One’s sense is that Hemingway, for these readings, wanted the characters<lb/>
to speak in a flat tone, without animation.<lb/></p>
<p>The matter is of some importance. As one reads dialogue in a text, one hears the<lb/>
rhythms and intonations of the spoken words by paying attention to the pointing, the<lb/>
accidentals. The voice of the character who is speaking rises and falls according to<lb/>
the punctuation. With the period at the end of the novel, Jake delivers his statement<lb/>
in a resigned tone. (“Isn’t it pretty to think so.”) This is consistent with his character<lb/>
and with the view he has come to take toward life. The question-mark, however,<lb/>
changes the way one hears the sentence. (“Isn’t it pretty to think so?”) Jake’s voice<lb/>
rises at the end, making his statement sound flippant. This is out of character for him.<lb/>
He is bitter but is careful not to let his bitterness show. The final line, spoken without<lb/>
emotion, is in keeping with his behavior elsewhere in the novel.<lb/></p>
<p>Which punctuation mark should an editor choose for an edition of <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also<lb/>
Rises</hi>? Here, as with <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, the editor must take a chance. How one<lb/>
hears the final line counts in the decision, as does one’s reading of Jake’s character.<lb/>
Documentary evidence, however, is a more reliable basis for editorial choice. The<lb/>
decision here seems straightforward. The period is present, in Hemingway’s hand,<lb/>
in the final line of the manuscript. The period is also present in the fair copy that<lb/>
Hemingway submitted to Scribner. For twelve other rhetorical questions the same<lb/>
thing happened: periods in manuscript and fair copy were replaced by question-<lb/>
marks in the first edition. The periods should be restored to the text.<lb/></p>
<p>Every edition of <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi> published between 1926 and 2020 has<lb/>
question-marks following the rhetorical questions. All of these editions end with:<lb/>
“Isn’t it pretty to think so?” In 2018 the Library of America persuaded Scribner<lb/>
and the Hemingway estate to allow inclusion of <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>, which was<lb/>
nearing the end of its copyright protection, in a volume of early writings by<lb/>
Hemingway. The texts were prepared by Robert W. Trogdon, who consulted the<lb/>
surviving manuscripts, typescripts, and proofs for the writings in the volume. In<lb/>
the Trogdon text of <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>, the periods at the ends of the rhetorical<lb/>
questions are restored, as are the three instances of “bulls have no balls.” The<lb/>
final line of this edition reads: “Isn’t it pretty to think so.”<hi rend="sup">16</hi><lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi> entered the public domain on 1 January 2022. Shortly<lb/>
thereafter, the Library of America published a paperback edition of the Trogdon<lb/>
text.<lb/></p>
<note place="foot" n="16">Hemingway, <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises &amp; Other Writings, 1918–1926</hi>, ed. Robert W. Trogdon<lb/>
(New York: Library of America, 2020). The emendations are recorded in the apparatus to<lb/>
this volume. The readings that involve the punctuation of rhetorical questions occur at 389.3,<lb/>
397.18, 401.22, 414.33, 432.24, 432.40, 437.30, 487.20, 506.4, 516.32, 527.34, 567.37, and 570.8 of<lb/>
the text.<lb/></note>
<pb n="345"/>
<p><lb/>text, ending with the period. This paperback includes a selection of Hemingway’s journalism and letters from 1925–1926.<hi rend="sup">17</hi><lb/>It is essential, after restoring a text, to make it available to readers in a reasonably priced edition.<lb/>This has happened for <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> and for <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>.<lb/>As we shall see, it has happened also for <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>.<lb/></p>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi></head>
<p><lb/><hi rend="dropcap">W</hi>illiam Faulkner’s eleventh novel, published on 19 January 1939, has a compli­cated textual history.<lb/>Faulkner wrote the novel under the title <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>.<hi rend="sup">18</hi> Random House, his publisher, changed the title to <hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi>.<lb/>The novel consists of two interwoven stories, in alternating chapters. The primary narrative, entitled “The Wild Palms,” is tragic; the secondary narrative, “Old Man,” is comic.<lb/>“The Wild Palms” is set in 1937. It tells the story of a woman and a man, Charlotte Rittenmeyer and Harry Wilbourne, who resolve to free themselves from the burdens and constraints of society.<lb/>Charlotte, a wife and mother, leaves her husband and two children; Harry, an unmarried medical student, abandons his studies and follows Charlotte in pursuit of what she conceives to be freedom.<lb/>Their first few months together go well, but their idyll cannot endure. Charlotte becomes pregnant, and Harry (at her urging) performs an abortion.<lb/>He botches the operation; Charlotte dies of hemorrhaging; Harry is sentenced to fifty years in prison.<lb/>He refuses to commit suicide and decides to live out his years in captivity. Harry resolves to keep Charlotte alive in memory.<lb/>The final line of “The Wild Palms,” in italicized interior monologue, gives his decision:<lb/><hi rend="italic">“Between grief and nothing I will take grief.”</hi><lb/></p>
<p><lb/>The secondary story, “Old Man,” is a comic fable. The characters have no names: the protagonist is called “the tall convict,” and the woman is simply “the woman” or “she.”<lb/>“Old Man” is set during the severe flooding of the Mississippi River in 1927.<lb/>The tall convict has been temporarily released from prison in order to rescue people stranded by the flood.<lb/>He takes a skiff and paddle and sets out on the river. He finds a pregnant woman clinging to a tree and helps her into the boat.<lb/>For the remainder of “Old Man,” he and she are tossed about on the powerful river, coming to rest briefly on a small island where, with his assistance, she gives birth.<lb/>The tall convict performs heroically during his period of freedom.<lb/>He saves the woman and brings her and the baby to dry land.<lb/>Throughout the narrative, however, he seems terrified of the woman and of what she represents.<lb/>His only desire is to return to captivity. He fears the disorder and messiness of life and prefers the regularity of imprisonment; he has no desire to complicate his existence with women, and certainly not with sex or childbirth.<lb/>In Faulkner’s manuscript and in the setting-copy typescript, which he typed, “Old Man” ends<lb/></p>
<note n="17" place="foot"><lb/>Hemingway, <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises: The Library of America Corrected Text</hi>, ed. Robert W. Trogdon (New&amp;nbsp;York: Library of America, 2022).</note>
<note n="18" place="foot"><lb/>The title is an allusion to Psalms&amp;nbsp;137: “By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down, yea, we wept, when we remembered Zion.” Images and wording from this psalm, which concerns captivity and freedom, appear throughout Faulkner’s novel.</note>
<pb n="346"/>
<figure>
  <figDesc>figure 6. From final page of the manuscript, <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>.<lb/>Papers of William Faulkner, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<figure>
  <figDesc>figure 7. From final page of the setting copy, <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>.<lb/>Papers of William Faulkner, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<p>with the convict back in prison (see figures 6 and 7). Another ten years have been <lb/>added to his sentence. He seems content, even pleased, with his fate. When asked <lb/>by another inmate whether he will miss the company of women, his reply (the <lb/>last line of the novel) is quite different from Harry’s last line:<lb/>“Women, shit,” the tall convict said.<lb/>Faulkner began composing “The Wild Palms” and “Old Man” as two sepa-<lb/>rate stories but soon realized that the narratives were related to each other, not <lb/>by plot and character but by theme and image. Both stories are about freedom <lb/>versus imprisonment, the disorder of life versus the security of incarceration. <lb/>Faulkner now began writing the novel in alternating stints, bringing “The Wild <lb/>Palms” to a point of high intensity, then shifting to the comedy of “Old Man,” <lb/>then returning to the drama of “The Wild Palms,” and onward until the end of <lb/></p>
<pb n="347"/>
<p>the novel. The manuscript, composed between September 1937 and June 1938,<lb/>
survives among Faulkner’s papers at the Small Special Collections Library. The<lb/>
pagination of the document confirms that Faulkner wrote the two stories in al-<lb/>
ternating chapters, composing a chapter of one and then a chapter of the other.<lb/>
He did not write “The Wild Palms” in its entirety, then write “Old Man,” and<lb/>
then shuffle the chapters. This structural experimentation was characteristic of<lb/>
Faulkner’s work from the late 1920s until the early 1940s, a period that saw pub-<lb/>
lication of <hi rend="italic">The Sound and the Fury</hi> (1929), <hi rend="italic">As I Lay Dying</hi> (1930), <hi rend="italic">Absalom, Absalom!</hi><lb/>
(1936), <hi rend="italic">The Hamlet</hi> (1940), and <hi rend="italic">Go Down, Moses</hi> (1942)—all of which take liberties<lb/>
with conventional narrative structure.<lb/></p>

<p>Faulkner’s publisher, however, seems not to have understood what he was<lb/>
doing. Saxe Commins, Faulkner’s editor at Random House, changed the title of<lb/>
the novel from <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>, an inclusive title, to <hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi>,<lb/>
the title of the primary story. The change in title, made over Faulkner’s objec-<lb/>
tions, caused confusion for many years after publication. Scholars and critics did<lb/>
not recognize <hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi> as a novel. The history of subsequent editions did<lb/>
not help matters. In 1948 both “The Wild Palms” and “Old Man” were issued<lb/>
separately, in individual paperback volumes.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> In a 1954 paperback the two nar-<lb/>
ratives were published together but one after the other, with the full text of “The<lb/>
Wild Palms” appearing first, followed by “Old Man” in its entirety.<hi rend="sup">20</hi><lb/></p>

<p>The novel was also bowdlerized. Faulkner objected to this sanitizing but was<lb/>
overruled.<hi rend="sup">21</hi> The setting-copy typescript, like the manuscript, is among Faulkner’s<lb/>
papers at the Small Special Collections Library.<hi rend="sup">22</hi> On the typescript Faulkner’s<lb/>
editor has marked out the word “shit.” He has preserved Faulkner’s comma and<lb/>
has substituted four ellipsis points for the profane word. Proofs for the book do<lb/>
not survive, but further changes in the final line must have occurred there. On<lb/>
page&amp;nbsp;339 of the first edition, the final page of “Old Man” and of the novel, the<lb/>
comma and the ellipsis points have been replaced by an open two-em dash and<lb/>
an exclamation point (see figure&amp;nbsp;8). The final line now reads:<lb/></p>

<p>“Women —— !” the tall convict said.<lb/></p>

<p>19.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi> (New&amp;nbsp;York: New&amp;nbsp;American Library, 1948); <hi rend="italic">The Old Man</hi> (New&amp;nbsp;York:<lb/>
New&amp;nbsp;American Library, 1948). For these and later editions, the word “The” was added to the<lb/>
title of “Old Man.”<lb/></p>

<p>20.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms and The Old Man</hi> (New&amp;nbsp;York: New&amp;nbsp;American Library, 1954).<lb/></p>

<p>21.&amp;nbsp;Faulkner had little leverage with his publisher in 1939. Random House was the fifth<lb/>
imprint to publish his work and was carrying him as a <hi rend="italic">succès d’estime</hi>. His first book with Random<lb/>
House, <hi rend="italic">Absalom, Absalom!</hi>, had not sold well; <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>, with another biblical title,<lb/>
was not likely to do better—hence, presumably, the change in title. In 1939 Faulkner was best<lb/>
known as the author of <hi rend="italic">Sanctuary</hi> (1931), a scandalous novel about a young woman who is raped<lb/>
with a corn cob. It is not surprising that the publisher bowdlerized <hi rend="italic">The Wild Palms</hi>. The sanitiz-<lb/>
ing, however, was incomplete: the words “pricks” and “cunts” appear on p.&amp;nbsp;52 of the first edition,<lb/>
and “Shit!” appears on p.&amp;nbsp;101. Later, after he had won the Nobel Prize in 1949, Faulkner swung<lb/>
more weight at Random House, and the heavy editing of his texts ceased.<lb/></p>

<p>22.&amp;nbsp;Both the manuscript and the setting-copy typescript of the novel have been published<lb/>
in facsimile in <hi rend="italic">William Faulkner Manuscripts</hi>, vol.&amp;nbsp;14, parts&amp;nbsp;1 and&amp;nbsp;2, ed.&amp;nbsp;Thomas&amp;nbsp;L.&amp;nbsp;McHaney<lb/>
(New&amp;nbsp;York and London: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1986).<lb/></p>
<pb n="348"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he open dash (i.e., preceded and followed by half-spaces) was presumably <lb/>
meant to stand for the word “shit.” Punctuation is often used in printed texts as <lb/>
a substitute for profanity, but the two-em dash here, with the exclamation point, <lb/>
does not suggest a profane word. The line instead conveys mild exasperation, or <lb/>
perhaps longing.<lb/></p>

<figure>
  <head>figure 8.</head>
  <figDesc>From final page of the first edition, The Wild Palms. Random House, 1939.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>

<p>Further change occurred in subsequent typesettings. In the Viking Portable <lb/>
Faulkner (1946), the half-spaces have been removed.<lb/>
“Women——!” the tall convict said.<lb/></p>

<p>The French translator, confused, rendered the line this way in 1952:<lb/>
— Ah ! Les femmes ! » dit le grand forçat.<hi rend="sup">23</hi><lb/></p>

<p>In the New American Library edition of 1954, the long dash becomes a closed <lb/>
one-em dash, with the exclamation point retained:<lb/>
“Women—!” the tall convict said.<lb/></p>

<p>The Vintage paperback of 1962 is a slight improvement, with three hyphens and <lb/>
the letter “t” plus the exclamation point. It reads:<lb/>
“Women---t!” the tall convict said.<lb/></p>

<p>These textual discoveries were noted first by Thomas L. McHaney in his dis-<lb/>
sertation in 1968.<hi rend="sup">24</hi> Twenty-two years later, McHaney and Noel Polk, with the <lb/>
permission of Faulkner’s literary estate, collaborated on a corrected text of the <lb/>
novel that was published by the Library of America. Here the title of Faulkner’s <lb/>
work is given as If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem [The Wild Palms].<hi rend="sup">25</hi> On the last page of <lb/>
this edition the final line has been restored. (“Women, shit,” the tall convict said.) <lb/>
Random House adopted this text, and indeed all of the corrected texts produced <lb/></p>

<p><hi rend="sup">23</hi>. Les Palmiers sauvages (Paris: Gallimard, 1952).<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">24</hi>. McHaney, “William Faulkner’s The Wild Palms: A Textual and Critical Study.” Diss. University of South Carolina, 1968. See especially Appendix I, “The Text,” pp. 252-65.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">25</hi>. In the volume William Faulkner, Novels 1936–1940 (1990): 493-726.<lb/></p>
<pb n="349"/>by Polk for the Library of America, in its subsequent editions of Faulkner’s nov-<lb/>els. Today, all copies published of <hi rend="italic">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</hi>, which is still under<lb/>copyright protection, end with the restored line. One hopes that the corrections<lb/>will be carried forward in editions issued after the novel enters the public domain<lb/>in 2035.<lb/>All editors hope to find significant variants in important works of literature. Edi-<lb/>tors want to discover variants that will alter meaning, or at least cause teach-<lb/>ers and critics to rethink their ideas about interpretation. This is probably a<lb/>legacy of the New Criticism, with its emphasis on close reading. The New Critics<lb/>taught that each word carries meaning, as does each punctuation mark, and that<lb/>the interpretation of a literary work can turn on a single sentence. Perhaps the<lb/>New Critics were right. Some sentences in fiction bring immediately to mind the<lb/>works in which they appear. (“Mr. Holmes, they were the footprints of a gigantic<lb/>hound!”) Some capture a central image. (“The red sun was pasted in the sky like<lb/>a wafer.”) Some sentences prepare the work for its conclusion. (“Marlow ceased,<lb/>and sat apart, indistinct and silent, in the pose of a meditating Buddha.”) Some<lb/>sentences tie together all that has come before. (“Reader, I married him.”) Other<lb/>sentences, appearing at the very end of a work, encapsulate its meaning. (“He<lb/>loved Big Brother.”)<lb/>The discovery of pivotal variants is rare. Many excellent scholarly editions<lb/>present texts that have been emended throughout, but the emendations are not<lb/>especially significant. Documentary or “versionist” editions usually offer texts<lb/>that are identical to, or not very different from, earlier texts. Facsimile editions<lb/>typically list emendations at the foot of the page or in an apparatus. These edi-<lb/>tions can do many good things: they can provide narratives of composition and<lb/>revision, trace the textual history of the work, and provide useful historical an-<lb/>notations. Time schemes are sometimes straightened out; the author’s accidentals<lb/>are reinstated; misspellings and other demonstrable errors are corrected. These<lb/>are valuable services, but they do not provide a definitive response, if there is one,<lb/>to the notion that scholarly editing is essentially clerical work. All editors have<lb/>heard this sort of thing. Why should an editor undertake the considerable labor<lb/>of a full-dress edition if the interpretation of the work is to remain unchanged?<lb/>Important variants might indeed turn up in the collations, but an editor usually<lb/>does not know this when beginning a project. The editor must proceed on faith.<lb/>In the case of these three final sentences, however, we do have variants of<lb/>consequence. Each of these readings falls at the very end of its novel, and each<lb/>involves punctuation. These are not minor works; they are important novels,<lb/>taught in classrooms and interpreted by critics. How these changes came about—<lb/>from dash to period, period to question-mark, profane word to long dash—these<lb/>stories can be included in lectures and discussed with students, most of whom<lb/>probably think that a literary work springs immaculate from its creator’s brow.<lb/>With a dash at the end of <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi>, the journey of its hero is just begin-<lb/>ning. With a period at the end of <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi>, the narrator takes a bleak<lb/>but realistic view of his future. And with the word “shit” at the end of <hi rend="italic">If I Forget<lb/>Thee, Jerusalem</hi>, the tall convict’s rejection of women, and of life, is made clear.
<pb n="350"/>
<pb n="351"/>
<head>Notes on Contributors</head><lb/>
<p>G. Thomas Tanselle is a former president of the Bibliographical Society of the<lb/>
University of Virginia, and his most recent book, published by the Society, is <hi rend="italic">Books in My Life</hi>.<lb/>
The present volume of <hi rend="italic">Studies</hi> is the forty‑sixth consecutive one<lb/>
to which he has contributed. In 2015 he was awarded the Gold Medal of the<lb/>
Bibliographical Society in England.</p>
<p>John Bidwell is a curator emeritus at the Morgan Library &amp; Museum.</p><lb/>
<p>Sam Lemley is curator of special collections at Carnegie Mellon University Librar‑<lb/>
ies. He is the editor of <hi rend="italic">The Four Shakespeare Folios, 1623–2023: Copy, Print, Paper,<lb/>
Type</hi> (Penn State Series in the History of the Book). His work has appeared in<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Library</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century<lb/>
Studies</hi>, and other journals.</p>
<p>Neal D. Curtis earned his MA from The University of Virginia, where he also di-<lb/>
rected the UVA Alderman Library Card Catalog Preservation Project. While at<lb/>
the University of Virginia, he held fellowships from the Bibliographical Society of<lb/>
UVA, Yale University’s Lewis Walpole Library, and Rare Book School, and he was<lb/>
named RBS’s William Reese Fellow in 2020. He is now Director of Implementation<lb/>
at Citeline, a global provider of R&amp;D intelligence to the pharmaceutical industry.</p>
<p>Madeline Zehnder is a postdoctoral researcher at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.<lb/>
Her work on nineteenth-century American literature and culture has appeared<lb/>
in publications including <hi rend="italic">Book History</hi>, <hi rend="italic">New Literary History</hi>, <hi rend="italic">American<lb/>
Literature</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">ALH</hi>.</p>
<p>Nora C. Benedict is an Associate Professor in Spanish and Digital Humanities at<lb/>
the University of Georgia. Her research centers on the Latin American publish-<lb/>
ing industry. She is the author of <hi rend="italic">Borges and the Literary Marketplace: How<lb/>
Editorial Practices Shaped Cosmopolitan Reading</hi> (Yale UP, 2021) and co-editor of<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Jorge Luis Borges</hi> (Oxford, 2024).</p>
<p>James McLaverty is emeritus professor of textual criticism at the University of<lb/>
Keele. He is the author of <hi rend="italic">Pope, Print, and Meaning</hi> (2001) and saw David Foxon’s<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade</hi> (1991) and David Fleeman’s<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">A Bibliography of the Works of Samuel Johnson</hi> (2000) into print.</p>
<p>John Considine taught English at the University of Alberta until 2021. <hi rend="italic">Sixteenth-Century<lb/>
English Dictionaries</hi>, the first volume of his <hi rend="italic">Dictionaries in the English-Speaking<lb/>
World, 1500–1800</hi>, was published by OUP in 2022, and <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge Handbook<lb/>
of the Dictionary</hi> (2024) includes his chapters “Dictionaries in Book History” and<lb/>
“Dictionaries and Intellectual History”.</p>
<p>Stephen Clarke is a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries and an Honorary Research<lb/>
Fellow of the University of Liverpool. He is Chairman of Dr Johnson’s House<lb/>
Trust and of the Beckford Society and Secretary to the Board of Managers of the<lb/>
Lewis Walpole Library at Yale University, and was a trustee of Strawberry Hill.</p>
</div>