<div type="section" n="4">
  <head>“Capítulo de una Novela en Prensa”: Teaser Chapters and Marketing Strategies in Victoria Ocampo’s Sur</head>
<pb n="174"/>
<p>journal and consider why certain titles might have been promoted more than<lb/>
others. In this way, I show how Ocampo’s decision to establish this publishing<lb/>
house was not merely to finance her literary journal, but rather a part of her<lb/>
business plan and overarching mission to introduce international writers to<lb/>
Latin American readers.<lb/></p>
<head>From Serial Publication<lb/>to Teaser Chapter</head>
<p>Serial publications— or serialized publications—appear frequently throughout<lb/>
the nineteenth century.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> “Serialization,” in the words of Catherine Delafield,<lb/>
“was the process by which many nineteenth-century novels were published prior<lb/>
to their appearance in discrete volume form.”<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Certain nineteenth-century au-<lb/>
thors even began to construct chapters of a particular style and length to fit<lb/>
within the parameters of a serial publication. In England, Charles Dickens ex-<lb/>
pertly used this method for the publication of many of his novels and is perhaps<lb/>
its best-known practitioner. In America, according to Michael Lund, “the sheer<lb/>
number of significant authors and works first appearing in part from 1850 to<lb/>
1900 suggest that a central mode of the American literary tradition was the se-<lb/>
rial form, the continuing story.”<hi rend="sup">7</hi> The serial publication format also was popu-<lb/>
lar in France (<hi rend="italic">feuilleton</hi>) and Spain (<hi rend="italic">folletín</hi>) during the nineteenth century,<hi rend="sup">8</hi> and<lb/>
examples cropped up in Russia as well with the works of Dostoyevsky and Tol-<lb/>
stoy. Instances of serial publications, such as Edith Wharton’s <hi rend="italic">The House of Mirth</hi><lb/>
(<hi rend="italic">Scribner’s Magazine</hi>, 1905), James Joyce’s <hi rend="italic">A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</hi><lb/>
(<hi rend="italic">Egoist</hi>, 1914–15), and Ernest Hemingway’s <hi rend="italic">A Farewell to Arms</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Scribner’s Magazine</hi>,<lb/>
1929) continued to appear in later decades, but in the early part of the twentieth<lb/></p>
<note place="foot">
<p>5.<lb/>While serial publications were most prominent in the nineteenth century, they have<lb/>
much earlier origins: “Serial fiction was not a Victorian invention. As R. M. Wiles has shown,<lb/>
already by the second quarter of the eighteenth century ‘number books, independently is-<lb/>
sued in weekly or month parts, wrapped in blue paper covers, had become a common com-<lb/>
modity in the publishing business’ (<hi rend="italic">Serial</hi>, 75). . . . By 1750 works thus published in fascicles<lb/>
already totaled several hundred and were occasionally issued in editions of as many as two or<lb/>
three thousand copies. Among them were both original and reprinted works, translated texts<lb/>
as well as those in the vernacular, and, among a wide variety of other genres, a number of<lb/>
examples of prose fiction, including Cervantes, Defoe, and imitations of Richardson such as<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Pamela in High Life</hi>.” Graham Law, <hi rend="italic">Serializing Fiction in the Victorian Press</hi> (London: Palgrave,<lb/>
2000), 3.<lb/></p>
<p>6.<lb/>Catherine Delafield, <hi rend="italic">Serialization and the Novel in Mid-Victorian Magazines</hi> (New York: Routledge, 2015), 1.<lb/></p>
<p>7.<lb/>Michael Lund, <hi rend="italic">America’s Continuing Story: An Introduction to Serial Fiction, 1850–1900</hi> (Detroit, MI: Wayne State University Press, 1993), 21–22.<lb/></p>
<p>8.<lb/>Alexandre Dumas’s <hi rend="italic">The Count of Monte Cristo</hi> (1844–45) and Gustave Flaubert’s <hi rend="italic">Madame Bovary</hi> (1856) originally appeared as serial publications in magazines in France. Many of the works of Benito Pérez Galdós also appeared in serial format in Spain. See Wright for more details on the development of the serial novel throughout Spain and Mexico.<lb/></p>
</note>
<pb n="175"/>
<p>century the use of this print format declined alongside the advent of new forms <lb/>of media, namely radio and television.<hi rend="sup">9</hi><lb/>With this background of serialized publications in mind, I argue that Ocampo’s literary journal <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> in the late 1930s presented a new form that borrowed <lb/>certain aspects of serialized publications with an eye toward marketing. While <lb/>the teaser chapters that Ocampo presented to readers have their roots in earlier <lb/>serial publications, her excerpts were slightly different. Unlike serialized publica-<lb/>tions that printed an entire work in installments, or fascicles, the teaser chapter <lb/>is exactly what its name describes: a single chapter (or, at times, two) that aimed <lb/>to excite readers about a forthcoming book and, by proxy, encouraged them to <lb/>buy the book once it was released. In a sense, these teaser chapters throughout <lb/>the pages of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> are a type of predecessor for the sample chapters—or “sneak <lb/>peaks” of forthcoming works—that appear at the end of many of today’s popular <lb/>novels.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> That is to say, these teaser chapters are a hybrid of a serialized install-<lb/>ment publication and a sample of forthcoming works. Readers can get a taste for <lb/>certain books through a periodical publication (like serial publications), but they <lb/>must purchase the book to read it in its entirety (like sample chapters at the end of <lb/>contemporary novels). As I will show in the following sections, the teaser chapters <lb/>that Ocampo appears to have included strategically in her literary journal from <lb/>a variety of forthcoming Editorial Sur works align with her mission to encourage <lb/>a broader readership while also boosting sales.</p>
<head>Sampling Editorial <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi></head><lb/>
<p>Before diving into the teaser chapters in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> I want to reflect briefly on the dif-<lb/>ferences between marketing and propaganda. Both seek to persuade people, but <lb/>whereas marketing attempts to sell goods or services, propaganda tries to pro-<lb/>mote a political cause or point of view. Ocampo certainly was concerned with <lb/>the marketing strategies of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> and Editorial Sur. The impetus behind those <lb/>projects was her drive to promote important works of literature. In a footnote to <lb/>the introduction of a special quadruple issue of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> dedicated to English litera-<lb/>ture she made clear how she had helped to bring this about: “En 1933, antes de <lb/>la fiebre editorial argentina, SUR publicó las primeras traducciones de Aldous <hi rend="italic">Huxley</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Contrapunto</hi>), D. H. Lawrence (<hi rend="italic">Canguro</hi>), Virginia Woolf (<hi rend="italic">Un Cuarto Propio</hi>…</p>
<note place="foot">9. Fitzgerald’s <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> (1920) and <hi rend="italic">The Beautiful and Damned</hi> (1922) present an-<lb/>other kind of serialization, yet this example is that in which the periodical publication in install-<lb/>ments comes after the publication of the work as a single volume (<hi rend="italic">Chicago Herald and Examiner</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Atlanta Georgian</hi>, 1921; <hi rend="italic">The Washington Herald</hi>, 1922), which suggests an even greater marketing <lb/>strategy since these second serializations tend to appear after large sales of the single-volume <lb/>work (West III).</note>
<note place="foot">10. A number of recent publishing manuals encourage authors to include sample chapters <lb/>for their forthcoming or already published books in their back matter, especially if the book is <lb/>part of a larger series (Coker; Crayton; Lynch). I should note, however, that I have yet to see <lb/>an example of this publishing phenomenon in Spanish-language books.</note>
<pb n="176"/>
<p>y <hi rend="italic">Orlando</hi>) y James Joyce (<hi rend="italic">Desterrados</hi>).”<hi rend="sup">11</hi> Ocampo’s decision to include in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi><lb/>
various promotional materials like teaser chapters from forthcoming Editorial<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> titles signals a logical approach to introducing Latin American readers to<lb/>
international authors and to selling her editions of their works.<lb/></p>
<p>The range of writers Ocampo published was itself evidence that she was not<lb/>
attempting to promote a narrow party line. Broadly speaking, throughout her<lb/>
literary journal she strived to maintain a neutral stance that was “outside poli-<lb/>
tics,” especially in light of the censorship measures that Perón instituted during<lb/>
his dictatorship.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> This neutral position could itself be viewed as political, but<lb/>
throughout a variety of journal issues Ocampo explicitly reiterated her hostility<lb/>
to partisan bias. For instance, in the same introduction to the quadruple issue<lb/>
of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>, Ocampo discusses the monstrous qualities of propaganda: “En este siglo<lb/>
la Propaganda devora al hombre como un nuevo dios que ni siquiera trata de<lb/>
disimular que es un monstruo. Vivimos, dice C. Day Lewis, en un ‘pandemonio<lb/>
de slogans, de himnos nacionales, de titulares, de altoparlantes, de manifiestos,<lb/>
de coimas, de chismes desatinados e ideales altamente explosivos.’”<hi rend="sup">13</hi> She con-<lb/>
tinues her diatribe by stating that <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> is against any type of political propaganda<lb/>
and, instead, simply wishes to provide its readers with examples of outstanding<lb/>
literature: “En atmósferas de pandemonio ni poetas, ni artistas verdaderos pu-<lb/>
eden respirar. No ha sido, ni será la atmósfera de nuestra revista. Y por eso este<lb/>
número especial de <hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> no es un número de propaganda. . . . Sólo se propone<lb/>
dar a conocer algunos nuevos valores.”<hi rend="sup">14</hi><lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Editorial Sur</hi> published forty-three books between the years 1936 and 1971<lb/>
that have teaser chapters in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> (table 1).<hi rend="sup">15</hi> These pre-publication texts found<lb/>
throughout the pages of Ocampo’s literary journal <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> were not reserved for<lb/>
one specific genre or type of literature, but rather reflected virtually every genre<lb/>
published by <hi rend="italic">Editorial Sur</hi> during its decades-long run. More specifically, there<lb/>
were excerpts of poetry, theater, novels, essays, short stories, and even memoirs<lb/>
in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> that were later included in full-length books published by <hi rend="italic">Editorial Sur</hi>.<hi rend="sup">16</hi><lb/></p>
<note n="11" place="foot"><lb/>“In 1933, before the frenzy of Argentine publishing, <hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> published the first transla-<lb/>
tions of Aldous Huxley (<hi rend="italic">Point Counter Point</hi>), D.&amp;nbsp;H. Lawrence (<hi rend="italic">Kangaroo</hi>), Virginia Woolf (<hi rend="italic">A Room<lb/>
of One’s Own</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Orlando</hi>), and James Joyce (<hi rend="italic">Exiles</hi>).”<lb/></note>
<note n="12" place="foot"><lb/>John King, “Towards a Reading of the Argentine Literary Magazine <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Latin Ameri-<lb/>
can Research Review</hi> 16, no.&amp;nbsp;2 (1981): 64.<lb/></note>
<note n="13" place="foot"><lb/>“In this century, Propaganda devours man like a new God who does not even try to<lb/>
hide the fact that he is a monster. We live, as C.&amp;nbsp;Day Lewis says, in a ‘pandemonium of slogans,<lb/>
national anthems, headlines, loudspeakers, manifestos, bribes, misguided rumors, and highly<lb/>
explosive ideals.” Victoria Ocampo, “Introducción,” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 153 (1947): 11.<lb/></note>
<note n="14" place="foot"><lb/>“In atmospheres of pandemonium, neither poets nor true artists can breathe. This has<lb/>
not been nor will it be the atmosphere of our journal. And for that reason, this special issue of<lb/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> is not an issue of propaganda. . . . It only aims to make a few new (literary) values known.”<lb/>
Ocampo, “Introducción,” 11.<lb/></note>
<note n="15" place="foot"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Editorial Sur</hi> published a total of 345 books during this time span, which means that<lb/>
12.5% of their titles were excerpted as teaser chapters in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>. That said, this percentage might<lb/>
actually be slightly higher given that at least one of the titles with teaser chapters in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> was re-<lb/>
published under a new title: Albert Camus, <hi rend="italic">Bodas</hi> [1957]; Albert Camus, <hi rend="italic">El verano / Bodas</hi> [1970].<lb/></note>
<note n="16" place="foot"><lb/>The following is the specific breakdown of each of the genres represented in these<lb/>
teaser chapters: Novel (37%), Essay (26%), Memoir (14%), Short Stories (9%), Poetry (9%),<lb/>
and Theater (5%).<lb/></note>
<pb n="177"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">I</hi>n essence, these teaser chapters showcased the breadth and depth of material<lb/>
that this publishing firm produced. What is more, the authors who penned these<lb/>
diverse works hailed from around the globe (England, France, Argentina, Italy,<lb/>
Chile, Russia, Spain, the United States,<hi rend="sup">17</hi> Ireland, and Germany). However, the<lb/>
names of virtually all the authors of these sample chapters would have been<lb/>
known to readers, especially for the educated and elite consumers of Sur. For<lb/>
instance, a few of the authors whose sampled works appeared in these issues<lb/>
included James Joyce, Virginia Woolf, Aldous Huxley, George Orwell, Gabriela<lb/>
Mistral, Albert Camus, and T. E. Lawrence, as well as Victoria Ocampo herself.<lb/>
When viewed in tandem with the numerous ads that filled the opening and clos-<lb/>
ing pages of each issue of the literary journal Sur, these teaser chapters reveal<lb/>
one potential way in which Ocampo might have marketed select works as a part<lb/>
of her more general mission to promote certain authors for her Latin American<lb/>
readers.<hi rend="sup">18</hi><lb/>
While Ocampo’s literary journal tended to include only one pre-publication<lb/>
chapter from each of these books, there were instances in which several chap-<lb/>
ters—or even entire works—appeared in Sur prior to the book publication with<lb/>
Editorial Sur. Consider, for instance, the following titles that had at least two<lb/>
chapters published in Sur prior to their releases as single-volume works with Edi-<lb/>
torial Sur: André Gide’s Perséphone (1936), Eduardo Mallea’s La ciudad junto al río<lb/>
inmóvil (1936), Virginia Woolf’s Un cuarto propio (1936), Aldous Huxley’s Con los<lb/>
esclavos en la noria (1937), Victoria Ocampo’s Virginia Woolf, Orlando y Cía<lb/>
(1938), and Silvina Ocampo’s Autobiografía de Irene (1948).<hi rend="sup">19</hi> Multiple poems from Gabri-<lb/>
ela Mistral’s Tala (1938) as well as Eduardo González Lanuza’s La degollación de los<lb/>
inocentes (1938) and Transitable cristal (1943) also appeared in the pages of Sur prior<lb/>
to their official release with Editorial Sur. It is telling that early on multiple teaser<lb/>
chapters from Editorial Sur books—if not the entire works—appeared in Sur. In<lb/>
essence, these early pre-publication chapters highlight the residual influence of<lb/>
serial publications. The only two books that were published in an entirely serial-<lb/>
ized format in Sur prior to their release with Editorial Sur were Woolf’s Un cuarto<lb/>
propio and Gide’s Perséphone.<hi rend="sup">20</hi> These two works are the second and third Editorial<lb/>
Sur works that were pre-published in Sur, respectively, which further stresses the<lb/>
</p>
<p>17. The only American writer, Christopher Isherwood, was born in the United Kingdom<lb/>
in 1904, but he became a United States citizen in 1946 and lived in California until his death<lb/>
in 1986.<lb/>
</p>
<p>18. Alongside the promotional materials for Editorial Sur editions and articles in forth-<lb/>
coming issues of Sur, the majority of advertisements found in the opening and closing pages<lb/>
of Ocampo’s literary journal throughout the 1930s and 1940s were for printers, bookstores, or<lb/>
other publishing houses in Buenos Aires.<lb/>
</p>
<p>19. Ocampo included three chapters from T. E. Lawrence’s Siete pilares de la sabiduría in<lb/>
Sur (120 [October 1944]), but these appeared the month after the entire book was released with<lb/>
Editorial Sur (September 1944).<lb/>
</p>
<p>20. I note in another work that this Spanish-language translation of Gide’s work with<lb/>
Editorial Sur was most likely “a type of reverse marketing to attract potential [buyers] by<lb/>
giving them access to a (successful) sample of the type of material that they publish” since, in<lb/>
addition to appearing in Sur in its entirety, it was distributed free of charge in book form (Nora<lb/>
Benedict, Borges and the Literary Marketplace: How Editorial Practices Shaped Cosmopolitan Reading.<lb/>
[New Haven: Yale University Press, 2021], 276).<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="178"/>
<head>Table 1.<lb/>Editorial Sur teaser chapters in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>, arranged by book publication date (1936–71)</head><lb/>
Author<lb/>Work<lb/>Publication date<lb/>Pre-publication in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi><lb/>
Eduardo Mallea<lb/>La ciudad junto al río inmóvil<lb/>1936<lb/>#2 (1931; pp. 86–131); #9 (1934; pp. 69–113)<lb/>
Virginia Woolf<lb/>Un cuarto propio<lb/>1936<lb/>#15 (1935; pp. 7–29); #16 (1936; pp. 25–58); #17 (1936; pp. 41–61); #18 (1936; pp. 46–81)<lb/>
André Gide<lb/>Perséphone<lb/>1936<lb/>#19 (1936; pp. 8–53)<lb/>
Aldous Huxley<lb/>¿Cómo lo resuelve usted? El problema de la paz constructiva<lb/>1936<lb/>#22 (1936; pp. 7–44)<lb/>
Aldous Huxley<lb/>Con los esclavos en la noria<lb/>1937<lb/>#29 (1937; pp. 47–54); #30 (1937; pp. 28–48)<lb/>
James Joyce<lb/>Desterrados<lb/>1937<lb/>#35 (1937; pp. 68–86)<lb/>
Conrado Nalé Roxlo<lb/>Claro desvelo<lb/>1937<lb/>#39 (1937; pp. 63–64)<lb/>
Victoria Ocampo<lb/>Virginia Woolf, Orlando y Cía<lb/>1938<lb/>#35 (1937; pp. 10–67)<lb/>
Ramón Fernández<lb/>¿Es humano el hombre?<lb/>1938<lb/>#41 (1938; pp. 42–50)<lb/>
Gabriela Mistral<lb/>Tala<lb/>1938<lb/>#38 (1937; pp. 38–40); #42 (1938; pp. 20–26)<lb/>
Victoria Ocampo<lb/>Emily Brontë. Terra Incognita<lb/>1938<lb/>#45 (1938; pp. 7–51)<lb/>
Emily Brontë<lb/>Cumbres borrascosas<lb/>1938<lb/>#45 (1938; pp. 7–51)<lb/>
Virginia Woolf<lb/>Al faro<lb/>1938<lb/>#43 (1938; pp. 7–30)<lb/>
Eduardo González Lanuza<lb/>La degollación de los inocentes<lb/>1938<lb/>#29 (1937; pp. 55–57); #33 (1937; pp. 78–80)<lb/>
León Chestov<lb/>Las revelaciones de la muerte<lb/>1938<lb/>#51 (1938; pp. 38–49)<lb/>
H. Bustos Domecq<lb/>Seis problemas de don Isidro Parodi<lb/>1942<lb/>#88 (1942; pp. 36–52)<lb/>
<pb n="179"/>
<p>Eduardo González Lanuza<lb/>Transitable cristal 1943<lb/>#51 (1938; pp. 50–51); #71 (1940; p. 27); #75 (1940; p. 107); #84 (1941; pp. 7–11); #100 (1943; p. 44); #101 (1943; pp. 7–12)<lb/>José Bianco<lb/>Las ratas 1943 #109 (1943; pp. 37–59)<lb/>T. E. Lawrence<lb/>Los siete pilares de la sabiduría 1944 #120 (1944; pp. 35–54)<lb/>Victoria Kent<lb/>Cuatro años en París (1940–1944) 1947 #150 (1947; pp. 32–55)<lb/>Albert Camus<lb/>La peste 1948 #147–149 (1947; pp. 211–221)<lb/>George Orwell<lb/>Ensayos críticos 1948 #153–156 (1947; pp. 129–150)<lb/>Adolfo Bioy Casares<lb/>La trama celeste 1948 #116 (1944; pp. 35–69)<lb/>Silvina Ocampo<lb/>Autobiografía de Irene 1948 #117 (1944; pp. 12–29); #164–165 (1948; pp. 9–34); #166 (1948; pp. 61–85); #167 (1948; pp. 32–49)<lb/>Christopher Isherwood<lb/>Adiós a Berlín 1948 #153–156 (1947; pp. 256–281)<lb/>Cyril Connolly<lb/>La tumba sin sosiego 1949 #153–156 (1947; pp. 95–128)<lb/>Juan Goyanarte<lb/>Lunes de carnaval 1952 #217–218 (1952; pp. 80–100)<lb/>Albert Camus<lb/>Bodas 1953 #211–212 (1952; pp. 24–41)<lb/>Juan Goyanarte<lb/>La quemazón 1953 #224 (1953; pp. 81–118)<lb/>Joseph Jean Lanza del Vasto<lb/>Peregrinación a las fuentes 1954 #161 (1948; pp. 22–97)<lb/>T. E. Lawrence<lb/>El troquel 1955 #153–156 (1947; pp. 247–251); #197 (1951; pp. 4–18)<lb/>Joseph Jean Lanza del Vasto<lb/>Vinoba o la nueva peregrinación 1955 #233 (1955; pp. 4–25)<lb/>H. A. Murena<lb/>La fatalidad de los cuerpos 1955 #236 (1955; pp. 9–30)<lb/>Alexandre Arnoux<lb/>La cifra 1955 #238 (1956; pp. 87–90)</p>
<pb n="180"/>
<head>Table 1.<lb/>(Continued)</head>
<p>Author	Work	Publication date	Pre-publication in Sur<lb/>
Samuel Beckett	Malone muere	1958	#255 (1958; pp. 4–13)<lb/>
Silvina Ocampo	La furia	1959	#217–218 (1952; pp. 27–34); #255 (1958; pp. 25–28)<lb/>
T.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;Eliot	Sobre la poesía y los poetas	1959	#153–156 (1947; pp. 129–150)<lb/>
Graham Greene	Un caso acabado	1961	#268 (1961; pp. 29–36)<lb/>
Victoria Ocampo	Tagore en las barrancas de San Isidro	1961	#270 (1961; pp. 62–83)<lb/>
C.&amp;nbsp;P.&amp;nbsp;Snow	Las dos culturas y la revolución científica	1963	#274 (1962; pp. 9–23)<lb/>
Vita Sackville-West	Toda pasión concluida	1963	#284 (1963; pp. 1–12)<lb/>
H.&amp;nbsp;A.&amp;nbsp;Murena	Los herederos de la promesa	1965	#296 (1965; pp. 23–34)<lb/>
Max Horkheimer &amp; Theodor W.&amp;nbsp;Adorno	Dialéctica del iluminismo	1971	#315 (1968; pp. 22–38)</p>
<pb n="181"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">I</hi>mpact of serial publications on marketing strategies in literary journals like <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>. <lb/>
In fact, Woolf’s work overtly harkened back to earlier serialized installments with <lb/>
the use of phrases like “<hi rend="italic">continuará</hi>” [will continue] and “<hi rend="italic">concluirá</hi>” [will con-<lb/>
clude] at the end of each separate chapter publication in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>, which were spread <lb/>
out over four different issues from December 1935 to March 1936. Editorial Sur’s <lb/>
single-volume book publication of <hi rend="italic">Un cuarto propio</hi> appeared in July 1936.<lb/>
<lb/>
In contrast to the multiple-teaser-chapter model, single teaser chapters be-<lb/>
came more common in the literary journal. The single-teaser chapter model <lb/>
coincided with Editorial Sur’s publication of the works of more high-profile, <lb/>
international authors. Generally speaking, this shift to a single-teaser chapter <lb/>
model not only would allow for the inclusion of more authors’ works, which <lb/>
certainly would have appealed to Ocampo’s more general goals, but also might <lb/>
be a logical change in light of the differences in sales that result from serialized <lb/>
publications and teaser chapters. While the presence of serialized publications <lb/>
within a journal might generate an uptick in buyers—<lb/>
or subscribers, these in-<lb/>
dividuals will only be purchasing issues of one particular journal, not separate <lb/>
books, and they might even stop their subscriptions after the last installment of a <lb/>
given work. On the other hand, the use of pre-publication chapters entices read-<lb/>
ers not only to continue to buy a given journal for the carefully curated snippets <lb/>
of forthcoming works, but also to purchase the books that are marketed with <lb/>
these teaser chapters. If the journal and publishing house are owned by the same <lb/>
individual, which is the case for <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> and Editorial Sur, this model would be the <lb/>
most logical and economically sound option as it encourages the largest amount <lb/>
of profit as well as the greatest number of readers and buyers.<lb/>
<lb/>
Another more subtle clue that these teaser chapters functioned as a type of <lb/>
marketing to help sell Editorial Sur editions are the footnotes that accompanied <lb/>
over half of the periodical publications.<hi rend="sup">21</hi> More specifically, the majority of these <lb/>
teaser chapters brought readers’ attention to the fact that the excerpt that they <lb/>
were about to read in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> was part of a forthcoming Editorial Sur book. For in-<lb/>
stance, James Joyce’s <hi rend="italic">Desterrados</hi> alerted readers that the “versión castellana pub-<lb/>
licará próximamente la Editorial SUR” [the Spanish version will be published <lb/>
shortly], while Conrado Nalé Roxlo’s <hi rend="italic">Claro desvelo</hi> was already “en prensa” [in <lb/>
production] with Editorial Sur, and Gabriela Mistral’s <hi rend="italic">Tala</hi> “publicará este mes” <lb/>
[will be published this month].<hi rend="sup">22</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
In comparison with these slight hints, Ocampo took a more direct route <lb/>
with other works. In particular, she endorsed Huxley’s <hi rend="italic">Con los esclavos en la noria</hi> <lb/>
and Cyril Connolly’s <hi rend="italic">La tumba sin sosiego</hi> more explicitly. Immediately before <lb/>
the first teaser chapter of Huxley’s work was a long introductory text about the <lb/>
publication and the “esfuerza editorial” [editorial effort] to produce this work <lb/>
in Spanish.<hi rend="sup">23</hi> What is more, this gloss did not simply announce the publica-<lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">21.</hi> Over half of these Editorial Sur books that are promoted through teaser chapters are <lb/>
also reviewed in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">22.</hi> Virtually all of the other footnoted teaser chapters presented a similar linguistic for-<lb/>
mula to announce that these textual fragments were part of a larger work.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">23.</hi> I should note that both of the introductory texts that I discuss here only appeared <lb/>
before the excerpted teaser chapters in the literary journal <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> and were not included in the <lb/>
full book-length publications with Editorial Sur.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="182"/>
 tion of Huxley’s novel with Editorial Sur, it conveyed the unique opportunity <lb/>
 that readers had to acquire “una obra de gran importancia” [a work of great <lb/>
 importance].<hi rend="sup">24</hi> The editors of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> also stressed that this was the “primera traduc-<lb/>
 ción [española] que aparece, pues el público no conoce aún más que la edición <lb/>
 inglesa” [first Spanish translation to appear since the public does not know any-<lb/>
 thing other than the English edition].<hi rend="sup">25</hi> This particular tactic of emphasizing the <lb/>
 fact that no other Spanish-language version of a given work exists is one that <lb/>
 Editorial Sur employed frequently throughout the 1930s with great success.<hi rend="sup">26</hi><lb/>
 Similar to Huxley’s teaser chapters, the pre-publication chapter from Connolly’s <lb/>
 <hi rend="italic">La tumba sin sosiego</hi> was prefaced by a lengthy two-page parenthetical note by <lb/>
 Ricardo Baeza, the novel’s translator. Aside from providing a brief biography of <lb/>
 Connolly and details on his other works, Baeza mentions that the complete trans-<lb/>
 lation of his most recent novel (<hi rend="italic">La tumba sin sosiego</hi>) “publicará en breve la Editorial <lb/>
 <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>” [will be published soon by Editorial Sur] (95). These two examples point to <lb/>
 Ocampo’s meticulous attention to the promotion and marketing of her books.<lb/>
 For most of these titles, the pre-publication chapters appeared in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> at least <lb/>
 one to two months before their release as books by Editorial Sur. In this way, <lb/>
 readers were made aware of forthcoming titles and given a preview of com-<lb/>
 ing attractions with the hopes of building anticipation for the entire book. This <lb/>
 marketing strategy makes sense given that over half of these works were the first <lb/>
 authorized translations of foreign works available to readers in Latin America, <lb/>
 which also aligned with Ocampo’s overarching mission and, given their unique <lb/>
 status in the Spanish-language book industry, made their availability more de-<lb/>
 sirable. That said, there are a few outliers (nine in total) whose teaser chapters <lb/>
 appeared in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> in the same month as their full-length book publication. The <lb/>
 vast majority of titles that fall into this camp of simultaneous publication are <lb/>
 those by authors whose works appeared in Spanish and, as a result, did not re-<lb/>
 quire translation, namely Conrado Nalé Roxlo, Gabriela Mistral, José Bianco, <lb/>
 Juan Goyanarte, H. A. Murena, and Victoria Ocampo.<hi rend="sup">27</hi> The only exceptions <lb/>
 are Alexandre Arnoux’s <hi rend="italic">La cifra</hi>, which was published as a book with Editorial <lb/>
 Sur in November 1955 and then excerpted in the January/February 1956 issue <lb/>
 of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> (238: 87–90), and T. E. Lawrence’s <hi rend="italic">Siete pilares de la sabiduría</hi>, which was <lb/>
 published as a book with Editorial Sur in September 1944 and then excerpted in <lb/>
 the October 1944 issue of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> (120: 35–54). Given Ocampo’s interest in promot-<lb/>
 24. “Un capítulo de <hi rend="italic">Eyeless in Gaza</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 29 (1937): 47.<lb/>
 25. “Un capítulo de <hi rend="italic">Eyeless in Gaza</hi>,” 48.<lb/>
 26. The colophons for many international works produced by Editorial Sur during these <lb/>
 years highlight the status of these books as the first Spanish-language translation authorized by <lb/>
 the author (e.g., Aldous Huxley, <hi rend="italic">Contrapunto</hi> [1933], <hi rend="italic">Con los esclavos en la noria</hi> [1937]; <lb/>
 D. H. Lawrence, <hi rend="italic">Canguro</hi> [1933], <hi rend="italic">La virgin y el gitano</hi> [1934]; André Malraux, <hi rend="italic">La condición humana</hi> <lb/>
 [1936]; Virginia Woolf, <hi rend="italic">Un cuarto propio</hi> [1936], <hi rend="italic">Orlando</hi> [1937], <hi rend="italic">Al faro</hi> [1938]; James Joyce, <hi rend="italic">Desterrados</hi> <lb/>
 [1937]; etc.). The advertising flyers inserted in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> to announce forthcoming works from Edito-<lb/>
 rial Sur praised the novelty of their Spanish-language translations. Take, for instance, the flyer <lb/>
 for Joyce’s <hi rend="italic">Desterrados</hi> that boldly states that “DESTERRADOS no ha sido traducido aún a <lb/>
 ningún otro idioma; es por lo tanto una primicia más de SUR” [EXILES has not been trans-<lb/>
 lated into any other language; it is therefore another first for SUR].<lb/>
 27. Aside from these authors, the works of León Chestov, Ramón Fernández, and Joseph <lb/>
 Jean Lanza del Vasto also appeared with simultaneous publications in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> and Editorial Sur.<lb/>
<pb n="183"/>
<lb/>ing exemplary literary works from writers of her time, it makes sense that she<lb/>
would have fueled anticipation for coming titles. The longer timeline involved in<lb/>
producing translations of these foreign works also might have factored into the<lb/>
months-long gap between teaser chapter publication in Sur and full-length book<lb/>
publication with Editorial Sur.<hi rend="sup">28</hi><lb/>
<head>Promotional Trends</head><lb/>
Certain trends emerge with these pre-publication texts. In the pages that follow I<lb/>
explain why certain Editorial Sur works might have been promoted more heavily<lb/>
than others and, with the help of extant archival material, reveal additional finan-<lb/>
cial pressures that might account for some of Ocampo’s marketing decisions. In<lb/>
general terms, the rationale for the use of teaser chapters in Sur falls into one of two<lb/>
categories: promotion of best sellers, or questions of copyright and authors’ permis-<lb/>
sions. Even though these two categories overlap in a number of ways, it will be use-<lb/>
ful to conceptualize the use of pre-publication chapters through these two lenses.<lb/>
If a publisher is looking to capitalize on international literary trends, then<lb/>
producing translations, especially the first authorized translations, of works that<lb/>
have already become commercial successes in other countries is a sound deci-<lb/>
sion. Ocampo’s editorial selections and keen eye for the best literary trends,<lb/>
therefore, made her a savvy businesswoman. In fact, Editorial Sur made many<lb/>
international best sellers available to Spanish-language readers for the first time.<lb/>
Perhaps more surprising is the fact that some of her firm’s translations are still<lb/>
the only Spanish-language translations available for certain foreign works. Here<lb/>
I examine two examples of best-selling authors whose work Editorial Sur trans-<lb/>
lated, published, and excerpted with teaser chapters in the literary journal Sur:<lb/>
Aldous Huxley and Albert Camus.<lb/>
Editorial Sur published two of Aldous Huxley’s novels—Contrapunto and Con<lb/>
los esclavos en la noria—as well as his short pamphlet ¿Cómo lo resuelve usted? El<lb/>
problema de la paz constructiva. In fact, Huxley’s Contrapunto is the first work that<lb/>
Ocampo’s firm published, and one of the author’s most successful. A short three<lb/>
years later, in 1936, Ocampo acquired the translation and publication rights for<lb/>
Huxley’s Eyeless in Gaza, which was already creating a stir: “That Eyeless in Gaza<lb/>
was awaited with growing interest is attested by its first-year sales in England,<lb/>
which at 26,700 copies […], were more than double those of Brave New World.<lb/>
The reviews of Eyeless in Gaza were the fullest and quite often the most analytical<lb/>
of any novel Huxley wrote.”<hi rend="sup">29</hi> According to the book’s colophon, Con los esclavos<lb/>
en la noria was the first and only authorized Spanish translation of Eyeless in Gaza,<lb/>
which accentuates its unique importance.<lb/>
Unlike Contrapunto, the publication of Huxley’s Con los esclavos en la noria with<lb/>
Editorial Sur was preceded—and highly anticipated—by two teaser chapters in<lb/>
Ocampo’s literary journal. What is more, as previously mentioned, the first of these<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">28</hi>. The publication of foreign language works in translation is also more costly than pro-<lb/>
ducing a Spanish-language work. As a result, the earlier (and heavier) advertising and promo-<lb/>
tion of these works might have been an intentional effort to recuperate funds.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">29</hi>. Donald Watt, Aldous Huxley (New York: Routledge, 2013), 19.<lb/>
<pb n="184"/>
<p>two teaser chapters was introduced with a lengthy page-and-a-half note to readers<lb/>
that emphasized the importance of this literary work. From its opening line, this<lb/>
introductory note presented an air of marketing: “La Editorial <hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> dará pronto al<lb/>
público de habla española una obra de gran importancia: la reciente y ya famosa<lb/>
novela con que el autor de <hi rend="smallcaps">CONTRAPUNTO</hi> ha igualado y aún sobrepasado los<lb/>
valores extraordinarios en cuanto a inteligencia y estilo que señalaron a ese título<lb/>
como el de una de las novelas más importantes de nuestro tiempo.”<hi rend="sup">30</hi> Apart from<lb/>
singing the praises of this new novel, this note mentioned Huxley’s previous novel<lb/>
published by Editorial Sur (<hi rend="italic">Contrapunto</hi>), which linked the two works and appeared<lb/>
to encourage readers to purchase this earlier title if they had not done so already.<lb/>
Finally, the author of this note suggested that this edition would be to the liking of<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>’s many readers: “<hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> espera que sus ya muchos millares de lectores aprecien<lb/>
el esfuerzo editorial que comporta el ofrecerles en forma tan rápida y prolija la<lb/>
gran obra, de la que podrán leer hoy un capítulo escogido al azar y cuyo texto<lb/>
se halla en prensa.”<hi rend="sup">31</hi> Along with this laudatory introductory note, the novel was<lb/>
reviewed in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> by Julio Irazusta, the work’s translator.<hi rend="sup">32</hi> More than a traditional<lb/>
book review, this note focused on the difficulties of translating Huxley’s style and<lb/>
highlighted the literary achievements of the work, like the development of a “ver-<lb/>
dadera caracterización, personajes de inconfundible vida propia” [true depiction<lb/>
(of) characters with an unmistakable life of their own] and “un hondo drama<lb/>
según las mejores reglas, con <hi rend="italic">catharsis</hi> y todo” [an intense tragedy that follows the<lb/>
best rules, with <hi rend="italic">catharsis</hi> and all].<hi rend="sup">33</hi> In the process, Irazusta referred extensively<lb/>
a Huxley’s previously translated work that Editorial Sur published (<hi rend="italic">Contrapunto</hi>),<lb/>
which might have further served to promote the firm’s books.<lb/>
As it had done with Aldous Huxley’s <hi rend="italic">Con los esclavos en la noria</hi>, Editorial Sur<lb/>
publicized its edition of Albert Camus’s <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi> extensively. In particular, a pre-<lb/>
publication teaser chapter appeared within the pages of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> alongside numerous<lb/>
advertisements for the edition. While Editorial Sur employed comparable mar-<lb/>
keting techniques for other books that they published, Huxley’s and Camus’s<lb/>
works needed almost no introduction given their level of international recogni-<lb/>
tion (and subsequent anticipation). Originally appearing in French in 1947, “La<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Peste</hi> was published in a printing of 22,000 copies” according to Herbert Lottman,<lb/>
which was “high for that time, high for a serious novel, but an underestimate<lb/>
</p>
<p>30. “Editorial <hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> will soon provide the Spanish-speaking public with a work of great<lb/>
importance: the recent and already famous novel with which the author of <hi rend="italic">Point Counter Point</hi><lb/>
has equaled and even surpassed the extraordinary values of intelligence and style that made<lb/>
this book one of the most important novels of our time.” “Un capítulo de <hi rend="italic">Eyeless in Gaza</hi>,” 47.<lb/>
31. “<hi rend="smallcaps">SUR</hi> hopes that their many thousand readers appreciate the editorial effort put forth<lb/>
to offer them this great work in such a fast and meticulous form, from which they will be able<lb/>
to read today a randomly chosen chapter from the work that is in production.” “Un capítulo de<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Eyeless in Gaza</hi>,” 48. While the description of certain teaser chapters being chosen at random<lb/>
here pertains to Huxley’s novel, it can be applied more broadly to virtually all teaser chapter<lb/>
selections in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>, which do not adhere to any pattern in terms of the book chapters that were<lb/>
chosen to pre-publish.<lb/>
32. Julio Irazusta, “Reflexiones de traductor. La última novela de Huxley,” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 34 (1937): 74–78.<lb/>
33. Irazusta, “Reflexiones de traductor,” 76.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="185"/>
<p>on the part of the Librarie Gallimard of the suitability of the book for its era.”<hi rend="sup">34</hi><lb/>
Lottman goes on to describe the incredible financial success of Camus’s novel:<lb/>
“By the fall [of 1947] it had sold nearly 100,000 copies and Camus was joking to<lb/>
Michel and Janine Gallimard that henceforth he’d have to pick up everybody’s<lb/>
restaurant checks.”<hi rend="sup">35</hi> These publishing successes of <hi rend="italic">La Peste</hi> were not just reserved<lb/>
for its first edition in the original French, but also spilled over to the first edition<lb/>
of its Spanish translation with Editorial Sur.<lb/>
<lb/>
Editorial Sur’s first edition of <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi> appeared in July of 1948 and was<lb/>
promoted quite extensively by the literary journal <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>. Immediately following its<lb/>
initial publication, <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> advertised the novel in virtually every issue, describing the<lb/>
work as “la novela más famosa aparecida en Francia en los últimos veinte años.<lb/>
El gran éxito de la post-guerra” [the most famous novel published in France<lb/>
in the last twenty years. The great success of the postwar].<hi rend="sup">36</hi> What is more,<lb/>
these same advertisements informed readers that this first edition of <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi> was<lb/>
“agotada” [sold out] within a year of its publication date, but that it would be<lb/>
reissued in a second edition. This new edition came out in December 1949 and<lb/>
not only was heavily advertised in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>, just like the first edition, but also had a<lb/>
noticeable price increase from nine Argentine pesos to twelve. The popularity<lb/>
and extensive sales of <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi> were further attested in its publication eight more<lb/>
times from 1951 to 1961.<hi rend="sup">37</hi> Coupled with these publications and sales tactics was<lb/>
the review of <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi> by Rosa Chacel, who also happened to be the translator<lb/>
of the work for Editorial Sur. Throughout her lengthy article on this novel and<lb/>
her work in translating it into Spanish, she praised Camus for his literary ac-<lb/>
complishments: “Ante todo, este libro es un ejemplar gloriosamente logrado de<lb/>
arte dirigido” [Above all, this book is a gloriously accomplished model of guided<lb/>
art].<hi rend="sup">38</hi> When viewed together, all of these marketing materials for <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi>—from<lb/>
a pre-publication teaser chapter to its numerous advertisements and reviews—<lb/>
highlight Ocampo’s aim to promote the works of foreign authors through both<lb/>
the journal articles and books that she published.<lb/>
<lb/>
Related to capitalizing on international bestsellers is Ocampo’s knack for<lb/>
identifying widely anticipated books. Take, for instance, T. E. Lawrence’s <hi rend="italic">The<lb/>
Mint</hi> (1955). <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> advertised the first edition of this work in their<lb/>
July 31, 1954 issue: “DOUBLEDAY will bring out in February a limited edition<lb/>
of 1,000 copies of ‘The Mint,’ a little-known work by T. E. Lawrence. . . . In<lb/>
his will, Lawrence stipulated that the book should not be published, however,<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">34</hi>. Herbert R. Lottman, <hi rend="italic">Albert Camus: A Biography</hi> (New York: Doubleday, 1979), 426.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">35</hi>. Lottman, <hi rend="italic">Albert Camus</hi>, 427.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">36</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 166 (1948): n.p.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">37</hi>. There were several subsequent Spanish-language editions that appeared shortly after<lb/>
Editorial Sur’s first authorized Spanish translation of <hi rend="italic">La peste</hi> in 1948. Virtually all of these new<lb/>
editions name Rosa Chacel as the translator (with the exception of those produced by Aguilar),<lb/>
which indicates that these “new” editions appear to be reprintings of Chacel’s original transla-<lb/>
tion of <hi rend="italic">La Peste</hi> for Editorial Sur. Some of the firms that published their own editions of <hi rend="italic">La<lb/>
Peste</hi> include Ediciones Azteca (1956), Taurus (1957), Ediciones Cid (1958; 1960), Aguilar (1960;<lb/>
1961; 1971; 1973; 1979), Editorial Sudamericana (1973; 1974), and Edhasa (1977; 1981; 1983).<lb/>
For a full list of these later editions and their respective publishers, as well as a brief discussion<lb/>
of censorship surrounding this novel and its dissemination in Spain, see Fondebrider.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">38</hi>. Rosa Chacel, “Breve exegesis de ‘La peste’,” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 169 (1948): 67.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="186"/>
<lb/>until certain people died. In 1936, Doubleday wished to publish the book, but because of the provisions of the will, was unable to do so at that time.”<sup>39</sup><lb/>In their February highlights section from 1955, this same periodical noted that the publication of <hi rend="italic">The Mint</hi> “is certain to be hailed as a major literary event.”<sup>40</sup><lb/>In its issue of March 19, 1955, <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> stated that “[the first limited release was] oversubscribed, and no more copies were available by March 9,” which showcased readers’ interest in and demand for the work.<sup>41</sup><lb/>A short few months after its initial publication with Doubleday, <hi rend="italic">The Mint</hi> appeared in translation with Editorial Sur (on May 28, 1955).<sup>42</sup><lb/>However, it is important to note that this edition was originally scheduled to appear simultaneously with the first English and French editions in February 1955: “SUR publicará este libro extraordinario en el mes de febrero del año próximo, simultáneamente con las ediciones inglesa y francesa” [SUR will publish this extraordinary book in the month of February next year, simultaneously with the English and French editions].<sup>43</sup><lb/>Perhaps sensing the splash that this book would have, along with her own personal interest in Lawrence’s writings, Ocampo excerpted various chapters and pre-published them in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> as teasers in 1947 and 1951, well before the work’s slated release date.<lb/>While the former publication in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> consisted of a few pages of fragments, the latter presented readers with an introductory note on the work, the difficulties of its translation, and a whopping eight chapters.<sup>44</sup><lb/>From its paratextual material, readers learned that Ocampo, unlike any other publisher around the globe, “[ha recibido] autorización de publicar ocho capítulos” [received the authorization to publish eight chapters], which spoke to her literary connections and editorial prowess as a publisher.<sup>45</sup><lb/>She even goes so far as to note how this material “[n]o es mucho, pero nos da un pregusto del libro extraordinario de que forman parte” [is not much, but it gives us a taste of the extraordinary book of which it forms a part].<sup>46</sup><lb/>Her subtle use of the word <hi rend="italic">pregusto</hi> here hints at how these chapters served as a preview of coming attractions and signaled her desire to develop readers’ interest in the entire book that she would publish a few years later.<lb/>While a large number of the authors whose works appeared with Editorial Sur might have been household names to an educated international audience, not all of their titles that appeared with Ocampo’s publishing house were critically acclaimed bestsellers, commercial successes, or the most adequate representations of their respective oeuvres. For these reasons, heightened marketing tactics might have been<lb/>
<sup>39</sup> <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, July 31, 1954: 466–67.<lb/>
<sup>40</sup> <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, February 1955: 1772.<lb/>
<sup>41</sup> <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, March 19, 1955: 1557.<lb/>
<sup>42</sup> Given the controversial nature of this work, Editorial Sur’s popular edition was expurgated. That said, in Ocampo’s personal copy of <hi rend="italic">El troquel</hi>, currently housed at Villa Ocampo in Argentina, she has filled in all of the censored passages herself in red pencil, and, according to advertisements in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 230 (September 1954) there also was an “edición limitada y sin purgar” [limited edition and without censorship] available by subscription only.<lb/>
<sup>43</sup> <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 230 (1954), n.p.<lb/>
<sup>44</sup> The earlier fragments from 1947 are translated by Jorge Luis Borges and Adolfo Bioy Casares while the latter material from 1951, as well as the entire published book, are translated by Victoria Ocampo (with the assistance of Enrique Pezzoni and Ricardo Baeza).<lb/>
<sup>45</sup> Victoria Ocampo, “The Mint,” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 197 (1951): 1.<lb/>
<sup>46</sup> Ocampo, “The Mint,” 1.<lb/>
<pb n="187"/>
<p>necessary. Take, for instance, James Joyce’s only surviving play, <hi rend="italic">Exiles</hi>, which was<lb/>translated and published by Editorial Sur in 1937 as <hi rend="italic">Desterrados</hi>. Unlike <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi> or<lb/>even <hi rend="italic">The Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</hi>, Joyce’s <hi rend="italic">Exiles</hi> is considered by many to<lb/>be his least successful play and was hardly ever performed.<hi rend="sup">47</hi> When analyzing these<lb/>examples, one might be tempted to argue that Ocampo had an eye toward the<lb/>most accessible works—in terms of both the level of difficulty of the works them-<lb/>selves and the ease of access to the rights for translation and publication—for her<lb/>publishing firm. However, this is not the case since Editorial Sur published some<lb/>of the first and only authorized Spanish translations of works of key twentieth-<lb/>century writers, such as Virginia Woolf, William Faulkner, Graham Greene, Nor-<lb/>man Mailer, Samuel Beckett, Albert Camus, and Aldous Huxley.<hi rend="sup">48</hi> And many of<lb/>these authors’ translated and published works with Editorial Sur were their most<lb/>notable, which is certainly what we saw with Aldous Huxley and Albert Camus.<lb/>Another instance in which Editorial Sur heavily marketed a lesser-known<lb/>work from a well-known author is with Graham Greene’s <hi rend="italic">Un caso acabado</hi> (1961).<lb/>Ocampo developed a close relationship with Greene after they first met in 1938<lb/>and remained in his inner circle throughout her life.<hi rend="sup">49</hi> Apart from his stays at<lb/>her homes in Argentina, he dedicated his novel <hi rend="italic">The Honorary Consul</hi> to her and<lb/>she, in turn, published a total of sixteen of his books with Editorial Sur.<hi rend="sup">50</hi> While<lb/>a number of Greene’s novels reached the status of best-sellers, most notably <hi rend="italic">The<lb/>Heart of the Matter</hi> (1948), which Editorial Sur translated and published in 1949,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Un caso acabado</hi> did not receive anywhere near the same amount of interest as<lb/>his other works.<hi rend="sup">51</hi> However, Ocampo promoted Greene’s <hi rend="italic">Un caso acabado</hi> with a<lb/>teaser chapter in the January 1961 issue of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi>, a full five months prior to its book-<lb/>length publication with Editorial Sur.<hi rend="sup">52</hi> Even though this work was not as success-<lb/>ful as his previous novels, it is possible that Ocampo relied on the cultural capital<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">47</hi>. Cor Hermans, <hi rend="italic">Interbellum Literature. Writing in a Season of Nihilism</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2017),<lb/>289.<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">48</hi>. Alongside these translated works, Editorial Sur published two of Jorge Luis Borges’s<lb/>most important collections of short stories: <hi rend="italic">El jardín de senderos que se bifurcan</hi> (1941) and <hi rend="italic">Ficciones</hi><lb/>(1944).<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">49</hi>. Wise and Hill note that Greene considered her “as one of his four best friends” (<hi rend="italic">The<lb/>Works of Graham Greene. Volume 2. A Guide to the Graham Greene Archives</hi> [London: Bloomsbury,<lb/>2015], 189).<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">50</hi>. The dedication to <hi rend="italic">The Honorary Consul</hi> reads: “For Victoria Ocampo, with love and in<lb/>memory of the many happy weeks I have passed at San Isidro and Mar del Plata.”<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">51</hi>. “<hi rend="italic">The Heart of the Matter</hi> was enormously popular, selling more than 300,000 copies<lb/>in Britain. It was also a main selection of the Book-of-the-Month Club in America. Though<lb/>Greene considered the book his most serious work to date, it brought him more money than all<lb/>his previous entertainments combined” (Michael Sheldon, “Greene, (Henry) Graham,” <hi rend="italic">Oxford<lb/>Dictionary of National Biography</hi>, January 8, 2015, n.p.).<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">52</hi>. Héctor J. Puglia’s review of <hi rend="italic">Un caso acabado</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 275 [1963]: 104–106) also marketed<lb/>the novel from its very opening line: “Una nueva obra de Graham Greene es siempre una opor-<lb/>tunidad para renovar el placer que produce la maestría de uno de los mejores narradores de<lb/>la novelística actual” (104). That said, Puglia concedes that the novel is “menos rica en matices<lb/>y de contrucción menos rigurosa que las mejores obras de Greene” (Puglia, “<hi rend="italic">Un caso acabado</hi>,”<lb/>106).<lb/></p>
<pb n="188"/>
<p>of his name, which she had already popularized through previous Editorial Sur<lb/>
translations of his best-selling works, to help promote and sell <hi rend="italic">Un caso acabado</hi>.<lb/>
Finally, there is the question of author’s rights. Other writers and intellectu-<lb/>
als involved in the Argentine publishing industry have noted the difficulty and<lb/>
extremely high cost of acquiring authors’ rights, which might account for why<lb/>
Ocampo focused on promoting the works of authors for whom she had already<lb/>
secured the translation rights.<hi rend="sup">53</hi> Not only that, most of the Spanish-language edi-<lb/>
tions that she produced were the first and only authorized translations of these<lb/>
works, which made them all the more valuable. That is to say, Ocampo identified<lb/>
a number of the best international literary works earlier on in her career as a<lb/>
publisher and then proceeded to corner the market by acquiring the translation<lb/>
and publication rights for these titles. One of the ways in which Ocampo might<lb/>
have been able to skirt the issue of paying large sums of money to acquire au-<lb/>
thors’ rights was through her impressive networks of contacts. Her close friend-<lb/>
ships with <hi rend="italic">Virginia Woolf</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Igor Stravinsky</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Rabindranath Tagore</hi> are well<lb/>
known and these connections undoubtedly provided her with a great deal more<lb/>
publishing freedom and access than most Latin American editors of the time. In<lb/>
fact, her teaser publications of T. S. Eliot’s <hi rend="italic">Sobre la poesía y los poetas</hi> and Cyril<lb/>
Connolly’s <hi rend="italic">La tumba sin sosiego</hi>, both of which appeared in 1947 in the special<lb/>
quadruple issue of <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> dedicated to English literature, illustrated her impressive<lb/>
literary connections. In her introductory note to the entire issue, Ocampo alludes<lb/>
to her networks by stating that “la lista de agradecimientos, en lo que respecta a<lb/>
mis relaciones personales con Inglaterra, sería tan larga que no intentaré agotarla<lb/>
en este prólogo” [the list of acknowledgements, with regard to my personal rela-<lb/>
tions with England, would be so long that I won’t attempt to exhaust it in this<lb/>
prologue].<hi rend="sup">54</hi> However, she still mentions several individuals by name who helped<lb/>
her fill the pages of the issues at hand. In particular, she notes her conversations<lb/>
with Connolly “sobre este número y sus <hi rend="italic">hints</hi> me han sido preciosos” [about<lb/>
this issue and that his hints have been very valuable].<hi rend="sup">55</hi> She also discusses Eliot’s<lb/>
foundational role in deciding on writers to include and the overall shape of the<lb/>
four-issue publication: “Yo quería saber lo que los ingleses pensaban de su propia<lb/>
literatura contemporánea y no cansaba de interrogarlos.... Así fué el propio T.<lb/>
S. Eliot quien eligió entre sus obras ¿Qué es un clásico? para este número de <hi rend="italic">SUR</hi>”<lb/>
[I wanted to know what the English thought of their own contemporary literature<lb/>
and I didn’t tire of asking them.... Thus, it was T. S. Eliot himself who chose<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">What is a Classic?</hi> from among his works for this issue of <hi rend="italic">SUR</hi>].<hi rend="sup">56</hi><lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">53</hi>. Adolfo Bioy Casares recalled similar snags when working with Jorge Luis Borges on<lb/>
their “<hi rend="italic">Séptimo Círculo</hi>” [Seventh Circle] collection with Emecé Editores in the 1940s: “el<lb/>
trabajo en la editorial nos asomó a los problemas de los derechos de autor, que hasta entonces<lb/>
habíamos ignorado.... Nos enteramos así de que algunas novelas que deseábamos incluir en El<lb/>
Séptimo Círculo no estaban libres” [our work in the publishing house showed us the problems<lb/>
of copyright that we had ignored up to that point.... We realized that some novels that we<lb/>
wanted to include in the Seventh Circle series were not free] (Adolfo Bioy Casares, <hi rend="italic">Memorias:<lb/>
Infancia, adolescencia, y cómo se hace un escritor</hi> [Barcelona: Tusquets, 1994], 101).<lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">54</hi>. Ocampo, “Introducción,” 9.<lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">55</hi>. Ocampo, “Introducción,” 8.<lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">56</hi>. Ocampo, “Introducción,” 8. The version of Eliot’s “¿Qué es un clásico?” that ap-<lb/>
peared in <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> is notably different from the final published version in his <hi rend="italic">Sobre la poesía y los poetas</hi>.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="189"/>
<p>
In a similar vein is the question of literary agents. Unlike other countries,<lb/>
literary agents did not become a staple of the publishing industry in Latin Amer-<lb/>
ica until the mid-twentieth century. One of the most well-known and successful<lb/>
literary agents in Argentina during this time, who worked extensively with Oc-<lb/>
ampo and Editorial Sur, was Lawrence Smith.<hi rend="sup">57</hi> These individuals would benefit<lb/>
financially from selling translation rights to publishing firms like Editorial Sur. In<lb/>
particular, according to Smith himself, “It is inadvisable to sell translation rights<lb/>
outright except in special cases. They should be paid for by a sum in advance<lb/>
on royalties, or per edition published.”<hi rend="sup">58</hi> Extant archival documents reveal that<lb/>
Smith followed his own advice quite closely. More specifically, he helped facilitate<lb/>
Ocampo’s acquisition, and ultimate publication, of works by William Faulkner,<lb/>
Christopher Isherwood, George Orwell, H. G. Wells, and T. E. Lawrence for<lb/>
Editorial Sur.<hi rend="sup">59</hi> What is more, these same documents clearly stated the required<lb/>
royalty payment of 5% of the sale price of any and all books. While these same<lb/>
upfront costs and royalty payments might not have factored into every work that<lb/>
Ocampo published with Editorial Sur, they help account for why the works of<lb/>
certain authors—namely those with heftier price tags for the publisher—were<lb/>
marketed more heavily than others. That is to say, Ocampo most likely would<lb/>
not have wanted to lose exorbitant sums of money just to publish the work of<lb/>
internationally acclaimed authors or of her close friends for that matter.<lb/>
Regardless of the specific rationale for every teaser chapter that appeared<lb/>
in Sur prior to the release of its full-length book with Editorial Sur, what all of<lb/>
these examples show is that Ocampo had a well-developed plan to popularize the<lb/>
works of international writers not just in her literary journal, but also through her<lb/>
publishing house. That is to say, taking a closer look at the teaser chapters that<lb/>
appeared throughout Ocampo’s literary journal reveals her shrewd instincts for<lb/>
identifying national and international authors whose literary works would inter-<lb/>
est her readers and, as a result, sell well in their full-length book form. Moreover,<lb/>
many of the titles that she selected to publish with Editorial Sur were the first<lb/>
authorized Spanish translations of best sellers by well-known authors, such as<lb/>
Albert Camus or Virginia Woolf, which resulted in large sales as is evident by<lb/>
the fact that the first editions of these works were very often sold out within the<lb/>
first few months of their publication. Even though Ocampo funneled a great deal<lb/>
of her own money and resources into Sur and Editorial Sur, she continued to<lb/>
publish both the journal and books for nearly half a century, an impressive feat<lb/>
made possible by her constant attention to the financial details of her literary<lb/>
enterprise as well as her own personal mission to present readers with exemplary<lb/>
works of international fiction and nonfiction.<lb/>
</p>
<note place="foot">
<hi rend="sup">57</hi> Aside from Lawrence Smith, the only other two major literary agents in the Spanish-<lb/>
speaking world during the twentieth century were Carmen Balcells and International Editors.<lb/>
</note>
<note place="foot">
<hi rend="sup">58</hi> Lawrence Smith, “Translation Sales Down South,” Publishers’ Weekly, September&amp;nbsp;13, 1941, 909.<lb/>
</note>
<note place="foot">
<hi rend="sup">59</hi> The extant correspondence between Ocampo and Smith, currently housed at Villa<lb/>
Ocampo in Argentina, mentions the following titles: William Faulkner’s <hi rend="italic">Light in August</hi>; Chris-<lb/>
topher Isherwood’s <hi rend="italic">Goodbye to Berlin</hi>; George Orwell’s <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays</hi>; H.&amp;nbsp;G. Wells’ <hi rend="italic">The Fate of<lb/>
Homo Sapiens</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">The Letters of T.&amp;nbsp;E.&amp;nbsp;Lawrence</hi>.<lb/>
</note>
<pb n="190"/>
<head>WORKS CITED</head><lb/>
Benedict, Nora C. Borges and the Literary Marketplace: How Editorial Practices Shaped<lb/>
Cosmopolitan Reading. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2021.<lb/>
Bioy Casares, Adolfo. Memorias: Infancia, adolescencia, y cómo se hace un escritor Barce-<lb/>
lona: Tusquets, 1994.<lb/>
Chacel, Rosa. “Breve exegesis de ‘La peste.’” Sur 169 (1948): 65–82.<lb/>
Coker, Mark. Smashwords Book Marketing Guide. Smashwords, 2018.<lb/>
Crayton, R. J. The Self-Publishing Road Map. Seven Steps to Make Your Journey a Success.<lb/>
CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform, 2015.<lb/>
Delafield, Catherine. Serialization and the Novel in Mid-Victorian Magazines. New York: <lb/>
Routledge, 2015.<lb/>
Fondebrider, Jorge. “Cuestiones sobre derechos de autor (6).” Club de traductores liter-<lb/>
arios de Buenos Aires, May 11, 2020. clubdetraductoresliterariosdebaires.blogspot.<lb/>
com/2020/05/cuestiones-sobre-derechos-de-autor-6.html.<lb/>
Hermans, Cor. Interbellum Literature. Writing in a Season of Nihilism. Leiden: Brill, 2017.<lb/>
Huxley, Aldous. Con los esclavos en la noria. Buenos Aires: Editorial Sur, 1937.<lb/>
Irazusta, Julio. “Reflexiones de traductor. La última novela de Huxley.” Sur 34 (1937): 74–78.<lb/>
King, John. Sur: A Study of the Argentine Literary Journal and Its Role in the Development of <lb/>
a Culture, 1931–1970. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1986.<lb/>
———. “Towards a Reading of the Argentine Literary Magazine Sur.” Latin American <lb/>
Research Review 16, no. 2 (1981): 57–78.<lb/>
Larkosh, Christopher. “Translating Woman: Victoria Ocampo and the Empires of <lb/>
Foreign Fascination.” In Translation and Power, 99–121. Edited by Maria Tymoczko-<lb/>
 and Edwin Gentzler. Amherst, MA: University of Massachusetts Press, 2002.<lb/>
Law, Graham. Serializing Fiction in the Victorian Press. London: Palgrave, 2000.<lb/>
Lottman, Herbert R. Albert Camus: A Biography. New York: Doubleday, 1979.<lb/>
Lund, Michael. America’s Continuing Story: An Introduction to Serial Fiction, 1850–1900.<lb/>
Detroit, MI: Wayne State University Press, 1993.<lb/>
Lynch, Maggie. Secrets to Becoming A Successful Author. Windtree Press, 2018.<lb/>
Majstorovic, Gorica. “An American Place: Victoria Ocampo’s Editorial Politics, the <lb/>
Foundation of Sur, and Hemispheric Alliances.” Arizona Journal of Hispanic Cul-<lb/>
tural Studies 9 (2005): 64–73.<lb/>
———. “Literature of the Americas in the Making: U.S. Writers and Translation in <lb/>
Sur, 1931–1944.” MonTI 5 (2013): 287–98.<lb/>
Meyer, Doris. Victoria Ocampo: Against the Wind and the Tide. Austin, TX: University <lb/>
of Texas Press, 1979.<lb/>
Ocampo, Victoria. “Introducción.” Sur 153 (1947): 7–11.<lb/>
<pb n="191"/>
<p>———. “The Mint.” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 197 (1951): 1–18.<lb/>
———. <hi rend="italic">Sur. Informe general y proyectos culturales de la sociedad.</hi> Buenos Aires: Editorial Sur, n.d.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, vols. 166–167 (1954–55).<lb/>
Sheldon, Michael. “Greene, (Henry) Graham.” <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography.</hi> January&amp;nbsp;8, 2015. doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/40460.<lb/>
Smith, Lawrence. “Translation Sales Down South.” <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly,</hi> September&amp;nbsp;13, 1941.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Sur,</hi> nos.&amp;nbsp;2–315 (1931–68).<lb/>
“Un capítulo de <hi rend="italic">Eyeless in Gaza.</hi>” <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi> 29 (1937): 47–48.<lb/>
Watt, Donald. <hi rend="italic">Aldous Huxley.</hi> New&amp;nbsp;York: Routledge, 2013.<lb/>
West&amp;nbsp;III, James&amp;nbsp;L.&amp;nbsp;W. “The Second Serials of <hi rend="italic">This Side of Paradise</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Beautiful and Damned.</hi>” <hi rend="italic">The Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi> 72, no.&amp;nbsp;1 (1979): 63–74.<lb/>
Willson, Patricia. <hi rend="italic">La constelación del sur: traductores y traducciones en la literatura argentina del siglo&amp;nbsp;XX.</hi> Buenos Aires: Siglo Veintiuno Editores, 2004.<lb/>
Wise, Jon and Mike Hill, eds. <hi rend="italic">The Works of Graham Greene. Volume&amp;nbsp;2. A Guide to the Graham Greene Archives.</hi> London: Bloomsbury, 2015.<lb/>
Wright, Amy&amp;nbsp;E. “Subscribing Identities: The Serial Novel in the Development of Novel and Nation. Spain and Mexico from the 1840s to the 1860s.” PhD diss. Brown University, 2006.</p>
<pb n="192"/>
<pb n="193"/>
<head>THE ENGRAVINGS OF POPE’S<lb/>
WORKS II (1735): ‘ENVY MUST OWN,<lb/>
I LIVE AMONG THE GREAT’</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">James McLaverty</name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">O</hi>n 24 April 1735, or perhaps a little earlier, Pope published the second <lb/>
volume of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> It contained: ‘Ethic Epistles to Henry St. John L. <lb/>
Bolingbroke’ (<hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi>), ‘Ethic Epistles, the Second Book. To Several Per-<lb/>
sons’, imitations of Horace and Donne, and the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi>.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Like the first <lb/>
volume of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, which had been published just after his twenty-ninth birthday, <lb/>
on 3 June 1717 (Griffith 79–86), the second volume was issued in the formats of <lb/>
his Homer translations – small folio, large folio, and quarto – and both the large <lb/>
folios and the quartos had illustrative headpieces, tailpieces, and initials. The <lb/>
engravings of 1717 have been subject to lively critical engagement, and the the-<lb/>
matic importance of the illustrations, symbolizing and reflecting on the poems, <lb/>
has been recognized.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> But the engravings in the second volume of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> <lb/>
have until recently been largely neglected. Close attention to them reveals that they <lb/>
were part of a considered, though hesitantly executed, plan to emphasize Pope’s<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">1</hi>. I am deeply grateful to David Vander Meulen for his corrections and advice, and for <lb/>
providing the illustrations for this essay from his own copies. A preliminary version of the essay <lb/>
was read for me by Dr Corrina Readioff at a session at the ISECS conference in Edinburgh <lb/>
in 2019. I am indebted to her for her generous assistance and for her report of the session’s <lb/>
discussion.<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">2</hi>. Reginald Harvey Griffith quotes the advertisement from the <hi rend="italic">Grub-street Journal</hi> <lb/>
of 24 April 1735 in <hi rend="italic">Alexander Pope: A Bibliography</hi>, 2 vols (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1922–7), <lb/>
2:287–8. His accounts of the folio (370), large-paper folio (371), and quarto (372) are still valu-<lb/>
able. Subsequent references are to Griffith and item number.<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">3</hi>. For comments on the illustrations, see David Foxon in his 1976 Lyell lectures, <hi rend="italic">Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade</hi> <lb/>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991), 44, 81–5; Vincent Carretta, ‘“Images Reflect from Art to Art”: Alexander Pope’s Collected <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> <lb/>
of 1717’, in Neil Fraistat (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Poems in Their Place: The Intertextuality and Order of Poetic Collections</hi>, (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1986), 195–233; and James McLaverty, <hi rend="italic">Pope, Print, and Meaning</hi> <lb/>
(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2001), 61–6, 70–4. A recent <lb/>
valuable probing of the illustrations of <hi rend="italic">The Rape of the Lock</hi> is by Allison Muri, ‘Of Words and <lb/>
Things: Image, Page, Text, and <hi rend="italic">The Rape of the Lock</hi>’, in Donald W. Nichol (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Anniversary <lb/>
Essays on Alexander Pope’s <hi rend="italic">The Rape of the Lock</hi> (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2016), <lb/>
167–217.<lb/></hi></p>
</div>