<back>
   <div type="appendix" n="figures">
      <head>Appendix A. Figures</head>
      <list>
         <item xml:id="fig6">
            <figure n="6">
               <head>From final page of the manuscript, <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title>.</head>
               <note>Papers of William Faulkner, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="fig7">
            <figure n="7">
               <head>From final page of the setting copy, <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title>.</head>
               <note>Papers of William Faulkner, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="fig8">
            <figure n="8">
               <head>From final page of the first edition, <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>.</head>
               <note>Random House, 1939.</note>
            </figure>
         </item>
      </list>
   </div>

   <div type="notes" n="endnotes">
      <head>Notes</head>
      <list>
         <note n="17" xml:id="n17">Ernest Hemingway, <title level="m">The Sun Also Rises: The Library of America Corrected Text</title>, ed. Robert W. Trogdon (New York: Library of America, 2022).</note>

         <note n="18" xml:id="n18">The title <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title> alludes to Psalms 137: “By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down, yea, we wept, when we remembered Zion,” a passage concerning captivity and freedom that echoes throughout Faulkner’s novel.</note>

         <note n="19" xml:id="n19"><title level="m">The Wild Palms</title> (New York: New American Library, 1948); <title level="m">The Old Man</title> (New York: New American Library, 1948). In these volumes the definite article “The” was added to the title “Old Man.”</note>

         <note n="20" xml:id="n20"><title level="m">The Wild Palms and The Old Man</title> (New York: New American Library, 1954).</note>

         <note n="21" xml:id="n21">Faulkner had little leverage with Random House in 1939. <title level="m">Absalom, Absalom!</title> (1936) had not sold well, and the biblical title <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title> was judged commercially risky, prompting the publisher’s change of title and its bowdlerizing of the text. After Faulkner won the Nobel Prize in 1949, such editorial interference ceased.</note>

         <note n="22" xml:id="n22">Both the manuscript and the setting-copy typescript have been reproduced in facsimile in <title level="m">William Faulkner Manuscripts</title>, vol. 14, parts 1–2, ed. Thomas L. McHaney (New York &amp; London: Garland, 1986).</note>

         <note n="23" xml:id="n23"><title level="m">Les Palmiers sauvages</title> (Paris: Gallimard, 1952).</note>

         <note n="24" xml:id="n24">Thomas L. McHaney, “William Faulkner’s <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>: A Textual and Critical Study” (PhD diss., University of South Carolina, 1968), esp. Appendix I, “The Text,” pp. 252–65.</note>

         <note n="25" xml:id="n25">The corrected text appears in William Faulkner, <title level="m">Novels 1936–1940</title> (New York: Library of America, 1990), 493–726.</note>
      </list>
   </div>

   <listBibl>
      <head>Bibliography</head>

      <bibl xml:id="bib1">Faulkner, William. <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem [The Wild Palms]</title>. Corrected text ed. Thomas L. McHaney and Noel Polk. New York: Library of America, 1990.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib2">———. <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>. New York: Random House, 1939.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib3">———. <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>. New York: New American Library, 1948.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib4">———. <title level="m">The Old Man</title>. New York: New American Library, 1948.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib5">———. <title level="m">The Wild Palms and The Old Man</title>. New York: New American Library, 1954.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib6">———. <title level="m">William Faulkner Manuscripts</title>. Vol. 14, parts 1–2. Edited by Thomas L. McHaney. New York &amp; London: Garland Publishing, 1986.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib7">Gallimard. <title level="m">Les Palmiers sauvages</title>. Paris, 1952.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib8">Hemingway, Ernest. <title level="m">The Sun Also Rises: The Library of America Corrected Text</title>. Edited by Robert W. Trogdon. New York: Library of America, 2022.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib9">McHaney, Thomas L. “William Faulkner’s <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>: A Textual and Critical Study.” PhD diss., University of South Carolina, 1968.</bibl>

      <bibl xml:id="bib10">Psalms 137 (King James Version).</bibl>
   </listBibl>

   <div type="index">
      <head>Index of Names and Titles</head>
      <list>
         <item>Absalom, Absalom!</item>
         <item>Charlotte Rittenmeyer</item>
         <item>Faulkner, William</item>
         <item>Harry Wilbourne</item>
         <item>Hemingway, Ernest</item>
         <item>If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</item>
         <item>McHaney, Thomas L.</item>
         <item>Old Man (story)</item>
         <item>Polk, Noel</item>
         <item>Random House</item>
         <item>Saxe Commins</item>
         <item>Small Special Collections Library (University of Virginia)</item>
         <item>The Sun Also Rises</item>
         <item>The Wild Palms</item>
      </list>
   </div>
</back>