<back>
  <div type="editorial">
    <head>Interleaved Annotations and Proof Corrections</head>
    <p>The text records a wealth of annotations made by Kirgate (and occasionally by Walpole) on the proof copy of the 1784 <emphasis>Description</emphasis>. These annotations include cancellations (e.g. Sections D, E, L, and O), notes on additions and changes (such as the insertion of a line on page 93 and a heading change on page 94), and comments on typographical errors. There are numerous marginal notes, comparisons with the printed text, and observations on the provenance of drawings, prints, and other objects.</p>
    <p>Among these notes, Kirgate records details of extra-illustration, including his instructions about the drawings pasted into the volume (for instance, notes on a drawing of the projecting canopy and a series of watercolors), and detailed price records for objects in the collection, ranging from a bust of Henry VIII and Children to a bronze padlock and various antiques.</p>
  </div>
  
  <div type="index">
    <head>Index of Rooms and Visitor Records</head>
    <p>An index is presented, headed “Index of Rooms,” which gives the page numbers of the 1784 edition. A pencil note at the foot of the second index provides information on the number of visitors to Strawberry Hill. For example, it records that in 1786 eighty tickets were given for admission, in 1787 seventy (with a "Ditto" marking) and in 1789 one hundred were given; later, in 1807, Mrs. Damer notes that about 80 or 90 tickets were used yearly. This index is supplemented by Walpole’s manuscript "Book of Visitors," which broadly confirms the early entries.</p>
  </div>
  
  <div type="appendix">
    <head>Appendix: Drawings and Additional Material</head>
    <p>Between the two versions of the Index of Rooms appears a pencil list headed "The following Drawings were made by Mr. Carter for Mr. Bull &amp; Mr. Walpole." This list records thirty-six drawings created for Bull’s copy of the <emphasis>Description</emphasis>, with several also appearing in Walpole’s copy. One drawing, "Gallery 10 G[uineas]," is crossed through and marked as having been bought by Mr. Baker. Additional material includes a transcription dated 6 February 1780 by Kirgate, notes about an early design for mirrors on either side of the Refectory window, and a drawing of Walpole’s coat of arms alongside a pencil drawing of an ossuarium from the Armoury.</p>
  </div>
  
  <div type="lists">
    <head>Lists of Late Acquisitions and Additional Entries</head>
    <p>Two short lists at the end of the More Additions appendix and on a blank back leaf record late acquisitions made by Walpole as late as 1791. The first list includes items such as a Brown earthen Miraculous Pitcher, a Miniature in enamel of [gap] Lord Bute (bought at Dalton’s Sale in 1791), and Six Portraits drawn by Rosalba. A second list records five further items: a carved Ivory Cup with a Bacchanalian Procession, Two Cocoa Nuts carved with the Arms of Orford, Two silver filigraine Hampers, and a Portrait of the Rev. William Cole on painted Glass.</p>
  </div>
  
  <div type="bibliography">
    <head>Bibliography</head>
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>Snodin.</bibl>
      <bibl>Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill, 36, figure 51.</bibl>
      <bibl>Hieroglyphic Tales. Kenneth W. Gross (London: Pallas Athene, 2011).</bibl>
      <bibl>A Catalogue of the Valuable and Curious Collection, Vine-Street, Piccadilly (Deceased): King &amp; Lochée, 3 December 1810 and following days, including Day 8, lot 413.</bibl>
      <bibl>A Catalogue of the Very Choice and Select Library of the late George Baker, Esq. of St. Paul’s Churchyard: Sotheby, 6 June 1825, Day 3, lot 822.</bibl>
      <bibl>Strawberry Hill Accounts, 20 and 179, note 1; Clarke, “Lord God! Jesus! What a House!” 380, note 41.</bibl>
      <bibl>Timothy Wilson, “‘Playthings Still?’ Horace Walpole as a Collector of Ceramics,” in Snodin, Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill, 200–219, at 201; also see Yale Edition of Horace Walpole’s Correspondence, 12:216–252.</bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
</back>