<back>
  <div type="notes">
    <head>Notes</head>
    <note n="17">Hemingway, <title level="m">The Sun Also Rises: The Library of America Corrected Text</title>, ed. Robert W. Trogdon (New York: Library of America, 2022).</note>
    <note n="18">The title is an allusion to Psalms&#160;137: “By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down, yea, we wept, when we remembered Zion.”  Images and wording from this psalm, which concerns captivity and freedom, appear throughout Faulkner’s novel.</note>
    <note n="19"><title level="m">The Wild Palms</title> (New York: New American Library, 1948); <title level="m">The Old Man</title> (New York: New American Library, 1948).  For these and later editions, the word “<quote>The</quote>” was added to the title of “Old Man.”</note>
    <note n="20"><title level="m">The Wild Palms and The Old Man</title> (New York: New American Library, 1954).</note>
    <note n="21">Faulkner had little leverage with his publisher in 1939.  Random House was the fifth imprint to publish his work and was carrying him as a <foreign xml:lang="fr">succès d’estime</foreign>.  His first book with Random House, <title level="m">Absalom, Absalom!</title>, had not sold well; <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title>, with another biblical title, was not likely to do better—hence, presumably, the change in title.  In 1939 Faulkner was best known as the author of <title level="m">Sanctuary</title> (1931), a scandalous novel about a young woman who is raped with a corn cob.  It is therefore not surprising that the publisher bowdlerized <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>.  The sanitizing, however, was incomplete: the words “<quote>pricks</quote>” and “<quote>cunts</quote>” appear on p.&#160;52 of the first edition, and “<quote>Shit!</quote>” appears on p.&#160;101.  Later, after he had won the Nobel Prize in 1949, Faulkner wielded more weight at Random House, and the heavy editing of his texts ceased.</note>
    <note n="22">Both the manuscript and the setting-copy typescript of the novel have been published in facsimile in <title level="m">William Faulkner Manuscripts</title>, vol.&#160;14, parts 1 and 2, ed. Thomas L. McHaney (New York and London: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1986).</note>
    <note n="23"><title level="m">Les Palmiers sauvages</title> (Paris: Gallimard, 1952).</note>
    <note n="24">McHaney, “William Faulkner’s <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>: A Textual and Critical Study.”  Diss. University of South Carolina, 1968.  See especially Appendix I, “The Text,” pp.&#160;252–65.</note>
    <note n="25">In the volume <author>William Faulkner</author>, <title level="m">Novels 1936–1940</title> (1990): 493–726.</note>
  </div>

  <div type="bibliography">
    <head>Bibliography</head>
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>Faulkner, William. <title level="m">If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem [The Wild Palms]</title>.  Corrected text edited by Thomas L. McHaney and Noel Polk.  New York: Library of America, 1990.</bibl>
      <bibl>———. <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>.  New York: New American Library, 1948.</bibl>
      <bibl>———. <title level="m">The Old Man</title>.  New York: New American Library, 1948.</bibl>
      <bibl>———. <title level="m">The Wild Palms and The Old Man</title>.  New York: New American Library, 1954.</bibl>
      <bibl>———. <title level="m">Sanctuary</title>.  New York: Random House, 1931.</bibl>
      <bibl>———. <title level="m">Absalom, Absalom!</title>.  New York: Random House, 1936.</bibl>
      <bibl>Hemingway, Ernest. <title level="m">The Sun Also Rises: The Library of America Corrected Text</title>.  Edited by Robert W. Trogdon.  New York: Library of America, 2022.</bibl>
      <bibl>McHaney, Thomas L. “William Faulkner’s <title level="m">The Wild Palms</title>: A Textual and Critical Study.”  PhD diss., University of South Carolina, 1968.</bibl>
      <bibl><title level="m">William Faulkner Manuscripts</title>.  Vol.&#160;14, parts 1–2.  Edited by Thomas L. McHaney.  New York and London: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1986.</bibl>
      <bibl><title level="m">Les Palmiers sauvages</title>.  Paris: Gallimard, 1952.</bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>

  <div type="listFigures">
    <head>List of Figures</head>
    <list>
      <item>Figure 6. From final page of the manuscript, <title>If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title>.  Papers of William Faulkner, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</item>
      <item>Figure 7. From final page of the setting copy, <title>If I Forget Thee, Jerusalem</title>.  Papers of William Faulkner, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</item>
      <item>Figure 8. From final page of the first edition, <title>The Wild Palms</title>.  Random House, 1939.</item>
    </list>
  </div>
</back>