<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>STUDIES IN BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <author>DAVID L. VANDER MEULEN</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
          <name>Transcription Team, University Library</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia</publisher>
        <pubPlace>By The University of Virginia Press, Charlottesville</pubPlace>
        <date>Volume Sixty-One, 2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Studies in Bibliography, ed. David L. Vander Meulen, Vol. 61 (2025)</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <pb/>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">STUDIES IN BIBLIOGRAPHY</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <pb/>
        <pb/>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">STUDIES IN BIBLIOGRAPHY</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">
            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edited by DAVID L. VANDER MEULEN</hi>
          </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA PRESS, CHARLOTTESVILLE</byline>
        <docImprint>
          <publisher>
            <hi rend="smallcaps">THE BIBLIOGRAPHICAL SOCIETY OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</hi>
          </publisher>
          <pubPlace>
            <hi rend="smallcaps">BY THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA PRESS, CHARLOTTESVILLE</hi>
          </pubPlace>
          <date>Volume Sixty-One, 2025</date>
        </docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="colophon">
        <pb/>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Founding Editor</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <name type="pname">Fredson Bowers</name> (<date>1905–1991</date>)
        </p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Assistant to the Editor</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <name type="pname">Elizabeth K. Lynch</name>
        </p>
        <p>THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA PRESS</p>
        <p>Copyright © <date>2025</date> by the Rector and Visitors
          <lb/>of the University of Virginia
        </p>
        <p>Virginia. University. Bibliographical Society.</p>
        <p>Studies in bibliography; papers v.1—</p>
        <p><date>1948 / 49</date>—</p>
        <p>
          <name type="place">Charlottesville.</name>
        </p>
        <p>v. illus. 26cm. annual.</p>
        <p>Title varies: <date>1948 / 49</date>—</p>
        <p>1. Bibliography—Societies. I. Title.</p>
        <p>z1008.V55</p>
        <p>010.6275549–3353 Rev.*</p>
        <p>ISBN 978-0-8139-4261-2</p>
        <p>
          The editor invites articles and notes on analytical bibliography, textual<lb/>criticism,
          manuscript study, the history of printing and publishing, and<lb/>related
          matters of method and evidence. Submissions consistent with any<lb/>widely used
          style sheet are acceptable, although <hi rend="italic">The Chicago Manual of Style</hi>
          <lb/>is preferred. All copy, <hi rend="italic">including quotations and notes</hi>, should be double-spaced.
          <lb/>Send manuscripts or electronic files to
          <name type="pname">David Vander Meulen</name>
          (dlv8g@<lb/>virginia.edu), University of
          <name type="place">Virginia</name>, English Department, 219 Bryan Hall,
          <lb/>PO Box 400121,
          <name type="place">Charlottesville</name>, VA 22904-4121.
        </p>
        <p>
          All correspondence concerning business affairs, including subscriptions<lb/>and
          memberships, should be sent to the Executive Secretary,
          <name type="pname">Anne G.<lb/>Ribble</name>, Bibliographical Society,
          Edgar Shannon Library, PO Box<lb/>400152,
          <name type="place">Charlottesville</name>, VA 22904-4152.
        </p>
        <p>This journal is a member of the Council of Editors of Learned Journals.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="content">
        <pb/>
        <head>Contents</head>
        <table>
          <row>
            <cell>John Carter: An Assessment and a Handlist<br/>By G. Thomas Tanselle</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The Sources of the Sussex Declaration: A Reconsideration<br/>By John Bidwell</cell>
            <cell>105</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>A Documentary History of the University of Virginia’s First Library and Its Jeffersonian Catalogs<br/>By Samuel V. Lemley, Neal D. Curtis, and Madeline Zehnder</cell>
            <cell>127</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>“Capítulo de una novela en prensa”: Teaser Chapters and Marketing Strategies in Victoria Ocampo’s Sur<br/>By Nora C. Benedict</cell>
            <cell>167</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The Engravings of Pope’s Works II (1735): ‘Envy must own, I live among the Great’<br/>By James McLaverty</cell>
            <cell>187</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Jonathan Richardson, Charles Chauncy, and the Manuscripts of Pope<br/>By John Considine</cell>
            <cell>221</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Extra-Illustrating Horace Walpole’s Description of Strawberry Hill: Three Case Studies<br/>By Stephen Clarke</cell>
            <cell>233</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Charles Dibdin and the Making of The Musical Tour of Mr. Dibdin (1788): A New “compact with the public”<br/>By David Chandler</cell>
            <cell>255</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Stages of Composition in Charlotte Brontë’s Fair-Copy Manuscript of Shirley<br/>By Barbara Heritage</cell>
            <cell>271</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>“The Brothers” and the English Comte de Gabalis<br/>By Joscelyn Godwin</cell>
            <cell>323</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Three Endings: Fitzgerald, Hemingway, Faulkner<br/>By James L. W. West III</cell>
            <cell>331</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>*     *     *     *     **     *     *     *     *</cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Notes on Contributors</cell>
            <cell>345</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia</cell>
            <cell>347</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Members</cell>
            <cell>348</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Available Publications</cell>
            <cell>353</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Programs</cell>
            <cell>355</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Student Awards in Book Collecting</cell>
            <cell>356</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Battestin Fellowships</cell>
            <cell>356</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div>
    </front>
<body>
<pb n="1"/>
<head>John Carter: An Assessment<lb/>and a Handlist</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">G. Thomas Tanselle</name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">J</hi>ohn carter was one of the most prominent and significant figures in the Anglo-American book world in the twentieth<lb/>century. Indeed, he held a unique position, for he distinguished<lb/>himself as a bookseller, a collector, a scholar, and a writer, equally<lb/>at home and equally recognized on both sides of the Atlantic.<lb/>He created innovative rare-book catalogues for the Scribner Book Store;<lb/>formed several notable collections, especially of Catullus and Housman;<lb/>was a pioneer investigator of the bibliographical problems of nineteenth-<lb/>century publishers’ bindings; performed (with Graham Pollard) a classic<lb/>piece of bibliographical detection in uncovering the Wise-Forman forger-<lb/>ies; produced a scholarly edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s <hi>Urne Buriall</hi> and<lb/><hi>the Garden of Cyrus</hi>; and wrote (or co-wrote or co-edited) several celebrated<lb/>works—<hi>An Enquiry into the Nature of Certain Nineteenth Century Pamphlets</hi><lb/>(1934), <hi>Taste and Technique in Book-Collecting</hi> (1948), <hi>ABC for Book-Collectors</hi><lb/>(1952), and <hi>Printing and the Mind of Man</hi> (1967).</p>
<p>A record of his published writings is obviously a basic guide to his ac-<lb/>complishment. But such a record is also desirable for another reason that<lb/>would not apply to many people: nearly every piece he wrote, no matter<lb/>how small (including brief reviews and letters to editors), is worth reading<lb/>for its style and wit. I am therefore presenting here a handlist (following in<lb/>Carter’s tradition of handlist-writing) that will enable readers to find these<lb/>pieces. Carter published so prolifically (some 1500 items are known) in such<lb/>a wide array of venues that there are bound to be many items I have missed,<lb/>especially among his letters to editors. But what is here is a comprehensive<lb/>nucleus to which additions can be made. As Carter said in his handlist of<lb/>Stanley Morison, it is “intended to serve as a series of signposts now and as<lb/>a basis for amplification, correction and addition in the future.”</p>
<p>As an introduction to the handlist, I shall attempt a brief assessment of<lb/>Carter’s achievement, which is a by-product of the overview provided by<lb/>the handlist. It is inevitably biographical to some extent; but the empha-<lb/>sis is on Carter’s writings, not his life, because a book-length biography<lb/>already exists: Donald C. Dickinson’s <hi>John Carter: The Taste and Technique of</hi><lb/></p>
<pb n="2"/>
<p> <lb/>a Bookman (2004). The biographical details selected for mention here and <lb/>in the handlist (many of which do not appear in the Dickinson book) are <lb/>those that seem to me most relevant for understanding the background <lb/>and context of his writings and his wide influence. I knew John Carter for <lb/>only the last ten years of his life: some of my recollections were written <lb/>up in section 36 of my memoir, “The Living Room” (published in vol-<lb/>ume 59 of <hi>Studies in Bibliography</hi> and then in <hi>Books in My Life</hi>, 2021), and <lb/>I dedicated my book about book-jackets to his memory. I shall not forget <lb/>the many kindnesses he showed me and the important favors he did for <lb/>me, and the present offering is a reflection of my gratitude.</p>
<head>ASSESSMENT</head>
<head>The 1930s</head>
<p>John Carter’s first post-collegiate publication on a bookish subject, an <lb/>article on “Original Condition” in the 15 November 1930 issue of <hi>Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, <lb/>came only three years after college and inaugurated an amaz-<lb/>ing four-year period of brilliant productivity. Born John Waynflete Carter <lb/>at Eton on 10 May 1905, he was educated at Eton and King’s College <lb/>Cambridge, where he achieved a double first in the classical tripos and <lb/>an honors degree in 1927. By that time he was already collecting Catullus <lb/>and had become interested in textual criticism through the influence of A. <lb/>E. Housman’s lectures. Almost immediately after leaving Cambridge he <lb/>was hired (in September 1927) by the London office of Charles Scribner’s <lb/>Sons to locate rare books to be sold in their New York shop. In the three <lb/>years between then and that 1930 article, he was becoming acquainted <lb/>with the book dealers and collectors both in Britain and in America (his <lb/>first visit to New York being January to April 1929). But he was clearly do-<lb/>ing more, for his first three letters to the <hi>Times Literary Supplement</hi> (in 1931-<lb/>33) show that by then he was already immersed in research on Sir Thomas <lb/>Browne, publishers’ bindings, and the pamphlets that became known as <lb/>the Wise-Forman forgeries—the subjects of his first major publications <lb/>(and of his early articles for the main book-collecting journals of the time, <lb/><hi>The Book Collector’s Quarterly</hi> in England and <hi>The Colophon</hi> in America). <lb/>In May 1932 he published <hi>Binding Variants in English Publishing, 1820-</hi><lb/>1900 as the sixth volume in Michael Sadleir’s important <hi>Bibliographia</hi> se-<lb/>ries, which had the significant subtitle “Studies in Book History and Book <lb/>Structure” (where “structure” makes clear the interest in bibliographical <lb/>analysis). Sadleir, a publisher (Constable was his firm), novelist, and col-<lb/>lector, had already established himself (he was sixteen and a half years <lb/>older than Carter) as a bibliographical scholar and a pioneer historian <lb/>of publishers’ bindings. He had published a bibliography of Trollope in <lb/>1928 (a landmark through its explicit demonstration that an author bibli-</p>
<pb n="3"/>
<p>ography can be a contribution to the history of publishing); and two years<lb/>
later <hi>The Evolution of Publishers’ Bindings Styles, 1770-1900</hi> came out as the<lb/>
first volume in his Bibliographia series. Carter’s admiration for Sadleir<lb/>
is suggested by a letter he wrote to <hi>The Times</hi> on 20 December 1957 to<lb/>
supplement <hi>The Times</hi>’s obituary of Sadleir: “None of those who moved<lb/>
in his orbit . . . was ever made to feel a satellite. But in our corner of the<lb/>
sky a star has fallen.” An “avowed disciple” of Sadleir (as he called himself<lb/>
in a 1970 article), Carter had been following Sadleir’s lead in investigat-<lb/>
ing edition binding; and he had published articles on the subject in 1931<lb/>
and 1932 that he was able to incorporate into his 1932 book. In the first<lb/>
chapter of that book, he modestly called it “a rather swollen appendix” to<lb/>
Sadleir’s book, but it is much more than that in several ways.<lb/>
</p>
<p>First, the chapter called “Historical,” though it is a condensed ac-<lb/>
count of the beginnings and early use of cloth for bindings, draws on his<lb/>
own original research in publishers’ catalogues and trade journals. Sec-<lb/>
ond, the bulk of the first half is a detailed account of how to go about in-<lb/>
vestigating the bindings of nineteenth-century books and determining the<lb/>
order of variant bindings. He touches on the use of publishers’ records<lb/>
and catalogues, review copies, inscriptions, inserted advertisements, end-<lb/>
papers, and edge treatments, among much else, and he deals with such<lb/>
topics as special bindings, series variants, and bindings-up of parts, along<lb/>
with the description of cloth grains. The first half of the book (“General”),<lb/>
which also includes a “specimen investigation,” provides a “method of<lb/>
attack” that is then applied in the second half (“Particular”) to numerous<lb/>
books by some five dozen authors. This extensive survey of examples,<lb/>
based on the examination of an impressive number of copies, is yet an-<lb/>
other contribution of the book, making it useful for reference—and in<lb/>
the process displaying Carter’s cautious and undogmatic way of reaching <lb/>
conclusions.<lb/>
</p>
<p>The book is addressed to “students and amateurs of book-structure”<lb/>
(p. xi), and Carter is concerned throughout to advance bibliographical<lb/>
study. He hopes to show “what an immensely important part of bibliog-<lb/>
raphy they [binding variants] become when they are taken seriously,” and<lb/>
he wants to help “develop a scientific method on general lines for dealing<lb/>
with so frequent a phenomenon” (p. 6). He makes clear that “the attitude<lb/>
of mind most desirable in a bibliographer is suspicion” (p. 39), and he<lb/>
stresses the necessity for examining multiple copies. His more specific<lb/>
observations on analyzing bindings form a perfect set of instructions for<lb/>
the beginner on how best to approach a nineteenth-century book: they<lb/>
have not been superseded, nor have they been stated in more attractive<lb/>
prose. Of the several pioneer studies of publishers’ bindings by Carter and<lb/>
Sadleir, this one is the most continuingly useful, still valuable as a guide.<lb/>
</p>
<p>A few months after <hi>Binding Variants</hi>, another of Carter’s major pub-<lb/>
lications came out: his edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s <hi>Urne Buriall</hi> and<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="4"/>
 the Garden of Cyrus (originally published in 1658, with “Urne Buriall” as a<lb/>
 subtitle to “Hydriotaphia”). It was a lavish production, elegantly printed<lb/>
 by the Curwen Press and published (in an edition of 215 copies) by Cassell<lb/>
 &amp; Company with thirty drawings by Paul Nash (printed by collotype and<lb/>
 colored by pochoir) and a morocco and vellum binding designed by him.<lb/>
 This handsome book is regularly regarded as one of the masterpieces of<lb/>
 twentieth-century book production—as, for example, in Martin Hutner<lb/>
 and Jerry Kelly’s A Century for a Century (Grolier Club, 1999). But the work<lb/>
 also makes a scholarly contribution to the study of Browne. Carter had<lb/>
 been reading Browne since his Eton days, and by the early 1930s he was<lb/>
 on the trail of author-corrected copies of the first edition (as his letter to<lb/>
 the Times Literary Supplement on 16 July 1931 shows), while he was working<lb/>
 on a new edition, at the request of Desmond Flower (of Cassell’s). He was<lb/>
 able to locate and use six such copies before his edition came out, only<lb/>
 two of which had previously been known. The thoroughness of his work<lb/>
 is symbolized by his annotated copy of Edward H. Marshall’s 1929 Mac-<lb/>
 millan edition: its leaves, mounted on larger paper, were interleaved with<lb/>
 blanks, which were covered with his notes reporting collations, references,<lb/>
 and critical observations (described in G. F. Sims catalogue 102 [1979],<lb/>
 item 85). As he noted in his introduction, he had collated all editions be-<lb/>
 fore 1800 and all published in Great Britain since then (though he does<lb/>
 not mention collating multiple copies of the early editions).<lb/>
 <hi rend="dropcap">C</hi>arter’s editorial approach was admirable. Because the successive<lb/>
 lifetime editions were unreliable, he based his text on the first edition<lb/>
 and reported all his departures from it (except the correction of turned,<lb/>
 dropped, or transposed letters), as well as the results of his collations.<lb/>
 Aside from the adoption of Browne’s own corrections, the departures<lb/>
 were few because he retained the punctuation and spelling of the first<lb/>
 edition (except the long s and the “sporadic” use of v for u). He correctly<lb/>
 recognized that Browne’s “use of commas and semicolons, like his use of<lb/>
 initial capitals and italics is too much a part of himself and his period to<lb/>
 submit to this wholesale modernization [of earlier editors].” Nevertheless<lb/>
 he did make an “irreducible minimum of corrections where the com-<lb/>
 positor’s carelessness has produced intolerable obscurity.” Clearly there<lb/>
 is room for disagreement here, for some of the obscurity may not have<lb/>
 been caused by the compositor, and in any case what is intolerable is a<lb/>
 subjective matter. But critical editing necessarily entails judgment, and<lb/>
 these alterations are all recorded in the notes. The introduction ends with<lb/>
 a gracious point not often made: although he has criticized earlier edi-<lb/>
 tions, he says, “one cannot begin to criticize an edition until one has used<lb/>
 it thoroughly, so that criticism becomes almost a proof of obligation.”<lb/>
 <hi rend="dropcap">O</hi>n 2 July 1934, less than two years after the Browne edition, Carter’s<lb/>
 third major publication appeared—the one that made him a book-world<lb/>
</body>
  </text>
</TEI>
