<div type="section" n="7">
  <head>Extra-Illustrating Horace Walpole’s Description of Strawberry Hill: Three Case Studies</head>
<pb n="240"/>
<p>distributed copies to friends as directed. This edition had a complex printing<lb/>
history, but the essential points are that it was not published or circulated during<lb/>
Walpole’s lifetime, nor was it shown to the many visitors who obtained tickets to<lb/>
be shown Walpole’s celebrated and curious house and collection.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><lb/></p>
<head>I</head>
<p>For the 1784 edition Walpole provided a preface, a brief but elegant testament<lb/>
of faith, accounting for his use of Gothic ornament at Strawberry Hill, cel-<lb/>\nebrating the great cabinets from which his collection was acquired, noting the<lb/>
miniatures and historic royal portraits and other highlights of the collection,<lb/>
and concluding with a flourish of justification, part whimsical and part defiant,<lb/>
of the “small capricious house … built to please my own taste, and in some<lb/>
degree to realize my own visions.”<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The body of the text then introduces the<lb/>
house and its setting, and proceeds to describe its interior, room by room. The<lb/>
decorative chimney pieces and plasterwork and other features are recorded, and<lb/>
there is a minute catalogue of the furniture, pictures, sculpture, bronzes, china,<lb/>
and curiosities that each room displayed, while the accompanying engravings<lb/>
show the exterior, the grounds, a number of the chimney pieces, and some of<lb/>
the major rooms.<lb/></p>
<p>The detailed account of the house and its contents of the 1784 edition in-<lb/>
vited extra-illustration, and in Walpole’s immediate circle there were a number<lb/>
of sumptuous copies—such as Walpole’s own, with the ninety-six quarto pages<lb/>
of the 1784 edition inlaid into an elephant folio expanded to over two hundred<lb/>
pages.<hi rend="sup">4</hi> He employed a succession of artists to provide illustrations and record<lb/>
his creation at Strawberry Hill, of whom the most prolific were Edward Edwards<lb/>
(1738–1806) and John Carter (1748–1817). Edwards provided watercolors that<lb/>
were engraved for the prints that appear in the 1784 edition of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>,<lb/>
and Carter, an artist, antiquary, and polemist for the conservation of Gothic<lb/>
architecture, worked at Strawberry Hill through the 1780s.<lb/></p>
<p>Walpole’s copy is matched for richness by that compiled by his correspondent<lb/>
Richard Bull (1721–1805)—but then Bull’s commitment to extra-illustration was<lb/>
heroic in its scale, and he illustrated at least sixteen titles from Walpole’s Straw-<lb/>
berry Hill Press. His copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> is enriched by more watercolors<lb/>
by Carter than is Walpole’s copy. Various other generously illustrated copies<lb/>
of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> from Walpole’s circle are known, including the copy com-<lb/>
piled by Carter for himself, which contains his sketches for some of the finished<lb/></p>
<note place="foot">
<lb/>2. For the complex printing history of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, see Stephen Clarke, “‘Lord God!<lb/>
Jesus! What a House!’: Describing and Visiting Strawberry Hill,” <hi rend="italic">Journal for Eighteenth-Century<lb/>
Studies</hi>, 33.3 (September 2010), 357–380.<lb/>
<lb/>3. Horace Walpole, <hi rend="italic">A Description of the Villa of Mr. Horace Walpole, youngest son of Sir Robert<lb/>
Walpole Earl of Orford, at Strawberry-Hill near Twickenham, Middlesex. With an Inventory of the Fur-<lb/>
niture, Pictures, Curiosities, &amp;c.</hi> (Strawberry Hill: Not published, 1784), iv.<lb/>
<lb/>4. Walpole’s extra-illustrated copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> is at the Lewis Walpole Library, Yale<lb/>
University, 49 3582.<lb/>
</note>
<pb n="241"/>
<p><lb/>watercolors in Bull’s copy; the copy of Charles Bedford (1742–1814), Walpole’s<lb/>Deputy in the office of Usher of the Exchequer; and two copies of his printer<lb/>Thomas Kirgate (1734/5–1810).<hi rend="sup">5</hi><lb/>These issues have been discussed and analyzed in detail by Nicolas<lb/>Barker in his edition of Charles Bedford’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> printed for the<lb/>Roxburghe Club.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Barker summarizes the history of extra-illustration and Walpole’s<lb/>involvement with James Granger and the Strawberry Hill Press and the print collec-<lb/>tors Bull and Anthony Storer (1746–99). He points out what an appealing subject<lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> offered, with an increasing number of engraved images of Strawberry<lb/>Hill becoming available on the market from the 1790s.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> These engravings were<lb/>accessible to collectors outside Walpole’s circle—and for them the essential<lb/>providers were the Harding family of booksellers and artists, at their shop in<lb/>Pall Mall.<lb/></p>
<head>II</head>
<p><lb/><hi rend="dropcap">S</hi>ilvester Harding (1745–1809) trained as a miniature painter and exhibited<lb/>at the Royal Academy from 1776. In 1786 with his younger brother Edward<lb/>(1755–1840) he opened a book and printseller’s shop in Fleet Street, moving<lb/>in 1792 to 102 Pall Mall. They specialized in theatrical and historical portraits,<lb/>and in 1789–93 published in numbers <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare Illustrated</hi> by an assemblage of<lb/><hi rend="italic">Portraits and Views</hi>, and in 1793 an edition of Anthony Hamilton’s<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Count Grammont</hi>, also illustrated with portraits. In the meanwhile Silvester Harding had<lb/>been introduced to Strawberry Hill in the early 1780s by the merchant and art<lb/>collector Nathaniel Hillier (c. 1707–83) and became a great friend of Walpole’s<lb/>printer Kirgate.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> From 1795 the Hardings published <hi rend="italic">The Biographical Mirrour</hi>,<lb/>a series of historical portraits with supporting text, and also in 1796 Bürger’s<lb/><hi rend="italic">Leonora</hi> and in 1797 Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Fables</hi>, both with engravings after drawings by<lb/></p>
<p><lb/><hi rend="sup">5</hi> Bull’s copy is at the Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, 33 30 copy 11; Carter’s<lb/>copy is at the Huntington Library, San Marino, 130368; Bedford’s copy is in the possession of<lb/>Lord Waldegrave of North Hill; and two copies that had belonged to Kirgate are at the Lewis<lb/>Walpole Library, 33 30 copy 6 and 33 30 copy 29.<lb/></p>
<p><lb/><hi rend="sup">6</hi> <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Description of the Villa at Strawberry-Hill: A facsimile of the copy extra-<lb/>illustrated for Charles Bedford in the collection of Lord Waldegrave of North Hill</hi>, ed. Nicolas Barker<lb/>(London: The Roxburghe Club, 2010). This discussion has recently been extended by Peltz in<lb/>Parts I and II of <hi rend="italic">Facing the Text</hi>.<lb/></p>
<p><lb/><hi rend="sup">7</hi> It is significant that lot 300 of the second part of the sale catalogue of the print collec-<lb/>tion of Sir Mark Masterman Sykes in 1824 was “a valuable collection of prints and drawings,<lb/>in colours &amp;c. … to illustrate Lord Orford’s Seat at Strawberry Hill, uniformly mounted, and<lb/>arranged for the purpose of binding, in a Russia Portfolio, lettered Strawberry Hill, and Mu-<lb/>seum.” This was bought by the print dealer Woodburn for £47–5–0, a ready-made collection<lb/>of images which Woodburn’s eventual customer could no doubt take out of its portfolio and<lb/>bind up in a copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>. Similarly, lot 314 on the third day of the sale in 1825 of<lb/>prints and drawings of George Baker, collector and bibliographer of the Strawberry Hill Press,<lb/>consisted of views of the house and contents, including many proof impressions of the portraits,<lb/>ripe for use in extra-illustration.<lb/></p>
<p><lb/><hi rend="sup">8</hi> Nathaniel Hillier to Walpole, 19 October 1780, <hi rend="italic">Yale Edition of Horace Walpole’s Correspondence</hi>,<lb/>16: 95–97.<lb/></p>
<pb n="242"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">W</hi>alpole’s protégée Lady Diana Beauclerk. In 1793 they published six plates to<lb/>
illustrate Walpole’s <hi rend="italic">The Castle of Otranto</hi>, and these are often seen in those copies<lb/>
that had not already been sold and bound up of the sixth edition printed for<lb/>
Dodsley and Bodoni’s edition printed in Parma (both 1791). Sometime before<lb/>
1798 the partnership dissolved, Silvester moving along the street to 127, while<lb/>
Edward moved to 98 Pall Mall until in 1803 he was appointed librarian to<lb/>
Queen Charlotte, for whose amusement he grangerized a number of historical<lb/>
works.<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">S</hi>ilvester Harding had two artist sons; Edward, who died young, and George<lb/>
Perfect Harding (1779/80–1853). George exhibited as a miniaturist at the Royal<lb/>
Academy from 1802 until 1840 —in 1839 submitting “The Library at Strawberry<lb/>
Hill, Seat of the Earl of Waldegrave,” current whereabouts unknown. For about<lb/>
forty years, from 1804, he travelled the country copying portraits, carefully re-<lb/>
cording dates and signatures. His watercolors are precise, finished, and compact,<lb/>
with sparing use of gold for rules and signatures. His notebooks of these travels<lb/>
survive at the National Portrait Gallery, four bound volumes of his “List of Por-<lb/>
traits, Pictures, in Various Mansions of the United Kingdom,” the fourth volume<lb/>
containing a list of manuscripts and printed books illustrated by him, with a list of<lb/>
pictures in the possession of the Crown. The second volume, a 358-page manu-<lb/>
script to which a table of contents and index are added, records the pictures he<lb/>
inspected at 141 properties, mostly country houses, but also universities, livery<lb/>
companies, and Inns of Court. At the foot of the title page is the note “Those<lb/>
that are mark’d thus X, have been copyed by G. P. Harding.” In that volume as<lb/>
in the others, most entries are of one page per property, a few extending to four<lb/>
or even five pages: for Tottenham Park in Wiltshire, for example, the seat of the<lb/>
Marquis of Ailesbury, Harding listed 101 portraits over five pages, of which six<lb/>
were marked with a cross as having been copied by him. But this, and all the<lb/>
other properties in the volume, is eclipsed by Strawberry Hill. In a list extend-<lb/>
ing over twenty pages, with headings for the different rooms, Harding lists 433<lb/>
portraits, of which he notes with his cross that he had copied sixty-four. Where<lb/>
he adds commentary to the name of the sitter, he takes or adapts the text from<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>. And this wealth of images is in addition to the numerous portraits<lb/>
that his father had copied there.<hi rend="sup">9</hi><lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he watercolors and prints by the Hardings of portraits and other items from<lb/>
the collection at Strawberry Hill run from Silvester Harding’s introduction to the<lb/>
house in the early 1780s to George’s watercolor of the library, noted above, of<lb/>
1839. Of their published works, twenty-three of the 151 plates in the <hi rend="italic">Biographical<lb/>Mirrour</hi> are from portraits at Strawberry Hill, while in 1803 Silvester Harding<lb/>
published <hi rend="italic">A Series of Portraits, to Illustrate the Earl of Orford’s Catalogue, of Royal and</hi><lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">9</hi>. NPG MS47. George Perfect Harding was the subject of a display at the National Por-<lb/>
trait Gallery, “The Tudors Reimagined: George Perfect Harding c. 1779–1853” (2015). See<lb/>
also W. S. Lewis, <hi rend="italic">The Forlorn Printer: Being Notes on Horace Walpole’s Alleged Neglect of Thomas<lb/>Kirgate</hi> (Farmington: Privately printed, 1931), and Stephen Clarke, <hi rend="italic">The Strawberry Hill Press<lb/>&amp; its Printing House: An Account and an Iconography</hi> (New Haven: Lewis Walpole Library, Yale<lb/>
University, 2011), 51 and 86–91.<lb/></p>
<pb n="243"/>
<p>Noble Authors, an eight-page pamphlet listing the authors’ portraits and the pages <lb/>
on which they appeared, providing the print collector with a checklist to work <lb/>
against. (A similar checklist for another title much favored by illustrators, A Co-<lb/>
pious Index to Pennant’s Account of London, was produced for the burgeoning army <lb/>
of illustrators by Thomas Downe in 1814.) The Hardings appear to have shared <lb/>
access to Strawberry Hill with Silvester and Edward senior’s brother-in-law, the <lb/>
engraver William Bawtree, and such access seems to have been continued to be <lb/>
afforded to them when after Walpole’s death the house was occupied by Anne <lb/>
Damer, who was there until 1811. It has long been known that Kirgate oper-<lb/>
ated with increasing autonomy at the end of Walpole’s life (hence his reprinting <lb/>
Strawberry Hill Press items in the year of Walpole’s death, presumably for his <lb/>
own benefit), and he is the essential link in enabling the Hardings to accumulate <lb/>
the images they needed to satisfy the demands of their print collector customers.<lb/></p>
<head>III</head>
<p>Kirgate had originally been employed by Walpole for five months in 1765 to <lb/>
finish off printing the second edition of the <hi rend="italic">Anecdotes of Painting</hi>, <lb/>
and was then <lb/>
discharged when Walpole left for Paris. He was re-engaged in April 1768 and <lb/>
stayed with Walpole until Walpole’s death nearly thirty years later, working as <lb/>
printer, secretary, and general factotum. Much has been written on his role in <lb/>
re-printing earlier Strawberry Hill pamphlets at the same press in the year of <lb/>
Walpole’s death, and the extremely modest sum of £100 left him in Walpole’s <lb/>
will.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> What is quite clear is that before leaving Strawberry Hill in 1797, Kirgate <lb/>
printed an address card for himself, “Thomas Kirgate, Late Printer at Straw-<lb/>
berry-Hill, Print and Bookseller, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 127, Pall-Mall”—that being the address <lb/>
of Silvester Harding’s shop. He subsequently moved to a house in Vine Street, <lb/>
Piccadilly, where he sold books and curiosities. Kirgate’s role in satisfying the <lb/>
needs of collectors and extra-illustrators cannot be better summarized than in an <lb/>
undated letter he wrote to Charles Bedford which has been quoted elsewhere, <lb/>
but merits repeating here:<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">George Harding had not finished the Drawing of the Duc de Nivernois till this morning, <lb/>
nor could I get Sir Kenelm Digby before yesterday, or I should have sent sooner. The late <lb/>
and present Sales afford nothing but what is extravagantly dear. A Guinea is a low price <lb/>
now for a scarce Print—upwards of Forty was given for one of a Duke of Norfolk, t’other <lb/>
day at Richardson’s. Five, Ten, nay Twenty Guineas, is readily given for a Print, that has <lb/>
no other value but scarcity. Illustrators of Granger, and other books, care less for Money <lb/>
than Portraits; the Rage for which increases—’tis a Madness which I hope will not reach <lb/>
Brixton [Bedford’s address]. The few Ladies you want for p. 16 &amp; 17, I do not think you <lb/>
will ever get; I bid upwards of a Guinea for one, the Duchess of Somerset, but she scorned <lb/>
such a paltry offer. Tis lucky, Sir, you want but such a few Prints to complete your Book; <lb/>
had you just begun to collect for it, you would soon quit the pursuit. I despair of finishing <lb/>
my Strawberry which I have now in hand.<lb/></hi></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">10.</hi> See Lewis, <hi rend="italic">The Forlorn Printer</hi>; A. T. Hazen, <hi rend="italic">A Bibliography of the Strawberry Hill Press</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1942), 12–14; Barker, <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Description of the Villa</hi>, 99; and Clarke, <hi rend="italic">The Strawberry Hill Press &amp; its Printing House</hi>, 47–53.<lb/></p>
<pb n="244"/>
<p>I know not when I shall have the Pleasure of seeing you, Sir, for I can get nothing to bring;<lb/>
and am so infirm, I cannot walk far. But I shall not forget to search for the few you still<lb/>
want. As soon as I can see Bawtree, I will get him to make a Drawing of the Bed in the<lb/>
Holbein Room, for I despair of getting Carter to do it Nor is Geo. Harding very willing to<lb/>
make any more Drawings—he has had the one now sent upwards of a Fortnight in hand.<ref target="#n11"><hi rend="sup">11</hi></ref></p>

<p>This letter is revealing on a number of levels. It shows Kirgate as facilitator,<lb/>
orchestrating the acquisition of missing prints for the collector while complain-<lb/>
ing about the exploding market in portrait prints, and displays George Harding’s<lb/>
role as provider of drawings. It also illustrates the somewhat obsessional needs of<lb/>
the collector, has Kirgate acknowledging that he is himself compiling an extra-<lb/>
illustrated copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, and offers the possibly illusory prospect of<lb/>
“finishing” one’s extra-illustrated book.</p>

<p>Kirgate offered his own extra-illustrated copy by raffle in 1801. The broad-<lb/>
sheet advertising the sale, “For the Benefit of T. Kirgate, Late Printer at Straw-<lb/>
berry-Hill,” announced that:</p>

<quote>Each Leaf of the above Book is inlaid on a large Sheet of fine Dutch paper; the Pages bor-<lb/>
dered with a double Line of red Ink; the Title printed in three Colours, and ornamented<lb/>
with a Drawing of a Foliage of Strawberries. The whole Book adorned with upwards of<lb/>
Two [crossed through in manuscript and amended to three] Hundred Drawings and<lb/>
Prints, illustrative of the external and internal Parts of that delightful Seat, its Furniture,<lb/>
Pictures, Sculptures, Antiquities, &amp;c. &amp;c. Several of the Prints are scarce and valuable,<lb/>
and most of the Drawings were made on Purpose for the Book, by the Friends of <hi rend="smallcaps">T. KIRGATE</hi>, who<lb/>
has been Fourteen Years in forming the Collection.<ref target="#n12"><hi rend="sup">12</hi></ref></quote>

<p>Potential subscribers could inspect the book at Harding’s shop in Pall Mall.<lb/>
The current whereabouts of the book are unknown, but it appears to have been a<lb/>
particularly fine example of Kirgate’s industry in the years after he had left Straw-<lb/>
berry Hill. Another example of his endeavors is an elephant folio scrapbook of im-<lb/>
ages of Strawberry Hill and its contents, perhaps used to display to customers what<lb/>
images could be acquired or copied for the extra-illustrated copy they ordered:<lb/>
this is now in the collection of Lord Waldegrave of North Hill. There is also at the<lb/>
Lewis Walpole Library a volume compiled by Kirgate consisting of lists of images<lb/>
from the house. Firstly, there is a two-page list of forty-six pictures and sculptures<lb/>
there, with page references to the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, twenty-four of them crossed through<lb/>
(perhaps as having already been obtained) and with Kirgate’s comments in red<lb/>
ink against almost all of the others—two prints of Rubens’s house “both scarce,”<lb/>
Anne Hyde Duchess of York “A foreign print, 8vo. scarce,” others “Engraving by<lb/>
Harding” or “In my List,” while of four portraits in the Gallery described on page<lb/>
52 he notes “I cannot say positively if there are Prints of these, the Pictures hang-<lb/>
ing too high to examine.” This is followed by a list dated 26 July 1800 of twelve<lb/>
drawings, with their <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> page numbers and prices, and then two longer lists,<lb/>
one “A List of the Prints and Drawings as placed in Lord Orford’s Illustrated Copy<lb/>
of the <hi rend="italic">Description of Strawberry-Hill</hi> printed there in 1784 by Thos. Kirgate,” the<lb/>
other a list of the 335 prints and drawings in his own copy. The historical portraits</p>

<note xml:id="n11" place="foot">Kirgate MSS. Folder, Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University; quoted in Barker, Hor-<lb/>
ace Walpole’s <hi rend="italic">Description of the Villa</hi>, 116; and Clarke, <hi rend="italic">The Strawberry Hill Press &amp; its Printing House</hi>, 87–89 (where it is explained that the letter, though undated, is probably of 1801).</note>

<note xml:id="n12" place="foot">Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, 53 K634 801.</note>
<pb n="245"/>
<p>that formed such a prominent part of the Strawberry Hill collection were pregnant <lb/>with possibilities for any print collector who knew his Granger, and Kirgate and <lb/>the Hardings were only too happy to meet that demand.</p>
<p>Kirgate died in 1810, and the sale of his collection was conducted by King <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> Lochée over ten days that December, immediately followed by a further day’s <lb/>supplemental sale. The auction catalogue contained multiple copies of Strawberry <lb/>Hill Press items, over eighty lots on the second day, and in the supplemental sale <lb/>ninety-eight lots of “Books Printed chiefly at Strawberry-Hill.” On the ninth day <lb/>there were more than two hundred drawings and prints of the house in twenty-nine <lb/>lots, with the artists listed including Carter, J.&amp;nbsp;C. Barrow, Edwards, the Hardings, <lb/>and Kirgate himself. This was followed by sixty-nine lots of prints in the supple- <lb/>mental sale, many of them related to Strawberry Hill. Both Edward and George <lb/>Harding appear among the successful bidders (Silvester had died the previous <lb/>year) and it seems clear that what was on offer was the remains of Kirgate’s stock.</p>
<head>IV</head>
<p>The first of the three extra-illustrated copies of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> here discussed is <lb/>chosen because it represents precisely what a collector with no connection to <lb/>Walpole or his circle could have acquired from the Hardings’ shop in Pall Mall. <lb/>Unlike the two other copies that will be considered, it is known and recorded: it <lb/>has been at the Huntington Library, San Marino, for over one hundred years, <lb/>having been acquired by Huntington at the sale of Robert Hoe’s library. It is <lb/>bound in green morocco with a title page printed in black, red, and blue, and it <lb/>has a total of seventy-three additional items bound into it, the large majority of <lb/>which have been listed by Nicolas Barker.<hi rend="sup">13</hi></p>
<p>The backbone of the illustrations is formed by thirty-two portrait prints by <lb/>the Hardings, largely stipple engravings from portraits at Strawberry Hill, of <lb/>which the earliest is dated 1792, the latest 1806. These stipple engravings are <lb/>almost all after Silvester Harding, who with his brother Edward was the leading <lb/>figure in providing drawings for engraving in stipple, whereas it appears that his <lb/>son George was primarily a painter and copyist.</p>
<p>In addition to the Harding stipple engravings, there are twenty-nine miscel- <lb/>laneous prints or printed items. These vary from the readily obtainable, such as <lb/>the views of Strawberry Hill from Birch’s <hi rend="italic">Delices de la Grande Bretagne</hi> (1791) and <lb/>from Boydell’s <hi rend="italic">History of the River Thames</hi> (1794–96), to items more directly as- <lb/>sociated with the Press at Strawberry—for example, Edwards’s scarce etching of <lb/>Kirgate, scarce because (as Edwards explained to Bull in a letter of 18 December <lb/>1784, when presenting him with a copy) “Mr.&amp;nbsp;Walpole thought fit to be offended <lb/>at its being done &amp; therefore its publication will be suppressed.” Bull of course <lb/>pasted Edwards’s print and his letter into his copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, whereas the</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">13</hi> Barker’s helpful list includes the extra-illustrations from the Huntington copy under <lb/>discussion, reference 131207, together with those of sixteen other copies. It does not include <lb/>the second of the three copies of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> described in this paper (Newberry Library, <lb/>Chicago), nor does it include a copy illustrated by the Hardings at New York Public Library <lb/>(reference Stuart 1057).</p>
<pb n="246"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">A</hi>nonymous compiler of the Huntington volume had to be content with the print.<lb/>
But he was also able to obtain a copy of Walpole’s printed “Rules for obtaining<lb/>
a Ticket to see Strawberry Hill” of 1784, and six drawings and six watercolors,<lb/>
quite possibly all of them by the Hardings, including Charlotte de Tremouille,<lb/>
Countess of Derby, the defender of Latham Castle in the Civil War, from the<lb/>
painting in the Tribune, a highly finished portrait in court dress, and Sir Chris-<lb/>
topher Wray, Queen Elizabeth’s Lord Chief Justice, and Sir Robert Walpole in<lb/>
the robes of the Order of the Bath, from the Great North Bedchamber. The<lb/>
prints underline the strength of Walpole’s holdings of 16th- and 17th-century<lb/>
portraits, though there is a real contrast between the quality of the Hardings’<lb/>
finished watercolors, which have been commended as painstaking in their detail<lb/>
and accuracy, and their stipple engravings, which when seen en masse can appear<lb/>
repetitive and somewhat mechanical.</p>
<p>The six watercolors and six drawings enliven the volume, as does Walpole’s<lb/>
“Rules for obtaining a Ticket” from the Strawberry Hill Press. But this is Straw-<lb/>
berry Hill at one remove, the images taken in the very last years of Walpole’s life,<lb/>
or after his death. There is no involvement whatever by Walpole, and also none<lb/>
by that central figure in the dissemination of Strawberry Hill Press in the years<lb/>
after Walpole’s death, Thomas Kirgate.</p>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">V</hi></head>
<p>What our second copy of an extra-illustrated <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> shows is what Kirgate<lb/>
could offer from his stock to a favored customer. The copy does not provide any<lb/>
evidence as to its original purchaser, but it was subsequently acquired by Henry<lb/>
Probasco (1820–1902), a Cincinnati hardware magnate, and was listed in the<lb/>
catalogue of his collection that he had printed in 1873—with the result that it is<lb/>
in turn listed by A. T. Hazen in his <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of the Strawberry Hill Press</hi>, where<lb/>
he describes it from Probasco’s catalogue entry, and suggests that it may have<lb/>
been the copy which was lot 411 on the second day of Kirgate’s sale.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> This seems<lb/>
unlikely, as lot 411 is simply described as being the 1784 edition with plates, with<lb/>
no suggestion that it was extra-illustrated over and above the standard plates<lb/>
with which it was issued (none of the copies of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> in Kirgate’s sale<lb/>
are described as extra-illustrated), and it is more likely that Kirgate sold the copy<lb/>
before his death. Curiously, what both Hazen and Lewis appear not to have real-<lb/>
ized was that in 1889 Probasco, who had suffered financial losses, sold his collec-<lb/>
tion to the Newberry Library, Chicago, which is where the book remains.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> Had<lb/>
Lewis, that most resourceful and imaginative of collectors, become aware that an<lb/>
untraced extra-illustrated <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> with unknown original drawings was resting<lb/>
undisturbed in the stacks of the Newberry, the Director would no doubt have<lb/>
received a visit with an irresistible offer to purchase alternative volumes more<lb/>
central to the Newberry’s core collection, in return for Probasco’s copy joining<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">14.</hi> Catalogue of the Collection of Books, Manuscripts, and Works of Art, belonging to Mr. Henry<lb/>
Probasco, Cincinnati, Ohio (Privately printed, 1873), 354; A. T. Hazen, <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of the Strawberry<lb/>
Hill Press</hi>, 127, item 3.</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">15.</hi> Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95.<lb/></p>
<pb n="247"/>
<lb/>the wealth of extra-illustrated examples of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> at Farmington. But <lb/>Probasco’s copy has stayed at the Newberry and has never been fully described.<lb/>The book is half-bound in mid nineteenth-century red morocco, with the <lb/>Newberry’s label dated 1890 identifying it as part of Probasco’s collection. Many <lb/>of the illustrations are annotated by Kirgate, but none of his notes are on the <lb/>sheets of the bound volume, which would have been bound up after his death. <lb/>The annotations consist of two notes in ink by Walpole, one recording the price <lb/>he paid for Reynolds’s painting of the Ladies Waldegrave in the Refectory, the <lb/>other mentioned below; twenty-two notes in ink on the prints and drawings by <lb/>Kirgate; two images inscribed by G. P. Harding; pencil numbers by an unidenti-<lb/>fied hand, giving the page numbers of the text in which the items illustrated are <lb/>described; and a few pencil notes in an unidentified hand, identifying the illus-<lb/>trations, and in one case mentioning the 1842 sale of the collection, so possibly <lb/>made by whoever is responsible for the present binding.<lb/>As for the illustrations, these break down as thirty-four miscellaneous engrav-<lb/>ings; twenty-five portrait prints in stipple after drawings by Silvester Harding and <lb/>published by the Hardings, nine of which also appear in the Huntington copy; <lb/>three portrait prints by the Hardings but published by others; four watercolors <lb/>by George Harding of items at Strawberry Hill, including two drawings of chim-<lb/>ney pieces at the house; eight drawings unsigned but I believe by the Hardings, <lb/>mostly of seals, but including a watercolor of the oaken Gothic bench in the <lb/>Chapel in the Woods mentioned on page 81 of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>; five signed colored <lb/>drawings by or prints colored by Kirgate; seven unsigned drawings by Kirgate; <lb/>and twelve other drawings.<lb/>The combination of prints, of drawings by Kirgate and the Hardings, and <lb/>of Kirgate’s notes on them, make this a volume of real interest: but the excite-<lb/>ment lies in the last group, the twelve other drawings, as this is where the book <lb/>has most to tell us about the creation of Strawberry Hill, displaying the potential <lb/>for extra-illustrated copies to illuminate their subjects. Some are alternative ver-<lb/>sions of known images, such as a watercolor by Edwards of the south front of <lb/>the house that was subsequently engraved in etching and aquatint by Jukes, and <lb/>a copy colored by Edwards of the etching by Jukes of the Printing House; there <lb/>is an unsigned pencil sketch of the Gothic lantern in the hall, similar to the fin-<lb/>ished watercolor in Bawtree’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>; an unsigned wash drawing, <lb/>perhaps by Kirgate or one of the Hardings, of the couvre-feu in the library, of <lb/>which Carter’s drawing is in Bull’s copy; and a finished wash drawing, perhaps <lb/>by George Harding, of the urn erected by Walpole to commemorate the actress <lb/>Kitty Clive, related to the drawing in Walpole’s own copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>.<hi rend="sup">16</hi><lb/>Of the seven other images, two (facing page 32) are drawings of a previously <lb/>unrecorded design by Carter of a series of shields each impaled over a trefoil so as <lb/>to form an inverted triangle that would have provided a series of inverted triangles <lb/>to fill the areas above the Gothic arched arcading over the bookshelves in the Li-<lb/>brary. One of these drawings, with the shield blank, is inscribed by Kirgate “Sketch <lb/>16. For the two Edwards views see Clarke, <hi rend="italic">The Strawberry Hill Press &amp; its Printing House</hi>, <lb/>plates 28 and 25; for the urn to Mrs. Clive, see the frontispiece to <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Fugitive Verses</hi>, <lb/>ed. W. S. Lewis (New York and London: Oxford University Press and Humphrey Milford, 1931).<lb/>
<pb n="248"/>
by Carter, for the Library” (figure 1) while the other, in which Walpole’s arms<lb/>
have been sketched in to the shield, is inscribed by George Harding “Taken from<lb/>
a Sketch by Carter for the Library at Strawberry Hill.” These triangular designs<lb/>
have not been previously recorded, though there is a reference in Walpole’s<lb/>
Straw-<lb/>
berry Hill Accounts under 22 October 1789 “for painting Triangles in the library<lb/>
£6 – 6 –0,” the relevance of which has not previously been clearly understood.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> If<lb/>
the painted triangles were realized, we do not know when they were painted over,<lb/>
but they would have represented Carter’s only known design contribution to the<lb/>
building, as opposed to watercolors and drawings recording it. In any event, if one<lb/>
looks at any of the surviving views of the interior of the Library one can see how a<lb/>
succession of shields on trefoils running around the room, immediately beneath the<lb/>
armorial fantasy of the painted ceiling, would have enriched its heraldic impact.<hi rend="sup">18</hi><lb/>
Three of the remaining images are wash drawings of chimney pieces. A num-<lb/>
ber of the chimney pieces at Strawberry Hill were designed by Richard Bentley<lb/>
(1708–82), son of the great classicist of the same name, who with Walpole and<lb/>
John Chute (1701–76) made up the Committee that was responsible for the de-<lb/>
veloping design of the house in the 1750s. Bentley’s contributions are marked by<lb/>
a creative excess of decorative Gothic and rococo detail. One of the drawings of<lb/>
chimney pieces designed by Bentley, pasted into the endpapers of the book, ap-<lb/>
pears to be by George Harding and is inscribed “Chimney in Red Bedchamber”<lb/>
by Kirgate, who has added measurements. More important, though, is a wash<lb/>
drawing facing page 15, which is inscribed in Walpole’s own hand “Chimney<lb/>
piece of the little parlour at Strawberry hill, taken from a tomb in Westminster<lb/>
Abbey” (figure 2). It is a design drawing with the left jamb of the chimney piece<lb/>
only outlined, and with a plan of the base of the right jamb and measurements<lb/>
given for the opening. It also shows mantling around the shield, which is not<lb/>
present in the surviving chimney piece, or in the similar but finished drawing in<lb/>
Bull’s copy of the Description. The text of the Description does not specify the de-<lb/>
signer, but the image relates in the use of wash and looseness of line to the Bentley<lb/>
chimney piece designs at the Lewis Walpole Library, both stylistically and in the<lb/>
paper used, though the paper on which those designs are drawn has been given<lb/>
a brown wash.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> And on closer inspection the mantling consists of writhing ser-<lb/>
pents’ heads, a conceit that Bentley was also to use in the charged and disturbing<lb/>
fantasy known as A Prospect of Vapourland of 1759.<hi rend="sup">20</hi> Apart from the mantling and<lb/>
the Walpole’s family crest of a Turk’s head above the shield, the drawing is virtu-<lb/>
ally indistinguishable from the chimney piece as built. Walpole’s inscription does<lb/>
not mention Bentley’s name any more than does the text of the Description, but<lb/>
the drawing provides a strong case for Bentley’s being responsible for the design.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">17.</hi> Strawberry Hill Accounts: A Record of Expenditure in Building Furnishing, &amp;c. Kept by Horace<lb/>
Walpole From 1747 to 1795, ed. Paget Toynbee (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1927), 18 and 175, note 9.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">18.</hi> See Snodin, Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill, 37, figure 52 for Edwards’s watercolor of<lb/>
the Library and 234, figure 260 for Carter’s watercolor.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">19.</hi> Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, Bentley Album, 49 35 85.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">20.</hi> Yale Centre for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection, accession no. B1975.3.188. It is<lb/>
discussed in Loftus Jestin, The Answer to the Lyre: Richard Bentley’s Illustrations for Thomas Gray’s<lb/>
Poems (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1990), 196–198, and illustrated at figure<lb/>
62, and also illustrated in Snodin, Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill, 335, figure 360.<lb/>
<pb n="249"/>
<milestone unit="horizontalRule" rend="hr"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 1.</head>
  <figDesc>Sketch by Carter, for the Library.<lb/>John Carter, the inscription in the hand of Thomas Kirgate.<lb/>Ink and wash on paper, 17 × 27 cm.<lb/>Facing p. 33 of Probasco’s copy of the Descrip-<lb/>tion of Strawberry Hill, Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95.<lb/>Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<p>
The third image, though also unsigned, is clearly by Bentley. It is an unre-<lb/>corded, unexecuted scheme for an original and idiosyncratic chimney piece de-<lb/>sign, the jambs faced with pyramidal forms topped with flambeaux, with a half<lb/>quatrefoil over the lintel within an arched hood, topped with another flambeau<lb/>reflecting those above the jambs (figure 3). A vase is placed within the reveal of the<lb/>quatrefoil, with small pots to either side, and there are two other vases in outline<lb/>behind the flambeaux at the head of each jamb. Like the Little Parlour drawing, it<lb/>relates directly to the Bentley chimney piece designs at the Lewis Walpole Library.<lb/>Both stylistically and in similarity in format to those designs it seems clearly to be<lb/>by Bentley and might conceivably be a preliminary design for the China Room or<lb/>perhaps the Waiting Room. It is a vibrant and idiosyncratic design, consistent with<lb/>Bentley’s surviving chimney pieces in the Beauty Room and the Blue Bedchamber.</p>
<p>
The two remaining drawings are more problematical. One is a scaled perspec-<lb/>tive line drawing for what was known as the trunk-ceiled passage that linked the<lb/>Holbein Chamber and Star Chamber to the Gallery, and is inscribed in George<lb/>Harding’s hand “Trunk ceiled passage Strawberry Hill.” The drawing, also</p>
<pb n="250"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 2.</head>
  <figDesc>Chimney piece of the little parlour at Strawberry hill, taken from a tomb in Westminster Abbey.<lb/>
  Richard Bentley attrib., the inscription in the hand of Horace Walpole. Wash drawing on paper, 21 × 17.3 cm. Facing p. 15 of Probasco’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description of Strawberry Hill</hi>,<lb/>
  Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95. Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<pb n="251"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 3.</head>
  <figDesc>
    Richard Bentley, unexecuted chimney piece for Strawberry Hill. Wash drawing on<lb/>
    paper, 14.3 × 11.9 cm. Facing p. 23 of Probasco’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description of Strawberry Hill</hi>,<lb/>
    Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95. Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.
  </figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<pb n="252"/>
<lb/>previously unknown, shows the applied wooden moldings that line the passage,<lb/>
the rounded ceiling, and at the end of the passage the arched window that was<lb/>
subsequently removed when the passage was extended in the nineteenth century<lb/>
to connect through to the Great North Bedchamber. It appears to be a design<lb/>
drawing, perhaps associated with Chute, but it is Harding who has inscribed it.<lb/>

<p>The final drawing is inscribed by Kirgate “Plan for a Gothic Mirror at Straw-<lb/>
berry hill” (<hi rend="smallcaps">figure&amp;nbsp;4</hi>). It has measurements in ink in feet and inches, a sketch plan<lb/>
</p>
<figure>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">figure&amp;nbsp;4.</hi></head>
<!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
<figDesc>Plan for A Gothic Mirror at Strawberry hill. Unsigned pencil drawing on paper,<lb/>
27.4 × 19&amp;nbsp;cm. Facing p.&amp;nbsp;13 of Probasco’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description of Strawberry Hill</hi>, Newberry<lb/>
Library Folio Case W&amp;nbsp;3945&amp;nbsp;95. Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="253"/>
<p>
<lb/>of the projecting canopy above, and a note at the side “a. looking glass / no back. 
<lb/>from the canopy / to the glass / Canopy projects,” that appears to be in Bentley’s 
<lb/>hand, though the drawing (as opposed to the design) is not immediately recogniz-
<lb/>able as Bentley’s. The design consists of a projecting arched and pierced canopy 
<lb/>over a mirror of quatrefoil shape with pointed projections, and the pierced canopy 
<lb/>closely relates to the pierced canopy of the chimney piece in the Refectory as 
<lb/>designed by Bentley. It seems most likely that the drawing, whoever it is by, is of 
<lb/>an unrealized Bentley design, and I am indebted to Michael Snodin for the sug-
<lb/>gestion that it may have been an early design for the mirrors on either side of the 
<lb/>window in the Refectory. The proportions of the sections of wall on either side of 
<lb/>the Refectory window are consistent with the area of wall shown in the drawing, 
<lb/>and the overall size of the mirror as shown in the drawing is broadly similar to 
<lb/>that of the mirrors actually commissioned for these positions, which are arched 
<lb/>and with Gothic moldings and a portrait roundel beneath the top of the arch.<hi rend="sup">21</hi>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>The Newberry volume shows how a selection of the Hardings’ prints and 
<lb/>drawings could be supplemented and enhanced from Kirgate’s extensive stock, 
<lb/>and enriched by drawings of unexecuted designs so as to convert that extra-
<lb/>illustrated copy into a living part of the unfolding story of the development of 
<lb/>Walpole’s house and collection. But that sense of immediacy with the creation of 
<lb/>the house and its collection is, if anything, only strengthened with the last of our 
<lb/>three copies of the Description.
</p>
<head>VI</head>
<p>
<lb/>The third copy of the Description differs most immediately from the other two in 
<lb/>that with the exception of two unsigned drawings, and six small pencil sketches 
<lb/>probably by Kirgate, it has no illustrations—not even the twenty-eight plates 
<lb/>that Walpole commissioned for the 1784 edition. It is a proof copy, interleaved, 
<lb/>and bound in early nineteenth-century half calf. Now in the collection of Charles 
<lb/>Sebag-Montefiore, it more than makes up for its lack of plates by its wealth of ad-
<lb/>ditional material and annotation. It opens with a transcription dated 6 February 
<lb/>1780 by Kirgate on one folded leaf of the sixth and last of Walpole’s fantastical 
<lb/>Hieroglyphic Tales, “A True Love Story,” tipped into the front endpapers. Wal-
<lb/>pole had written the Tales by 1772, but they were not printed by Kirgate at the 
<lb/>Strawberry Hill Press until 1785, and then in only seven copies. This holograph 
<lb/>therefore pre-dates the first printing and was presumably copied from Walpole’s 
<lb/>manuscript. A comparison with the text as first printed five years later shows that 
<lb/>the printed text did not follow Kirgate’s capitalization or repeat one spelling er-
<lb/>ror, and it expanded some abbreviations (presumably it would have been taken 
<lb/>from Walpole’s manuscript), but the differences are not significant.<hi rend="sup">22</hi>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Also among the preliminary pages at the front are a drawing pasted down 
<lb/>of Walpole’s coat of arms resting on three of the books he had written, with 
<lb/>Strawberry Hill in the distance; and a pencil drawing of an ossuarium from the 
<lb/>Armoury. There are in addition two separate lists complied by Kirgate both
</p>
<note place="foot">
<lb/><hi rend="sup">21</hi> Snodin, Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill, 36, figure 51.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">22</hi> See Hieroglyphic Tales, Kenneth W. Gross (London: Pallas Athene, 2011).
</note>
<pb n="254"/>
<lb/>headed “Index of Rooms,” giving page numbers of the 1784 edition. At the foot <lb/>of the second Index Kirgate has added a pencil note giving information on the <lb/>number of visitors to the house:<lb/>In 1786, Eighty tickets were given to different People for admission to view <lb/> Strawberry Hill<lb/>In 1787, Seventy Ditto were given<lb/>In 1789, One Hundred were given<lb/>In 1807, Mrs. Damer says about 80 or 90 are used yearly<lb/>Upon an average, about 80 were given yearly<lb/>For the period 1784 –96 we have Walpole’s manuscript “Book of Visitors,” <lb/>which broadly confirms the first three entries, but there is no comparable evidence <lb/>for the number of visitors after his death in the years of Anne Damer’s occupa-<lb/>tion.<hi rend="sup">23</hi> The note also confirms that the volume, in which the earliest entries are <lb/>proofing corrections that are part of the process of printing the 1784 Description, <lb/>was annotated by Kirgate until at least 1807, only three years before his own death.<lb/>Between the two versions of the Index of Rooms is a list in pencil by Kirgate <lb/>headed “The following Drawings were made by Mr. Carter for Mr. Bull &amp; Mr. <lb/>Walpole” (see appendix below). It lists thirty-six drawings created for Bull’s copy <lb/>of the Description, while five of them were also in Walpole’s. One drawing, “Gal-<lb/>lery 10 G[uineas],” is crossed through and marked “bought by Mr. Baker”— <lb/>presumably the Strawberry Hill Press collector and bibliographer George Baker <lb/>(1781–1858). It is correct that Bull’s copy, despite its wealth of Carter watercolors <lb/>and drawings, does not have his view of the Gallery.<lb/>But as well as this additional material, there are many annotations to the text <lb/>by Kirgate, for this is his interleaved proof copy of the 1784 text. It preserves a <lb/>number of cancels that were corrected in the text as issued, and contains numer-<lb/>ous notes by him as the orchestrator of extra-illustration, and even a few notes <lb/>inserted or initiated by Walpole that throw shafts of light on Walpole’s last years <lb/>at Strawberry Hill. It is very likely that this is the copy that was lot 413 on the <lb/>eighth day of the sale of Kirgate’s library, where it was described as “containing <lb/>many Notes in MS. by T. Kirgate,” and was bought by George Baker for £16. <lb/>At Baker’s sale in 1825, it appears among some seventy-six Strawberry Hill Press <lb/>and related books and ephemera as “A Description of Strawberry Hill, with sev-<lb/>eral loose pieces interleaved, with M.S. memoranda throughout.” It was bought <lb/>by Longman for a far more modest £1.19s., a reflection of the depression in book <lb/>prices that was to be lamented in Dibdin’s Bibliophobia (1832).<hi rend="sup">24</hi><lb/>To begin with Walpole’s notes, these are only on the text pages (pre-dating <lb/>the book’s being bound up interleaved) and are limited but essentially correc-<lb/>23. “Book of Visitors,” Percival Merritt Collection, Houghton Library, Harvard Uni-<lb/>versity, M.S. Eng. 1502, printed in Yale Edition of Horace Walpole’s Correspondence, 12: 216 –252.<lb/>24. A Catalogue of the Valuable and Curious Collection, late the Property of Mr. Thomas Kirgate, of <lb/>Vine-Street, Piccadilly (Deceased) … King &amp; Lochée, 3 December 1810 and nine following days: <lb/>Day 8, lot 413; and A Catalogue of the Very Choice and Select Library of the late George Baker, Esq. of <lb/>St. Paul’s Churchyard … Sotheby, 6 June 1825 and two following days: Day 3, lot 822.<lb/>
<pb n="255"/>
<lb/>tive, and largely relate to those sections of the proof that were cancelled so that<lb/>
corrected text could be printed. Sections D, E, L, and O are cancels, and in the<lb/>
case of section O there are two variant cancels: in one Kirgate has noted the need<lb/>
to add “A small whole length of Dryden, in oil, by Maubert” as the third line of<lb/>
“More Additions” on page 93, and in the other he has marked a change to the<lb/>
heading of page 94. It is possible that some of the minor typographical correc-<lb/>
tions on these pages may be by Walpole rather than Kirgate, but certainly Wal-<lb/>
pole wrote the notes on page 26, crossing through in ink an entry for James 5th<lb/>
and Mary of Lorraine his Queen, a watercolor by Wale, adding the instructions<lb/>
“This is now in the Holbein Room, where you must insert it,” and adding against<lb/>
a Flemish picture of Boors reading “it was in Sir R. Walpole’s collection”—which<lb/>
note duly appears in the printed text of the corrected sheet.<lb/>
There are notes by Walpole adding anecdotal details and provenance infor-<lb/>
mation to the printed text, while his correction on page 24 of Benedict 13th to<lb/>
Benedict 14th has Kirgate’s marginal note “worked so.” That is Kirgate speaking<lb/>
as printer, and another, later example appears on page 92, which concludes the<lb/>
Appendix: “The small 4to. Edit [that is, the original edition of 1774] was printed as<lb/>
far as here, but the Preface was not, I believe, printed for it.” This must have been<lb/>
written by Kirgate as an older man, as he himself had printed the preface in 1786.<lb/>
There is a sense of conversations overheard, as in Kirgate’s note on page 67,<lb/>
on the famous silver bell in the Tribune attributed to Cellini, “Mr. W called it, as<lb/>
Madame de Montbazon was called, ‘La Belle des Belles.’” Similarly, there is his<lb/>
note at the foot of page 56, devoted to the cabinet of miniatures in the Tribune:<lb/>
“This Collection cost Mr. W upwards of 1300£” immediately followed by “Co-<lb/>
lumb [Walpole’s manservant] says under 1200£,” while of the cameo of Tiberius<lb/>
in onyx in the box of antique rings in the Tribune he adds “Mr. W. says, very<lb/>
fine.” Some notes serve as an aide memoire, as on page 34, against the account<lb/>
of a brass padlock in the shape of a hand, he writes “ask Carter for this” [that is,<lb/>
for a drawing of it]. Again, against the footnote on page 65 describing a table of<lb/>
polished pebbles at Chiswick House, he notes “Go to Chiswick to see it.”<lb/>
We also get a sense of items in the collection moving around and out of the<lb/>
house, as in Kirgate’s comment on page 73 that the whole-length portrait of<lb/>
Henry Vere, Earl of Oxford, in the Great North Bedchamber was “Now on the<lb/>
back Stairs” and a landscape by Müntz after Gaspar Poussin had been moved<lb/>
to the Little Parlour, while Vanloo’s whole-length portrait of Sir Robert Walpole<lb/>
was “Removed, and given I think to Mrs. Keppel.”<lb/>
For some items in the collection Kirgate provides supplemental information.<lb/>
Of the Turkish dagger (now lost) believed by Walpole to have belonged to Henry<lb/>
VIII and displayed in the Tribune he notes that “on one side of the Blade are<lb/>
Arabic Characters in Gold. The Handle and Case have on them, 127 Rubies and<lb/>
6 Diamonds.” He also notes the verses written by Walpole on the back of Lady<lb/>
Craven’s picture and the verses on the stand of the Sevres figure of Cupid, both<lb/>
in the Breakfast Room.<lb/>
Kirgate’s entry on page 3, “The Staircase and Hall were repainted, in 1793,<lb/>
by Mr. Cornelius Dixon, in a much more accurate and picturesque Stile, tho from<lb/>
the same model, and cost 250-12-6,” supplements the entry in the Strawberry Hill<lb/>
Accounts and (within two shillings) confirms the cost, while the final blank leaf<lb/>
of the book has Kirgate’s note identifying the builder and cost of the offices that<lb/>
<pb n="256"/>
Walpole had built in about 1790—he also added to the Directions to the Binder<lb/>
 the titles of the two plates of offices, engraved after the sheet had been printed off.<hi rend="sup">25</hi> Other entries illustrating life at the house include Kirgate’s note against<lb/>
 the description of the building of the Gallery and Round Tower that “Cowie,<lb/>
 the Gardiner, says he placed Medals and a Copper-plate, with an Inscription,<lb/>
 on the Foundation Stone of the above Buildings, which is under the Scullery of<lb/>
 the Round Kitchen.” Equally evocative is his recording that most of the small<lb/>
 Etruscan and black Staffordshire vases in the Little Library in the Cottage in the<lb/>
 Garden “were broke by an Owl getting down the Chimney into the Room.”<lb/>
Of particular importance are two short lists, the first at the end of the More Additions appendix on page&amp;nbsp;96, the other on one of the blank leaves at the back.<lb/>
 They record late acquisitions for the collection, after the printing of More Addi-<lb/>
 tions in 1791. Timothy Wilson has quoted Walpole’s letter to Sir Horace Mann<lb/>
 of 1785, in which he asks him to find some examples of a particular Florentine<lb/>
 ceramics manufacture, and then adds “but am I not an old simpleton to be want-<lb/>
 ing playthings still?”<hi rend="sup">26</hi> These lists show the elderly Walpole, still adding to the<lb/>
 collection to within three years of his death. The first list is:<lb/>
Brown earthen Miraculous Pitcher—Earthen Bottle, labelled, Claret<lb/>
A Miniature in enamel of [gap] Lord Bute, by Spencer; bought at Dalton’s Sale,<lb/>
1791.<lb/>
Six Portraits, with Pen and ink, of Mr. Walpole, Mr. Chute, Mr. Spence, &amp;c.<lb/>
 drawn by Rosalba, when those Gentlemen were in Italy, unknown to them,<lb/>
 when at some public Place; yet very like<lb/>
Dead Christ, by Carrache, small oil painting on Copper, from Sir Laurence<lb/>
 Dundas’s Sale, in 1794.<lb/>
Miniature Portrait of Charles James Stuart, eldest son of the Pretender; Given<lb/>
 by Mrs. Hunter, In 1794.<lb/>
The second has five more items:<lb/>
A carved Ivory Cup, with a Bacchanalian Procession, in relievo, set in Silver,<lb/>
 with the Orford Crest on the Cover; from Houghton.<lb/>
Two Cocoa Nuts, carved with the Arms of Orford, and mounted with Silver gilt<lb/>
 feet; from Ditto, 1793.<lb/>
Two silver filigraine Hampers; from Ditto, 1794.<lb/>
A Portrait of the Rev.&amp;nbsp;William Cole, of Botesham Hall, Cambridge, on painted<lb/>
 Glass.<lb/>
25.&amp;nbsp;Strawberry Hill Accounts, 20 and&amp;nbsp;179, note&amp;nbsp;1; and Clarke, “Lord God! Jesus! What a House!” 380, note&amp;nbsp;41.<lb/>
26.&amp;nbsp;Timothy Wilson, “‘Playthings Still?’ Horace Walpole as a Collector of Ceramics,”<lb/>
 in Snodin, Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill, 200–219, at&amp;nbsp;201. The letter is in Correspondence,<lb/>
 25:&amp;nbsp;590.<lb/>
<pb n="257"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">A Cast in Plaister of Miss Farren, from a bust in marble, executed by Mrs. Damer</hi><lb/>
Of these, three are Walpole silver, presumably acquired through family piety,<lb/>
and two come from sales of 1791 and 1794. One is a gift, and one a plaster bust of<lb/>
the actress Elizabeth Farren by his admired cousin. The portraits by Rosalba are<lb/>
curious—it would be surprising that they only came into Walpole’s possession<lb/>
in the 1790s, over fifty years after his Grand Tour, and some years after all the<lb/>
other persons mentioned had died; or perhaps they were existing possessions that<lb/>
had not previously been listed. And the portrait on glass of his correspondent,<lb/>
the antiquary William Cole, who had died in 1782, is intriguing. Some of the<lb/>
Rosalbas are at The Vyne (John Chute’s house), the carved ivory cup is in the<lb/>
Derby collection at Knowsley Hall, and the mounted coconuts are in a private<lb/>
collection: the rest have disappeared, but the group of items do display the still<lb/>
dedicated collector, adding to his treasures and adorning his house to the last.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
There are, however, three topics that constitute by far the largest number<lb/>
of Kirgate’s annotations. The first of these is the cost of items—what Walpole<lb/>
had paid for them. These can be treated anecdotally, as in Kirgate’s note at the<lb/>
foot of page 72 of the painting over the chimney piece of the Great North Bed-<lb/>
chamber: “the Picture of Henry 8th. and Children, which Mr. Walpole bought<lb/>
for 80 Guineas, was formerly sold on London Bridge for 5 Pounds.” Of the bust<lb/>
of Vespasian in the Gallery described at page 50 he comments “it was reckoned<lb/>
the 7th Bust in Rome, and cost under 20£,” while the Boccapadugli eagle in the<lb/>
Gallery “Cost but 50£. Mr. W. has been offered 1000£ for it. The pedestal cost<lb/>
25£.” Mostly, though, he simply notes the price paid by Walpole in the margin<lb/>
against objects, doing so for about fifty-five of them.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
The other two series of annotations bring us back to Kirgate as dealer in prints<lb/>
of the collection. They are notes as to whether there are available prints of items<lb/>
in the collection, and descriptions of the poses of portraits. There are over 130<lb/>
notes querying whether a print or drawing exists, or if there is a print, by whom<lb/>
it is engraved. At the foot of page 24 of the book, for example, the text lists three<lb/>
portraits in the Green Closet, of Henry Carey, Earl of Monmouth, Pope Benedict<lb/>
XII, and Lady Newburgh: against the first two Kirgate has noted “Engraved by<lb/>
S. Harding,” but against the third he has written “Q. if engraved by Harding?”<lb/>
and added “No. But I have a copy by Harding.” On the preceding page, against<lb/>
Scott’s view of Pope’s house in Twickenham, he asks “See if Sayer has not a<lb/>
Print like this”—a reference to the printseller Robert Sayer (1725–94). There<lb/>
are page after page of such entries, many just noting that there is a mezzotint, or<lb/>
an engraving by Harding, or noting a print’s scarcity: as a random selection, of<lb/>
the Maid of Honour Mrs. Trevor “No Print in that name in Bromley [Bromley’s<lb/>
Catalogue of Engraved British Portraits (1793)] Q. was She married? Drawing of her<lb/>
by G. Harding”; various notes as to whether antiquities that Walpole had bought<lb/>
from Conyers Middleton were engraved in his Antiquities (1745); and of an antique<lb/>
silver figure of a seated muse in the Tribune Kirgate writes “Beg a Drawing of<lb/>
it,” to remind himself to ask (presumably) Mrs. Damer for permission to have it<lb/>
copied. But especially revealing is his comment on the ancient oak chair in the<lb/>
Holbein Chamber that Walpole believed to have come from Glastonbury Abbey:<lb/>
“Engraved by Captn. Grose, Prints of which may be had of T. Kirgate.”<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="258"/>
<p>
Almost as frequent, though, are Kirgate’s annotations as to the poses of<lb/>
portraits at Strawberry Hill. There are approximately one hundred of these,<lb/>
carefully written out in pencil. A good example of this is provided by the nineteen<lb/>
heads in oil from the Court of Charles II, copied by Jarvis, and hung by Walpole<lb/>
in the Beauty Room. Kirgate has numbered these from 1 to 19 and written out<lb/>
descriptions of them on the facing interleaved blank sheet. There is, for instance,<lb/>
King William when Prince of Orange, “In armour, truncheon in right hand, left<lb/>
on a helmet, point cravat, dog’s head looking up, battle in the background,” and<lb/>
Frances Stuart, Duchess of Richmond, “Standing in a wood, leaning on left arm<lb/>
on bank, right cross’d to ditto, mantle tied with pearls over left breast, curl on<lb/>
ditto.” For a number of the portraits, Kirgate’s notes seek to distinguish between<lb/>
the Strawberry Hill picture and other similar prints: from the same group of<lb/>
nineteen, there is Henry, Earl of Ogle (with in his case an additional note in ink<lb/>
“No Print of him”), described as “Standing, full faced, flowing hair, point cravat,<lb/>
left hand in robe, right hand pointing with fore finger, Curtain behind. A print<lb/>
of Sir Thomas Isham, Bart (D. Loggan exct.) is exactly like this of Ogle, except<lb/>
the face. A ditto of Sir [blank] Fielding is also, the face excepted, more so.” He<lb/>
is followed in the list by Lady Elizabeth Percy, later Duchess of Somerset “Sit-<lb/>
ting on a bank, supported by right hand, left pointing to a parrot in an orange<lb/>
tree in a vase, lock of hair on left breast, column at left”: this has two additional<lb/>
notes on the text page “Mezzo[tint] Print of her, sold by Browne,” and “A Print<lb/>
of Madam Lucy Loftus is much like the Dss. of Somerset.”<lb/>
What these notes represent is Kirgate’s index for identifying prints from<lb/>
Strawberry Hill portraits when he did not have the originals in front of him.<lb/>
If he were to see in the London print trade a mezzotint of a Lady Elizabeth<lb/>
Percy, he could turn to his notes to see if the print showed her pointing to the<lb/>
required parrot in an orange tree, and if so it could be added to stock for his<lb/>
Strawberry Hill customers. There is even a memorandum to himself “remr.<lb/>
to describe this” against the Van Dyck of Soldiers at Cards, in the manner of<lb/>
Teniers, in the Tribune. The notes serve a similar function of identification to<lb/>
the briefer summaries of poses that appear in some of the entries in Granger’s<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Biographical History</hi>.<lb/>
It is no surprise that Kirgate kept the book until his death, for the function<lb/>
of this copy had been transformed. What had started as a proof copy with his<lb/>
master’s corrections had been interleaved, and become a repository for infor-<lb/>
mation and anecdote, opening a window onto Walpole’s last thirteen years at<lb/>
Strawberry Hill. It had then become the essential reference source for Kirgate’s<lb/>
later career as book and printseller and purveyor of illustrations of the house<lb/>
and its collections. This was a cottage industry by which—as the three copies<lb/>
of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> discussed in this paper illustrate—he and the Harding family<lb/>
not only helped to support themselves, but disseminated to a wider audience<lb/>
Walpole’s vision of Strawberry Hill. The second and third of these volumes pro-<lb/>
vide a wealth of supplemental information and some previously unknown design<lb/>
drawings for Strawberry Hill—but all three together also give us an unusual<lb/>
opportunity to see extra-illustration and annotation from the perspective of the<lb/>
booksellers, printsellers and artists who facilitated the leisured amusement of a<lb/>
generation of collectors.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="259"/>
<head>APPENDIX</head><lb/>
In his annotated proof copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description of Strawberry Hill</hi>, Thomas Kirgate listed the following thirty-six drawings by John Carter for Richard Bull’s extra-illustrated copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> (B) and those of them that were also in Walpole’s copy (W).<lb/>
The following Drawings were made by Mr. Carter for Mr. Bull &amp; Mr. Walpole<lb/>
B Great Cloyster W.<lb/>
B Red Hall W.<hi rend="sup">27</hi><lb/>
B Parlour<lb/>
B Holbein Room<lb/>
B Round Room<lb/>
B Passage to Gallery<lb/>
B Great Bedchamber<lb/>
B Prior’s Garden W.<lb/>
B Cabinet of Enamels<lb/>
B Printing House, inside view<lb/>
B Sceptre &amp; Dagger &amp; Missal<lb/>
B Becket’s tomb &amp; Chalice<lb/>
B Tomb in Chapel<lb/>
B Crucifix in Chapel<lb/>
B Figures of Window of Do.<lb/>
B North Front<lb/>
B Round Tower<lb/>
B Obelisk; poor<hi rend="sup">28</hi><lb/>
B Chimney in Mr. W’s Bedchamber<lb/>
B Dia Helenora in Little Cloyster<hi rend="sup">29</hi><lb/>
B Implements of War in Armory<lb/>
B Little Cloyster<lb/>
B Inside of Oratory<lb/>
B Four old Pictures in Chapel<lb/>
B Chair in Holbein Room<lb/>
B The Armoury W<lb/>
B View of the House from Offices<lb/>
B Library W<lb/>
B Gallery 10G. bought by Mr. Baker<lb/>
B Urns in Gallery<lb/>
B Bust of Nic. Poussin’s Wife<lb/>
B Ditto of Caligula and another<lb/>
B Ditto of Jupiter Serapis<lb/>
B Egyptian Idols<lb/>
B Ground Plan of Strawberry<lb/>
B Castle of Otranto<lb/>
Drawings at 2.2.0 each is 75.12.0<hi rend="sup">30</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">27.</hi> The entrance hall is also referred to as the “Red Hall” in Carter’s list of his drawings for Bull in his copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> at the Huntington Library, and it does appear from his watercolor that it had red floor tiles.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">28.</hi> This and the two preceding items are bracketed together as “Views.”<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">29.</hi> Described by Walpole in a footnote to page 2 of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> as a bas-relief head in marble of Eleanora d’Este, inscribed Dia Helianora.<lb/>
<hi rend="sup">30.</hi> From the list in the Appendix, Carter’s watercolors are reproduced in Snodin, <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill</hi>, as follows: Red Hall (33, fig. 45), Parlour (35, fig. 48), Holbein Room (43, fig. 61), Round Room (48, fig. 72), Passage to Gallery (301, fig. 326), Great Bedchamber (50, fig. 77), Cabinet of Enamels (99, fig. 128), Printing House, inside view (243, fig. 274), Sceptre &amp; Dagger &amp; Missal (226, fig. 253), Tomb in Chapel (147, fig. 163), Round Tower (253, fig. 282), Implements of War in Armory (224, fig. 251), The Armoury (220, fig. 245), Library (234, fig. 260), Bust of Caligula [though alone, not with another] (176, fig. 187), and Bust of Jupiter Serapis (176, fig. 188).<lb/>
<pb n="260"/>
<pb n="261"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">CHARLES DIBDIN AND THE MAKING OF</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">THE MUSICAL TOUR OF MR. DIBDIN (1788):</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">A NEW “COMPACT WITH THE PUBLIC”</hi></head><lb/>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi><lb/> <name type="pname">David Chandler</name></byline><lb/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">O</hi>n 17&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1787, Charles&amp;nbsp;Dibdin&amp;nbsp;(1745–1814) took the stagecoach from London to Oxford, “with a few shirts and books in a trunk, [and] a well-digested plan in [his] head.”<hi rend="sup">1</hi><lb/>
Famous first as an actor-singer, then as a theatre composer who collaborated with such luminaries as David&amp;nbsp;Garrick and Isaac&amp;nbsp;Bickerstaff, then as a writer for the theatre himself, Dibdin was “an extremely well-known public character”<hi rend="sup">2</hi><lb/>
who was now, in the spirit of entrepreneurship increasingly shaping his activities, seeking to integrate his talents.<lb/>
The “well-digested plan” was for a one-man musical show which Dibdin intended touring round the country to fund his family’s planned emigration to India; standing be­hind a piano (an instrument he had introduced in Britain), he would alternately speak and sing to his audience.<lb/>
By appearing as poet, composer, performer and “band,” Dibdin later wrote, he was doing something “so unprecedented, that one should rationally suppose, if it were only for the novelty, it were likely to attract curiosity, and ensure encouragement.”<hi rend="sup">3</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Readings and Music</hi>, as he called his entertainment, was to prove personally, professionally, even culturally trans­formative;<lb/>
with it, the second half of Dibdin’s career commenced.<lb/>
In the end, he never did go to India, but he decided that the one-man show, which he began calling a “Table Entertainment,” on the model of “table talk,” was his natural medium, and he went on developing the form.<lb/>
For a time, his shows were sensationally popular, and between 1791 and 1805 Dibdin even had his own London theatre, the Sans&amp;nbsp;Souci, specifically to present them.<lb/>
The songs he produced for these Table Entertainments had an immense impact on the popular song repertoire, making Dibdin overwhelmingly the leading anglophone singer-songwriter of the age.<lb/>
The form of the shows, too, had a huge influence on popular entertainment, almost every subsequent proponent of the one-man show with music owing something, directly or indirectly, to Dibdin.<lb/>
They very</p><lb/>
<note place="foot">1.&amp;nbsp;Charles&amp;nbsp;Dibdin, <hi rend="italic">The Musical Tour of Mr.&amp;nbsp;Dibdin</hi> (Sheffield, 1788), 13–14.<lb/>
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Subsequent references are noted parenthetically in the text.<lb/>
2.&amp;nbsp;Oskar&amp;nbsp;Cox&amp;nbsp;Jensen, David&amp;nbsp;Kennerley and Ian&amp;nbsp;Newman&amp;nbsp;(eds.), <hi rend="italic">Charles Dibdin and Late Georgian Culture</hi><lb/>
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018), 1. This volume is the best introduction to the great variety of Dibdin’s achievements and cultural impacts, though it has little to say about him as a writer or solo performer.<lb/>
3.&amp;nbsp;Charles&amp;nbsp;Dibdin, <hi rend="italic">The Professional Life of Mr.&amp;nbsp;Dibdin</hi>, 4&amp;nbsp;vols. (London, 1803), 1:4.</note>
</div>