<div type="section" n="1">
  <head>Introductory chapters — John Carter and Studies in Bibliography</head>
<pb n="7"/>
<head>John Carter: An Assessment<lb/>
and a Handlist</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname"><hi rend="smallcaps">G. THOMAS TANSELLE</hi></name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">J</hi>ohn carter was one of the most prominent and significant <lb/>
figures in the Anglo-American book world in the twentieth <lb/>
century. Indeed, he held a unique position, for he distinguished <lb/>
himself as a bookseller, a collector, a scholar, and a writer, equally <lb/>
at home and equally recognized on both sides of the Atlantic. <lb/>
He created innovative rare-book catalogues for the Scribner Book Store; <lb/>
formed several notable collections, especially of Catullus and Housman; <lb/>
was a pioneer investigator of the bibliographical problems of nineteenth-<lb/>
century publishers’ bindings; performed (with Graham Pollard) a classic <lb/>
piece of bibliographical detection in uncovering the Wise-Forman forger-<lb/>
ies; produced a scholarly edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s Urne Buriall and <lb/>
the Garden of Cyrus; and wrote (or co-wrote or co-edited) several celebrated <lb/>
works—An Enquiry into the Nature of Certain Nineteenth Century Pamphlets <lb/>
(1934), Taste and Technique in Book-Collecting (1948), ABC for Book-Collectors <lb/>
(1952), and Printing and the Mind of Man (1967).<lb/>
A record of his published writings is obviously a basic guide to his ac-<lb/>
complishment. But such a record is also desirable for another reason that <lb/>
would not apply to many people: nearly every piece he wrote, no matter <lb/>
how small (including brief reviews and letters to editors), is worth reading <lb/>
for its style and wit. I am therefore presenting here a handlist (following in <lb/>
Carter’s tradition of handlist-writing) that will enable readers to find these <lb/>
pieces. Carter published so prolifically (some 1500 items are known) in such <lb/>
a wide array of venues that there are bound to be many items I have missed, <lb/>
especially among his letters to editors. But what is here is a comprehensive <lb/>
nucleus to which additions can be made. As Carter said in his handlist of <lb/>
Stanley Morison, it is “intended to serve as a series of signposts now and as <lb/>
a basis for amplification, correction and addition in the future.”<lb/>
As an introduction to the handlist, I shall attempt a brief assessment of <lb/>
Carter’s achievement, which is a by-product of the overview provided by <lb/>
the handlist. It is inevitably biographical to some extent; but the empha-<lb/>
sis is on Carter’s writings, not his life, because a book-length biography <lb/>
already exists: Donald C. Dickinson’s John Carter: The Taste and Technique of <lb/>
</p>
<pb n="8"/>
<p>
 a Bookman (2004). The biographical details selected for mention here and<lb/>
 in the handlist (many of which do not appear in the Dickinson book) are<lb/>
 those that seem to me most relevant for understanding the background<lb/>
 and context of his writings and his wide influence. I knew John Carter for<lb/>
 only the last ten years of his life: some of my recollections were written<lb/>
 up in section 36 of my memoir, <hi rend="italic">“The Living Room”</hi> (published in vol-<lb/>
 ume 59 of <hi rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</hi> and then in <hi rend="italic">Books in My Life</hi>, 2021), and<lb/>
 I dedicated my book about book-jackets to his memory. I shall not forget<lb/>
 the many kindnesses he showed me and the important favors he did for<lb/>
 me, and the present offering is a reflection of my gratitude.<lb/>
</p>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">ASSESSMENT</hi></head><lb/>
<head>The 1930s</head><lb/>
<p>
 John Carter’s first post-collegiate publication on a bookish subject, an<lb/>
 article on <hi rend="italic">“Original Condition”</hi> in the 15 November 1930 issue of <hi rend="italic">Publishers’<lb/>
 Weekly</hi>, came only three years after college and inaugurated an amaz-<lb/>
 ing four-year period of brilliant productivity. Born John Waynflete Carter<lb/>
 at Eton on 10 May 1905, he was educated at Eton and King’s College<lb/>
 Cambridge, where he achieved a double first in the classical tripos and<lb/>
 an honors degree in 1927. By that time he was already collecting Catullus<lb/>
 and had become interested in textual criticism through the influence of A.<lb/>
 E. Housman’s lectures. Almost immediately after leaving Cambridge he<lb/>
 was hired (in September 1927) by the London office of Charles Scribner’s<lb/>
 Sons to locate rare books to be sold in their New York shop. In the three<lb/>
 years between then and that 1930 article, he was becoming acquainted<lb/>
 with the book dealers and collectors both in Britain and in America (his<lb/>
 first visit to New York being January to April 1929). But he was clearly do-<lb/>
 ing more, for his first three letters to the <hi rend="italic">Times Literary Supplement</hi> (in 1931-<lb/>
 33) show that by then he was already immersed in research on Sir Thomas<lb/>
 Browne, publishers’ bindings, and the pamphlets that became known as<lb/>
 the Wise-Forman forgeries—the subjects of his first major publications<lb/>
 (and of his early articles for the main book-collecting journals of the time,<lb/>
 <hi rend="italic">The Book Collector’s Quarterly</hi> in England and <hi rend="italic">The Colophon</hi> in America).<lb/>
</p>
<p>
 In May 1932 he published <hi rend="italic">Binding Variants in English Publishing, 1820-1900</hi> as the<lb/>
 sixth volume in Michael Sadleir’s important <hi rend="italic">Bibliographia</hi> se-<lb/>
 ries, which had the significant subtitle “Studies in Book History and Book<lb/>
 Structure” (where “structure” makes clear the interest in bibliographical<lb/>
 analysis). Sadleir, a publisher (Constable was his firm), novelist, and col-<lb/>
 lector, had already established himself (he was sixteen and a half years<lb/>
 older than Carter) as a bibliographical scholar and a pioneer historian<lb/>
 of publishers’ bindings. He had published a bibliography of Trollope in<lb/>
 1928 (a landmark through its explicit demonstration that an author bibli-<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="9"/>
ography can be a contribution to the history of publishing); and two years<lb/>
later <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Publishers’ Bindings Styles, 1770–1900</hi> came out as the<lb/>
first volume in his Bibliographia series. Carter’s admiration for Sadleir<lb/>
is suggested by a letter he wrote to <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> on 20 December 1957 to<lb/>
supplement <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>’s obituary of Sadleir: “None of those who moved<lb/>
in his orbit . . . was ever made to feel a satellite. But in our corner of the<lb/>
sky a star has fallen.” An “avowed disciple” of Sadleir (as he called himself<lb/>
in a 1970 article), Carter had been following Sadleir’s lead in investigat-<lb/>
ing edition binding; and he had published articles on the subject in 1931<lb/>
and 1932 that he was able to incorporate into his 1932 book. In the first<lb/>
chapter of that book, he modestly called it “a rather swollen appendix” to<lb/>
Sadleir’s book, but it is much more than that in several ways.<lb/>
First, the chapter called “Historical,” though it is a condensed ac-<lb/>
count of the beginnings and early use of cloth for bindings, draws on his<lb/>
own original research in publishers’ catalogues and trade journals. Sec-<lb/>
ond, the bulk of the first half is a detailed account of how to go about in-<lb/>
vestigating the bindings of nineteenth-century books and determining the<lb/>
order of variant bindings. He touches on the use of publishers’ records<lb/>
and catalogues, review copies, inscriptions, inserted advertisements, end-<lb/>
papers, and edge treatments, among much else, and he deals with such<lb/>
topics as special bindings, series variants, and bindings-up of parts, along<lb/>
with the description of cloth grains. The first half of the book (“General”),<lb/>
which also includes a “specimen investigation,” provides a “method of<lb/>
attack” that is then applied in the second half (“Particular”) to numerous<lb/>
books by some five dozen authors. This extensive survey of examples,<lb/>
based on the examination of an impressive number of copies, is yet an-<lb/>
other contribution of the book, making it useful for reference—and in<lb/>
the process displaying Carter’s cautious and undogmatic way of reaching<lb/>
conclusions.<lb/>
The book is addressed to “students and amateurs of book-structure”<lb/>
(p. xi), and Carter is concerned throughout to advance bibliographical<lb/>
study. He hopes to show “what an immensely important part of bibliog-<lb/>
raphy they [binding variants] become when they are taken seriously,” and<lb/>
he wants to help “develop a scientific method on general lines for dealing<lb/>
with so frequent a phenomenon” (p. 6). He makes clear that “the attitude<lb/>
of mind most desirable in a bibliographer is suspicion” (p. 39), and he<lb/>
stresses the necessity for examining multiple copies. His more specific<lb/>
observations on analyzing bindings form a perfect set of instructions for<lb/>
the beginner on how best to approach a nineteenth-century book: they<lb/>
have not been superseded, nor have they been stated in more attractive<lb/>
prose. Of the several pioneer studies of publishers’ bindings by Carter and<lb/>
Sadleir, this one is the most continuingly useful, still valuable as a guide.<lb/>
A few months after <hi rend="italic">Binding Variants</hi>, another of Carter’s major pub-<lb/>
lications came out: his edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Urne Buriall</hi> and<lb/>
</div>