<div type="section" n="1">
  <head>John Carter: An Assessment and a Handlist</head>
<pb n="7"/>
<head>John Carter: An Assessment<lb/>and a Handlist</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">G. Thomas Tanselle</name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">J</hi>ohn Carter was one of the most prominent and significant figures in the Anglo-American book world in the twentieth century.<lb/>Indeed, he held a unique position, for he distinguished himself as a bookseller, a collector, a scholar, and a writer, equally<lb/>at home and equally recognized on both sides of the Atlantic.</p>
<p>He created innovative rare-book catalogues for the Scribner Book Store; formed several notable collections, especially of Catullus and Housman;<lb/>was a pioneer investigator of the bibliographical problems of nineteenth-century publishers’ bindings; performed (with Graham Pollard) a classic<lb/>piece of bibliographical detection in uncovering the Wise-Forman forgeries; produced a scholarly edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Urne Buriall</hi> and<lb/><hi rend="italic">the Garden of Cyrus</hi>; and wrote (or co-wrote or co-edited) several celebrated works—<hi rend="italic">An Enquiry into the Nature of Certain Nineteenth Century Pamphlets</hi><lb/>(1934), <hi rend="italic">Taste and Technique in Book-Collecting</hi> (1948), <hi rend="italic">ABC for Book-Collectors</hi> (1952), and <hi rend="italic">Printing and the Mind of Man</hi> (1967).</p>
<p>A record of his published writings is obviously a basic guide to his ac-<lb/>complishment. But such a record is also desirable for another reason that<lb/>would not apply to many people: nearly every piece he wrote, no matter<lb/>how small (including brief reviews and letters to editors), is worth reading<lb/>for its style and wit. I am therefore presenting here a handlist (following in<lb/>Carter’s tradition of handlist-writing) that will enable readers to find these<lb/>pieces. Carter published so prolifically (some 1500 items are known) in such<lb/>a wide array of venues that there are bound to be many items I have missed,<lb/>especially among his letters to editors. But what is here is a comprehensive<lb/>nucleus to which additions can be made. As Carter said in his handlist of<lb/>Stanley Morison, it is “intended to serve as a series of signposts now and as<lb/>a basis for amplification, correction and addition in the future.”</p>
<p>As an introduction to the handlist, I shall attempt a brief assessment of<lb/>Carter’s achievement, which is a by-product of the overview provided by<lb/>the handlist. It is inevitably biographical to some extent; but the empha-<lb/>sis is on Carter’s writings, not his life, because a book-length biography<lb/>already exists: Donald C. Dickinson’s <hi rend="italic">John Carter: The Taste and Technique of</hi><lb/>
<pb n="8"/>
<p>a Bookman (2004). The biographical details selected for mention here and<lb/>
in the handlist (many of which do not appear in the Dickinson book) are<lb/>
those that seem to me most relevant for understanding the background<lb/>
and context of his writings and his wide influence. I knew John Carter for<lb/>
only the last ten years of his life: some of my recollections were written<lb/>
up in section 36 of my memoir, “The Living Room” (published in vol-<lb/>
ume 59 of <hi rend="italic">Studies in Bibliography</hi> and then in <hi rend="italic">Books in My Life</hi>, 2021), and<lb/>
I dedicated my book about book-jackets to his memory. I shall not forget<lb/>
the many kindnesses he showed me and the important favors he did for<lb/>
me, and the present offering is a reflection of my gratitude.</p>
<head>ASSESSMENT</head>
<head>The 1930s</head>
<p>John Carter’s first post-collegiate publication on a bookish subject, an<lb/>
article on “Original Condition” in the 15 November 1930 issue of<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, came only three years after college and inaugurated an amaz-<lb/>
ing four-year period of brilliant productivity. Born John Waynflete Carter<lb/>
at Eton on 10 May 1905, he was educated at Eton and King’s College<lb/>
Cambridge, where he achieved a double first in the classical tripos and<lb/>
an honors degree in 1927. By that time he was already collecting Catullus<lb/>
and had become interested in textual criticism through the influence of A.<lb/>
E. Housman’s lectures. Almost immediately after leaving Cambridge he<lb/>
was hired (in September 1927) by the London office of Charles Scribner’s<lb/>
Sons to locate rare books to be sold in their New York shop. In the three<lb/>
years between then and that 1930 article, he was becoming acquainted<lb/>
with the book dealers and collectors both in Britain and in America (his<lb/>
first visit to New York being January to April 1929). But he was clearly do-<lb/>
ing more, for his first three letters to the <hi rend="italic">Times Literary Supplement</hi> (in 1931-<lb/>
33) show that by then he was already immersed in research on Sir Thomas<lb/>
Browne, publishers’ bindings, and the pamphlets that became known as<lb/>
the Wise-Forman forgeries—the subjects of his first major publications<lb/>
(and of his early articles for the main book-collecting journals of the time,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Book Collector’s Quarterly</hi> in England and <hi rend="italic">The Colophon</hi> in America).<lb/>
In May 1932 he published <hi rend="italic">Binding Variants in English Publishing, 1820-<lb/>
1900</hi> as the sixth volume in Michael Sadleir’s important <hi rend="italic">Bibliographia</hi> se-<lb/>
ries, which had the significant subtitle “Studies in Book History and Book<lb/>
Structure” (where “structure” makes clear the interest in bibliographical<lb/>
analysis). Sadleir, a publisher (Constable was his firm), novelist, and col-<lb/>
lector, had already established himself (he was sixteen and a half years<lb/>
older than Carter) as a bibliographical scholar and a pioneer historian<lb/>
of publishers’ bindings. He had published a bibliography of Trollope in<lb/>
1928 (a landmark through its explicit demonstration that an author bibli-<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="9"/>
ography can be a contribution to the history of publishing); and two years <lb/>
later <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Publishers’ Bindings Styles, 1770–1900</hi> came out as the <lb/>
first volume in his <hi rend="italic">Bibliographia</hi> series. Carter’s admiration for Sadleir <lb/>
is suggested by a letter he wrote to <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> on 20 December 1957 to <lb/>
supplement <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>’s obituary of Sadleir: “None of those who moved <lb/>
in his orbit . . . was ever made to feel a satellite. But in our corner of the <lb/>
sky a star has fallen.” An “avowed disciple” of Sadleir (as he called himself <lb/>
in a 1970 article), Carter had been following Sadleir’s lead in investigat-<lb/>
ing edition binding; and he had published articles on the subject in 1931 <lb/>
and 1932 that he was able to incorporate into his 1932 book. In the first <lb/>
chapter of that book, he modestly called it “a rather swollen appendix” to <lb/>
Sadleir’s book, but it is much more than that in several ways. <lb/>
First, the chapter called “Historical,” though it is a condensed ac-<lb/>
count of the beginnings and early use of cloth for bindings, draws on his <lb/>
own original research in publishers’ catalogues and trade journals. Sec-<lb/>
ond, the bulk of the first half is a detailed account of how to go about in-<lb/>
vestigating the bindings of nineteenth-century books and determining the <lb/>
order of variant bindings. He touches on the use of publishers’ records <lb/>
and catalogues, review copies, inscriptions, inserted advertisements, end-<lb/>
papers, and edge treatments, among much else, and he deals with such <lb/>
topics as special bindings, series variants, and bindings-up of parts, along <lb/>
with the description of cloth grains. The first half of the book (“General”), <lb/>
which also includes a “specimen investigation,” provides a “method of <lb/>
attack” that is then applied in the second half (“Particular”) to numerous <lb/>
books by some five dozen authors. This extensive survey of examples, <lb/>
based on the examination of an impressive number of copies, is yet an-<lb/>
other contribution of the book, making it useful for reference—and in <lb/>
the process displaying Carter’s cautious and undogmatic way of reaching  <lb/>
conclusions. <lb/>
The book is addressed to “students and amateurs of book-structure” <lb/>
(p. xi), and Carter is concerned throughout to advance bibliographical <lb/>
study. He hopes to show “what an immensely important part of bibliog-<lb/>
raphy they [binding variants] become when they are taken seriously,” and <lb/>
he wants to help “develop a scientific method on general lines for dealing <lb/>
with so frequent a phenomenon” (p. 6). He makes clear that “the attitude <lb/>
of mind most desirable in a bibliographer is suspicion” (p. 39), and he <lb/>
stresses the necessity for examining multiple copies. His more specific <lb/>
observations on analyzing bindings form a perfect set of instructions for <lb/>
the beginner on how best to approach a nineteenth-century book: they <lb/>
have not been superseded, nor have they been stated in more attractive <lb/>
prose. Of the several pioneer studies of publishers’ bindings by Carter and <lb/>
Sadleir, this one is the most continuingly useful, still valuable as a guide. <lb/>
A few months after <hi rend="italic">Binding Variants</hi>, another of Carter’s major pub-<lb/>
lications came out: his edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Urne Buriall and</hi> <lb/>
<pb n="10"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Garden of Cyrus</hi> (originally published in 1658, with “<hi rend="italic">Urne Buriall</hi>” as a<lb/>
subtitle to “<hi rend="italic">Hydriotaphia</hi>”). It was a lavish production, elegantly printed<lb/>
by the Curwen Press and published (in an edition of 215 copies) by Cassell<lb/>
&amp; Company with thirty drawings by Paul Nash (printed by collotype and<lb/>
colored by pochoir) and a morocco and vellum binding designed by him.<lb/>
This handsome book is regularly regarded as one of the masterpieces of<lb/>
twentieth-century book production—as, for example, in Martin Hutner<lb/>
and Jerry Kelly’s <hi rend="italic">A Century for a Century</hi> (Grolier Club, 1999). But the work<lb/>
also makes a scholarly contribution to the study of Browne. Carter had<lb/>
been reading Browne since his Eton days, and by the early 1930s he was<lb/>
on the trail of author-corrected copies of the first edition (as his letter to<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Times Literary Supplement</hi> on 16 July 1931 shows), while he was working<lb/>
on a new edition, at the request of Desmond Flower (of Cassell’s). He was<lb/>
able to locate and use six such copies before his edition came out, only<lb/>
two of which had previously been known. The thoroughness of his work<lb/>
is symbolized by his annotated copy of Edward H. Marshall’s 1929 Mac-<lb/>
millan edition: its leaves, mounted on larger paper, were interleaved with<lb/>
blanks, which were covered with his notes reporting collations, references,<lb/>
and critical observations (described in G. F. Sims catalogue 102 [1979],<lb/>
item 85). As he noted in his introduction, he had collated all editions be-<lb/>
fore 1800 and all published in Great Britain since then (though he does<lb/>
not mention collating multiple copies of the early editions).<lb/>
<lb/>
Carter’s editorial approach was admirable. Because the successive<lb/>
lifetime editions were unreliable, he based his text on the first edition<lb/>
and reported all his departures from it (except the correction of turned,<lb/>
dropped, or transposed letters), as well as the results of his collations.<lb/>
Aside from the adoption of Browne’s own corrections, the departures<lb/>
were few because he retained the punctuation and spelling of the first<lb/>
edition (except the long s and the “sporadic” use of <hi rend="italic">v</hi> for <hi rend="italic">u</hi>). He correctly<lb/>
recognized that Browne’s “use of commas and semicolons, like his use of<lb/>
initial capitals and italics is too much a part of himself and his period to<lb/>
submit to this wholesale modernization [of earlier editors].” Nevertheless<lb/>
he did make an “irreducible minimum of corrections where the com-<lb/>
positor’s carelessness has produced intolerable obscurity.” Clearly there<lb/>
is room for disagreement here, for some of the obscurity may not have<lb/>
been caused by the compositor, and in any case what is intolerable is a<lb/>
subjective matter. But critical editing necessarily entails judgment, and<lb/>
these alterations are all recorded in the notes. The introduction ends with<lb/>
a gracious point not often made: although he has criticized earlier edi-<lb/>
tions, he says, “one cannot begin to criticize an edition until one has used<lb/>
it thoroughly, so that criticism becomes almost a proof of obligation.”<lb/>
<lb/>
On 2 July 1934, less than two years after the Browne edition, Carter’s<lb/>
third major publication appeared—the one that made him a book-world<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="11"/>
<p><lb/>
celebrity: <hi rend="italic">An Enquiry into the Nature of Certain Nineteenth Century Pamphlets</hi>,<lb/>
written in collaboration with Graham Pollard, a bookseller with the firm<lb/>
of Birrell &#38; Garnett. The story of how Carter and Pollard uncovered the<lb/>
Wise-Forman forgeries has been told often; indeed, it is one of the best-<lb/>
known episodes in bibliographical history, familiar to many people out-<lb/>
side the book world (as a result of such treatments as Richard D. Altick’s,<lb/>
in his 1950 book <hi rend="italic">The Scholar Adventurers</hi>, and Dwight Macdonald’s, in a<lb/>
1962 <hi rend="italic">New Yorker</hi> article, as well as Carter’s own accounts). Its wide appeal<lb/>
is understandable, as the story of two young booksellers who, through<lb/>
persistent research, were able to bring down a dominant and respected<lb/>
figure (for Thomas J. Wise was a distinguished collector and widely known<lb/>
book-world symbol, the author of many bibliographies, and a former<lb/>
president of the Bibliographical Society). It also has the elements of a de-<lb/>
tective story, with parts of a puzzle gradually, but inexorably, falling into<lb/>
place. And in the <hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi>, given the panache of Carter’s prose, the story<lb/>
was given a presentation that increased its appeal.<lb/>
<lb/>
Many of the people who are attracted to the story for all these reasons,<lb/>
however, do not recognize its important contribution to bibliographical<lb/>
scholarship. Identifying the perpetrators (which the book did not explic-<lb/>
itly do) is a different activity from proving that the pamphlets are indeed<lb/>
fraudulent. In the absence of explicit documents, the former involves<lb/>
circumstantial evidence, such as the fact that the suspected pamphlets<lb/>
entered the market from the stock of a single dealer (Herbert E. Gorfin).<lb/>
But the latter requires physical evidence from the items themselves. The<lb/>
use of such evidence for investigating books of earlier periods was well es-<lb/>
tablished by this time, but the bibliographical analysis of nineteenth- and<lb/>
twentieth-century books was in its infancy. The attention paid to “points”<lb/>
in modern books by collectors, dealers, and the writers of author bibliog-<lb/>
raphies was a form of physical examination, but it was often undisciplined<lb/>
and lacking in a concern for uncovering book-production history. Pub-<lb/>
lishers’ bindings, however, were beginning to be seriously studied, under<lb/>
the leadership of Sadleir and Carter. And the <hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi> took a major step<lb/>
forward in demonstrating ways in which the analysis of paper and type<lb/>
could also be applied to post-1800 books.<lb/>
<lb/>
It is possible that Carter’s collecting of detective fiction played a role<lb/>
in inspiring the analysis of paper reported in the <hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi>. He was certainly<lb/>
aware of the detective stories of R. Austin Freeman (discussed in his es-<lb/>
say in <hi rend="italic">New Paths in Book Collecting</hi> as reaching “a new level in scientific<lb/>
detection”, and it is not unlikely that he knew “The Apparition of Burl-<lb/>
ing Court” (1923; collected in <hi rend="italic">The Puzzle Lock</hi>, 1925). In that story, the<lb/>
detective, Dr. Thorndyke, proves a book to be fraudulent through several<lb/>
physical tests, the decisive one being a laboratory examination of the pa-<lb/>
per, which showed that the paper contained mechanical wood-pulp and<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="12"/>
<p>
<lb/>esparto. Thorndyke stated that “esparto was not used until 1860,” which
<lb/>was twenty years after the purported date of the book. It turns out that the
<lb/>presence of esparto in the paper of some of the pamphlets that Carter and
<lb/>Pollard were investigating was the basis for proving them to be forgeries.
<lb/>(Although Dr. Thorndyke is not referred to, another fictional detective,
<lb/>Edgar Allan Poe’s Auguste Dupin, is cited as a precursor in a later chapter
<lb/>[p. 87].) Whether or not there was any connection with Dr. Thorndyke,
<lb/>Carter and Pollard used the same procedure: after having the papers of
<lb/>the pamphlets tested and determining the dates when esparto and chemi-
<lb/>cal wood-pulp were introduced into papermaking, they found that twenty-
<lb/>two of the pamphlets had printed dates that preceded the dates when their
<lb/>paper would have been available, and thus they were fraudulent.
<lb/>The authors were aware that their use of paper evidence was more
<lb/>groundbreaking than that of typographical evidence. The paper test, they
<lb/>said, “has not hitherto been applied to bibliographical purposes” (p. 42),
<lb/>whereas, in the opening sentence of the chapter on type, they call atten-
<lb/>tion to Robert Proctor’s work, decades earlier, identifying the printers
<lb/>of incunabula through the type designs. They also note that Proctor, a
<lb/>friend of William Morris, had in 1898 questioned (on the basis of its type)
<lb/>the Morris pamphlet that Carter and Pollard proved to be a forgery.
<lb/>The typographical tests they used throughout were proposed by Stanley
<lb/>Morison (they could hardly have had a greater typographical adviser).
<lb/>He noticed the kernless “f” and “j” and the tilted question mark used
<lb/>in many of the pamphlets; and these characteristics not only provided
<lb/>another dating test (based on the earliest use of a kernless font) but also
<lb/>led to the identification of the printer as Richard Clay &amp; Sons (Clay had
<lb/>added that question mark to the font). The Clay firm was not involved in
<lb/>the deception: having been commissioned by Wise to print many facsimi-
<lb/>les for the Browning and Shelley societies, they had no reason to question
<lb/>the imprints and dates being placed on these other pamphlets. Carter and
<lb/>Pollard concluded that sixteen of the fraudulent pamphlets were definitely
<lb/>printed by Clay &amp; Sons and that all the rest probably were.
<lb/>The analysis of paper and type is set out in chapters 4 and 5 with
<lb/>meticulous care and exemplary thoroughness. These chapters are part
<lb/>of the six that constitute part I, “Deduction,” tracing the story from the
<lb/>initial suspicion to the “proved conclusion.” In the last chapter of part I,
<lb/>the authors say, “With all its drudgery, detective work has a great intel-
<lb/>lectual fascination” (p. 93)—and this fascination has been conveyed to
<lb/>the reader. With the “machinery of detection” having been set forth, the
<lb/>authors move in part II, “Reconstruction,” to a description of the forger’s
<lb/>motivation, methods, and marketing strategies. Then comes the largest
<lb/>section of the book, part III, “Dossiers,” in which each of forty-six pam-
</p>
<pb n="13"/>
<p>
phlets (by fifteen authors) is given a thorough account, reporting (among <lb/>
other things) the history of references to it, the location of known cop-<lb/>
ies, the results of tests, and a conclusion. The book as a whole not only <lb/>
demonstrates the use of certain paper and typographical tests in biblio-<lb/>
graphical analysis but also provides a model of how to draw conclusions <lb/>
cautiously and present the results responsibly.<lb/>
Another attraction of the book is its prose style. Although the book was <lb/>
a true collaboration between Carter and Pollard, Carter’s voice emerges <lb/>
plainly at many points, and some chapters are clearly his work, especially <lb/>
those in part II. The opening one, “The Modern First Edition Market, <lb/>
1885–1895,” is an expert survey of the development of interest in literary <lb/>
first editions (a preview of the more detailed account in <hi rend="italic">Taste and Tech-<lb/>
nique in Book-Collecting</hi>), providing the necessary context for understand-<lb/>
ing why the kinds of pamphlets that Wise produced were sought after. It <lb/>
has many characteristic touches, such as this: “New vistas were opening <lb/>
before the collectors’ eyes, each with a glint of Eldorado at the end” (p. <lb/>
107). In “these feverish and speculative conditions,” Carter added, “it <lb/>
would have been almost surprising if there had not been some collateral <lb/>
descendant of Annius to perceive this golden opportunity. . . . At this time, <lb/>
the thing was, comparatively, easy money: the fish were rising, he [the <lb/>
forger] found (after a few experiments) the right fly, and they swallowed it <lb/>
with a regularity and unanimity which must have been to him exceedingly <lb/>
satisfactory” (pp. 108–09).<lb/>
The chapter on “Establishing the Pedigrees” shows Carter at his most <lb/>
skillful, for he convincingly points the finger at Wise without saying out-<lb/>
right that Wise created the forgeries (which could not be said, since the <lb/>
documentary evidence that later turned up—incriminating Harry Buxton <lb/>
Forman as well as Wise—was not known at that time). Wise could be <lb/>
criticized in other ways, however, especially for his supposed failure to be <lb/>
suspicious of the pamphlets, given the circumstances of their appearance <lb/>
and his bibliographical expertise. His behavior, Carter suggests, “savoured <lb/>
of Nelson with the telescope to his blind eye” (p. 134). Carter was unspar-<lb/>
ing in his condemnation of the “shocking negligence” of Wise (even though <lb/>
he had to call the forger “anonymous”) and of the resulting damage:<lb/>
</p>
<quote>
Mr. Wise, by his credulity, by his vanity in his own possessions, by his dogmatism, by <lb/>
abuse of his eminence in the bibliographical world, has dealt a blow to the prestige <lb/>
of an honourable science, the repercussions of which will be long and widely felt. . . . <lb/>
Like the thirteenth stroke of a faulty clock, which discredits the accuracy of the hours <lb/>
which have gone before, the spuriousness of these books must inevitably cast asper-<lb/>
sions on many similar books which are, in fact, genuine. . . . If Mr. Wise, one of the <lb/>
most eminent bibliographers of our time, can be so extensively wrong, who can we <lb/>
be sure is right? (pp. 141–42)<lb/>
</quote>
<pb n="14"/>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi> is a landmark of bibliographical analysis and the presentation <lb/>
of bibliographical evidence, and it is written in such a way that it is an <lb/>
enduringly readable story of detection.<lb/>
The three major books of 1932-34 were not Carter&#8217;s only significant <lb/>
publications of the early 1930s. In November 1934, four months after the <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi> appeared, Constable (in London) and Scribner&#8217;s (in New York) <lb/>
brought out a volume of essays (planned by him and Michael Sadleir) <lb/>
that he edited, entitled <hi rend="italic">New Paths in Book Collecting</hi>. There had of course <lb/>
been a number of books about book collecting during the previous forty <lb/>
years, but what made this one distinctive was that it consisted of essays <lb/>
by different writers, each taking up an appealing direction for collecting. <lb/>
The authors were drawn primarily from his and Sadleir&#8217;s circle of book-<lb/>
world friends, half of them dealers and half collectors: Carter (on &#8220;Detec-<lb/>
tive Fiction&#8221;), Sadleir (&#8220;Yellow-Backs&#8221;), P. H. Muir (&#8220;Ignoring the Flag&#8221; <lb/>
and &#8220;War Books&#8221;), Graham Pollard (&#8220;Serial Fiction&#8221;), David A. Randall <lb/>
(&#8220;American First Editions, 1900-1933&#8221;), Thomas Balston (&#8220;English Book <lb/>
Illustration, 1880-1900&#8221;), C. B. Oldman (&#8220;Musical First Editions&#8221;), and <lb/>
John T. Winterich (&#8220;The Expansion of an Author Collection&#8221;). When <lb/>
Carter commented on this book in 1948 (in <hi rend="italic">Taste and Technique in Book-</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Collecting</hi>), he called it &#8220;only one instance of the responsible part taken in <lb/>
recent years by professional booksellers, not merely through their practi-<lb/>
cal influence exerted in the course of business but also by their contribu-<lb/>
tions to bibliophilic literature and propaganda, in the formulation and <lb/>
the exposition of theory, of policy and of practice in the book-collecting <lb/>
world&#8221; (Cambridge edition, p. 84). Here he was not only observing a de-<lb/>
velopment but also describing the path he saw for himself as a bookseller, <lb/>
one he faithfully followed.<lb/>
The title of the volume was not meant to suggest that the subjects <lb/>
discussed were entirely new, for some collectors were already focusing <lb/>
on them; but they were new in the sense that they were not traditional, <lb/>
and the purpose of the book was to call attention to, and encourage, <lb/>
the approach to collecting represented by these trends. It was the paths <lb/>
that were new, not necessarily the subjects: the book aimed not to &#8220;dic-<lb/>
tate&#8221; but &#8220;to suggest by means of examples&#8221; (p. 7). As Carter remarked <lb/>
in <hi rend="italic">Taste and Technique</hi>, the volume was &#8220;one gambit&#8221; in the &#8220;general <lb/>
propagandist movement towards diversity of method&#8221; (p. 84). Through-<lb/>
out his career, Carter argued that collectors should think on their own <lb/>
and not simply repeat what earlier collectors had done. In the intro-<lb/>
duction to this volume, for example, he says that collectors should have <lb/>
&#8220;enough independence to dislike joining the herd movements which <lb/>
are always ploughing their way across the book market&#8221; (p. 6). The <lb/>
point is made several times in the opening pages through metaphor. <lb/>
For example:<lb/></p>
<pb n="15"/>
<p>A collection of “high spots” may sound the chord of C major, which is indeed a fine <lb/>
and resounding noise; yet there are other and more subtle harmonies, the pleasantest <lb/>
of which are those which we evolve for ourselves. These are composed of notes which <lb/>
anyone can use and many have used, but by our own arrangement of them we can <lb/>
achieve a sound never heard before. (p. 11)<lb/></p>
<p>Earlier, in a visual metaphor, he says that the coherence of such a collec-<lb/>
tion can reveal a “beautiful pattern” (p. 4). This newly revealed pattern, <lb/>
like the “sound never heard before,” makes a “contribution to knowl-<lb/>
edge” (a phrase used on the first page). Implicit in all the essays that <lb/>
follow (“essays in method,” he calls them), and often explicit as well, is a <lb/>
recognition that collecting is a form of historical study and that follow-<lb/>
ing new paths increases our understanding of the past. With this kind of <lb/>
grounding, New Paths remains one of the most perceptive and inspiring <lb/>
of introductory guides.<lb/></p>
<p>Carter followed up on this book in two ways the same year. With <lb/>
Sadleir, he organized an exhibition “arranged to illustrate” New Paths at J. <lb/>
&amp; E. Bumpus, accompanied by a substantial annotated catalogue; and for <lb/>
the Scribner Book Store he put together a catalogue on detective fiction <lb/>
(largely from his own collection). (In the next few years, he and David A. <lb/>
Randall, head of Scribner’s Rare Book Department in New York as of <lb/>
March 1935, publicized many more new paths in their catalogues.) His <lb/>
interest in publishers’ bindings also led to further contributions to their <lb/>
history in the form of two introductions to Elkin Mathews catalogues <lb/>
(1932) and two small books, Publishers’ Cloth (1935, in connection with <lb/>
an exhibition at the New York Public Library) and More Binding Variants <lb/>
(1938, a supplement to his 1932 book).<lb/></p>
<p>His editorial work also continued with editions of Housman’s Intro-<lb/>
ductory Lecture (1933) and The Collected Poems (1939) and an incomplete <lb/>
edition of Catullus (two fascicles only, 1934–35). (The Collected Poems was <lb/>
published without an editor’s name; but four years later, in the course of <lb/>
an article in the Times Literary Supplement on 5 and 12 June 1943, Carter <lb/>
revealed his editorship publicly.) These efforts, however, did not have the <lb/>
scholarly merit of the Browne edition. The Housman Collected Poems, to <lb/>
take the primary example, could have been a triumph; but it was hastily <lb/>
produced and involved faulty editorial judgments. Housman’s will autho-<lb/>
rized his brother Laurence to destroy some manuscripts and to oversee <lb/>
the use of the others; and Laurence in turn asked Carter (who had helped <lb/>
organize the manuscripts) to produce an edition of the poetry. The result <lb/>
was criticized, beginning in the autumn of 1952 (when the book was in <lb/>
its thirteenth impression), by two American scholars, Tom Burns Haber <lb/>
(Ohio State) and William White (Wayne State), leading to an acrimonious <lb/>
feud that erupted periodically in the pages of the Times Literary Supplement <lb/>
(and, to a lesser extent, The Book Collector) over the next sixteen years.<lb/></p>
<pb n="16"/>
<p>
It started on 26 September 1952 in the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> with a letter from White,<lb/>
using information from Haber, who had studied the Housman manu-<lb/>
scripts, beginning in 1950, much more thoroughly than Carter had.<lb/>
White’s letter, referring to Carter’s “slip-shod editing,” alludes to the<lb/>
two concerns that were the basis of their criticism: the outright errors<lb/>
in the text and the questionable judgment underlying the handling of<lb/>
uncanceled manuscript alternatives, where Carter followed the choices<lb/>
made by Laurence Housman in the poems included in his posthumous<lb/>
editions. Carter’s response (24 October 1952) was weak on both counts.<lb/>
Regarding the first, he said he had only claimed “a <hi rend="italic">more</hi><lb/>
correct text.” As<lb/>
for the second, he asserted that “the person authorized to perform this<lb/>
[choice among variants] . . . was the author’s brother, whose judgment<lb/>
they [White and Haber] are not entitled to challenge.” Haber’s long letter<lb/>
on 7 November mainly described the history of the manuscripts and his<lb/>
work with them; and it was not until a year later (2 October 1953) that<lb/>
Haber, in a good letter summarizing the situation, made a proper reply<lb/>
to Carter’s second point. Carter, he said, “is speaking wildly when he<lb/>
says (of the poet’s brother) that consanguinity endows an editor with om-<lb/>
niscience when choosing between alternative readings in a manuscript.”<lb/>
Haber ends by regretting that the text “should be toyed with once again,”<lb/>
since the fourteenth impression, about to appear, was not to be a thor-<lb/>
ough revision.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
That fourteenth impression, “freshly corrected” according to Carter<lb/>
(23 October 1953), still contained errors that were noted by White (12<lb/>
February 1954), who also questioned Carter’s assertion that Housman’s<lb/>
will gave his brother the right to choose between variants. Despite Carter’s<lb/>
assurance (5 March 1954), White’s quotation from the will (14 May 1954)<lb/>
suggests that Carter was incorrect. But this point, of course, is a legal one<lb/>
and is irrelevant to a scholarly editor’s obligation to think through textual<lb/>
decisions independently. The debate was quiescent for the next five years;<lb/>
but during that time Haber’s <hi rend="italic">The Manuscript Poems of A. E. Housman</hi><lb/>
(1955) appeared, and it produced discussion in the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> (1 July 1955; 15 June, 20,<lb/>
27 July 1956) and <hi rend="italic">The Book Collector</hi> (4:110–14) that intensified the lack of<lb/>
civility between Carter and Haber—though the anonymous front-page<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> review of Haber’s book on 29 April 1955, one of the most severe at-<lb/>
tacks the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> has ever published, was not by Carter but by his friend and<lb/>
occasional collaborator John Sparrow.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
The controversy over <hi rend="italic">The Collected Poems</hi> revived again when Haber<lb/>
brought out a volume in 1959 called <hi rend="italic">Complete Poems: Centennial Edition</hi><lb/>
(from the same American publisher as <hi rend="italic">The Collected Poems</hi>), which contained the<lb/>
same poems as Carter’s edition but with different texts. Carter asked (29<lb/>
May 1959) whether Haber had received authorization from the Housman<lb/>
estate, questioned a number of readings, and said that Haber’s textual es-<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="17"/>
<p>say “follows the expectable line of quiet superiority.”<lb/>After Haber replied (24 July 1959), Carter maintained that only his edition was authorized<lb/>and that Haber was not qualified to “tamper” with the text; and he concluded<lb/>his letter (14 August 1959) as follows:<lb/></p>
<quote>
<p>I am if anything more conscious to-day of the fallibility of my eyes and of my<lb/>judgment than I was, thirty-odd years ago, when Housman lectured to us on textual<lb/>criticism at Cambridge. Mr. Haber, as students of his writings must by now be well<lb/>aware, is afflicted with no such humility. This puts him at an advantage in the<lb/>protracted controversy into which I have been, most reluctantly, drawn. But I am not<lb/>sure that the advantage is shared by the poet and his readers, whom each of us is<lb/>trying in his own way to serve.<lb/></p>
</quote>
<p>Haber’s <hi rend="italic">Complete Poems</hi> was withdrawn after several impressions (follow-<lb/>ing the English publisher’s insistence that it was unauthorized), and the<lb/>debate over <hi rend="italic">The Collected Poems</hi> finally ended almost a decade later, when<lb/>White reported (11 January 1968) only three “trifling errors” in the latest<lb/>impression (the correction of which he acknowledged on 1 October 1971).<lb/>But since in the same issue (11 January 1968) Haber pursued his feud<lb/>with Sparrow, Carter could not resist one more sarcastic retort (14 March<lb/>1968). Reacting to Haber’s account of first looking into the manuscripts,<lb/>Carter says, “It is as if stout Cortes had beheld the Pacific for the first<lb/>time (except that Cortes, if Keats is to be believed, was silent).” And in the<lb/>same letter Carter calls White “that indefatigable vigilante of Housman’s<lb/>text.” The condescending tone was inappropriate, for Carter should him-<lb/>self have been such a vigilante, having accepted the task of editing these<lb/>poems. Nevertheless, his 1939 edition gave readers convenient access to<lb/>the body of Housman’s poetry for the first time; and, in its successive revi-<lb/>sions, it remained the standard text for many decades.<lb/></p>
<p>Aside from his various book publications of the 1930s, Carter made<lb/>important contributions to the book world during these years through his<lb/>journalism and his participation in other activities that promoted com-<lb/>munication among members of that world. His first book-related jour-<lb/>nalism appeared in <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, as a result of his having become<lb/>acquainted with its editor, Frederick G. Melcher, during his first trip to<lb/>New York in 1929. At that time <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> was a crucial journal<lb/>for the antiquarian-book world as well as the new-book world through its<lb/>inclusion of a department called “Old and Rare Books,” which provided<lb/>substantial articles and reviews along with columns by Frederick M. Hop-<lb/>kins (“Rare Book Notes”) and Jacob Blanck (“News from the Rare Book<lb/>Shops”). Carter became a regular contributor, producing nearly seventy<lb/>pieces (articles, reviews, letters) from 1930 through 1947, at which time<lb/>the function of the rare-book section was taken over by a new periodical,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Antiquarian Bookman</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> did not forget its role in Carter’s<lb/>)</p>
<pb n="18"/>
<p>career and offered one of the most informative biographical articles about <lb/>
him in its issue of 3 January 1953.) When, in the issue of 20 December <lb/>
1941, he looked back on his <hi rend="italic">PW</hi> writings, he found “some couched in <lb/>
the intolerant language of youth, others in the autocratic style of middle <lb/>
age, but none of them expressing sentiments to which their writer would <lb/>
not still subscribe.” They include some of the best articles he ever wrote.<lb/>
</p>
<p>At the same time Carter was playing a role in the creation of another <lb/>
outlet for book-world news, the back page of the <hi rend="italic">Times Literary Supplement</hi>.<lb/>
Michael Sadleir was the prime mover in this endeavor: in early 1931 he <lb/>
convened a group of friends (including Carter, Pollard, Percy Muir, John <lb/>
Hayward, and Dudley Massey) to discuss with Simon Nowell-Smith, a <lb/>
new member of the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> staff, the possibility of expanding the cover-<lb/>
age of the book world on the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> back page from the limited “<hi rend="italic">Notes <lb/>on Sales</hi>” it presently carried. This group, which became known as the <lb/>
“Biblio Boys,” continued (with an evolving membership) to have monthly <lb/>
dinners for many decades; it stands as a major example of the role that <lb/>
social connections and personal communication can play in the respon-<lb/>
sible development of a field (as glimpsed in Bertram Rota catalogue 290, <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Biblio-Boys</hi>, 1999). The earliest instance of the group’s influence was <lb/>
the invigoration of the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> back page, which did become a widely fol-<lb/>
lowed forum for the antiquarian-book world. Carter was by far its most <lb/>
prolific contributor—and, beginning in 1946 during Stanley Morison’s <lb/>
editorship, its formally appointed supervisor, a position he kept (except <lb/>
during his Washington years, 1953–55) until 1967, when the bibliographi-<lb/>
cal page ceased to be a regular feature. He wrote about 700 reviews for <lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> between 1931 and the end of his life, along with some 300 other <lb/>
pieces (letters, articles, and notes, many of them amounting to additional <lb/>
reviews). His sensible and well-expressed views (which had a scholarly <lb/>
underpinning) were thereby given wide circulation. But the <hi rend="italic">TLS</hi> policy of <lb/>
anonymity meant that most readers (those not privy to book-world gos-<lb/>
sip) were not aware that Carter’s was the dominant voice through which <lb/>
they were being provided with remarkably thorough coverage from the <lb/>
antiquarian-book world, including reports of auctions and exhibitions as <lb/>
well as reviews of bibliographical journals and books.<lb/>
</p>
<p>Another product of the Biblio Boys’ conversations, though of much <lb/>
shorter duration, was <hi rend="italic">Bibliographical Notes &amp; Queries</hi>, a periodical that <lb/>
Muir undertook to edit from the Elkin Mathews shop, beginning in Janu-<lb/>
ary of 1935. Carter did his part to make the journal succeed by furnishing <lb/>
a large number of queries and replies (many under pseudonyms), covering <lb/>
a wide range of topics, from publishing practices to specific books (often <lb/>
with substantial discussions). But the services to scholarship provided by <lb/>
the journal were not sufficiently used to allow it to continue past the May <lb/>
1939 issue. It was nevertheless a valiant attempt to promote the inter-<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="19"/>
<p>
change of ideas and information, a perennial concern of Carter’s circle <lb/>
of book-world friends. His own efforts— in reviews, notes, catalogue en-<lb/>
tries, talks, and conversations—took up a lot of his time, but they played <lb/>
a major role, through their ubiquity and style, in educating all kinds of <lb/>
participants in the book world. And they did not prevent his producing <lb/>
substantial scholarly work. In May of 1939, when <hi rend="italic">BN&amp;Q</hi> ended and he <lb/>
marked his thirty-fourth birthday, he could look back on a decade of im-<lb/>
pressive accomplishment, rarely equaled in bibliographical history.<lb/>
</p>
<head>The 1940s</head>
<p>
Carter’s role in the war effort began in September 1939, when he be-<lb/>
came a press censor for the Ministry of Information, serving as informa-<lb/>
tion secretary to the Minister, Brendan Bracken. His duties there allowed <lb/>
him to continue his work at Scribner’s (whose office at 23 Bedford Square <lb/>
was around the corner); but four years later, in November 1943, he was <lb/>
named director of the General Division of the Ministry’s New York office, <lb/>
called British Information Services, which necessitated his taking a leave <lb/>
of absence from Scribner’s. (In his New York position, which involved <lb/>
being supervisor of publications, he wrote in 1945 an anonymous and <lb/>
widely circulated pamphlet, <hi rend="italic">Victory in Burma</hi>, intended to show, as he says <lb/>
at the outset, that Britain’s Burma campaigns “have been an integral and <lb/>
a vital part of the over-all Allied strategy in the war against Japan.”) His <lb/>
government service ended in October 1945; and at the beginning of 1946 <lb/>
he was named managing director of Scribner’s London office, with new <lb/>
responsibilities added to his previous ones. It is understandable, therefore, <lb/>
that the pace of his writing in the 1930s could not be maintained in the <lb/>
1940s. But he did produce a major book and kept up his journalistic pres-<lb/>
ence, even adding two mass-circulation magazines, <hi rend="italic">The Atlantic Monthly</hi> <lb/>
and <hi rend="italic">The Cornhill Magazine</hi>, to his outlets (having written some theater <lb/>
reviews for <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> in 1940).<lb/>
</p>
<p>
His reviews and reports for <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> in the late 1930s and <lb/>
early 1940s contain many moving references to the war. He begins his <lb/>
comment on the first volume of W. W. Greg’s drama bibliography this <lb/>
way: “This is the week of Hitler’s invasion of Holland, Belgium, Luxem-<lb/>
bourg and France. It is, therefore, a week in which the words ‘important’ <lb/>
and ‘a major event’ sound a little odd when applied to a book.” Later in <lb/>
the same column, he notes the ending of <hi rend="italic">Bibliographical Notes &amp; Queries</hi> and <lb/>
adds, “Let us hope that it may revive, with other humane activities, when <lb/>
we reach that post-war world which now looks so much like a mirage” <lb/>
(15 June 1940). The title of another piece, “Bomb-Proof Bibliography” <lb/>
(21 October 1939), is explained at the outset: “When the newspapers <lb/>
are full of the war, and our sleep is constantly interrupted by air-raid <lb/>

<pb n="20"/>
<p>
warnings, it is comforting to turn, for a change of air, to these scholarly <lb/>
pages” (referring to Dorothy Blakey’s Minerva Press bibliography). In the <lb/>
spring of 1941 he could report, in reference to the Maggs shop, that “the <lb/>
nightingale is still singing in Berkeley Square—this year in the key of B <lb/>
minor” (19 April 1941). <lb/>
One of the high points of the war years for him, and one of the most <lb/>
emotional, was the occasion (7 July 1941) when he presented to Churchill <lb/>
the manuscript of Clough’s poem that Churchill had read in a radio broad-<lb/>
cast two months earlier; his charming account, in the issue of 2 August <lb/>
1941, is “Clough to Churchill.” On that occasion he also gave Churchill <lb/>
a copy of <hi rend="italic">Grim Glory</hi>, the 1941 book of wartime photographs edited by his <lb/>
wife, for which he had composed the dedication to Churchill. (Five years <lb/>
earlier, on 26 December 1936, he had married Ernestine Fantl, a native <lb/>
of Savannah, Georgia, who was then the curator of architecture at the <lb/>
Museum of Modern Art.) The most memorable of all these pieces, “A <lb/>
Bookseller’s Day in London” (2 November 1940), reports that “it’s three <lb/>
weeks now since I went to sleep not hearing a German bomber some-<lb/>
where overhead”; and he wakes up to “the now all too familiar sound of <lb/>
the demolition squads shovelling piles of broken glass into trucks.” Instead <lb/>
of reading the morning papers he turns to a favorite essay by his great-<lb/>
great-uncle William Johnson Cory, “which makes me think of sanity and <lb/>
the classics and all the things I was brought up to respect.” His account of <lb/>
his day’s routine under wartime conditions is journalism at its best, vividly <lb/>
conveying the atmosphere of a particular time and place. <lb/>
Carter’s major book of the 1940s resulted from his being asked to de-<lb/>
liver the Sandars Lectures in Bibliography at Cambridge in 1947. Entitled <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Taste and Technique in Book-Collecting</hi>, the book was published on 26 July <lb/>
1948 by R. R. Bowker in New York (the publisher of <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>) <lb/>
and, three months later (on 29 October), by Cambridge University Press <lb/>
in England. (The Cambridge edition is preferable, with its wonderful <lb/>
typography, its comfortable feel in the hand, and its old-fashioned use <lb/>
of recto running-titles, obviously written by Carter, that summarize the <lb/>
content of each two-page spread—this last a feature of the <hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi> also. <lb/>
For typographic excellence, the book was named one of the “Fifty Books <lb/>
of the Year” by the National Book League.) It is, in my opinion, Carter’s <lb/>
best book, and the best book about book collecting ever written. Although <lb/>
it has many devotees, it has nevertheless been overshadowed by several <lb/>
of his other books. The reason may be its title, which sounds like a how-<lb/>
to manual. But the book is actually a perceptive historical study of book <lb/>
collecting, along with an account of the role of taste and technique (that <lb/>
is, connoisseurship) in making it a serious scholarly pursuit. He states in <lb/>
the preface that it is “not a primer or a text-book or a manual for begin-<lb/>
ners” but rather “a somewhat ruminative treatise”—or, as he later says, <lb/>
</p>
<pb n="21"/>
<lb/>an “advanced treatise of a general kind” (Cambridge edition, p. 107). And<lb/>
he begins the second part by describing what is to follow as “reflexions, <lb/>
not advice.” No one, he believes, “can learn how to collect from manuals <lb/>
or at second hand” (p. 91). Nevertheless, the book is full of well–reasoned <lb/>
observations, and anyone who takes them to heart will have acquired the <lb/>
best kind of preparation—not conveyed by instructions but by penetrat-<lb/>
ing insights born of wide experience and learning.<lb/>
<lb/>
The book is a <hi rend="italic">tour de force</hi>, or a series of such <hi rend="italic">tours</hi>, for each chapter <lb/>
is a showpiece. Elegant in structure, as in all other aspects, it is divided <lb/>
into two parts of six chapters each: the first part is called “Evolution” <lb/>
and the second “Method.” This pairing is not to be equated with “taste” <lb/>
and “technique,” because the latter two (for which we could substitute <lb/>
“temperament” and “approach”) run throughout the book as a unifying <lb/>
thread. The “Evolution” section is a marvelously rich account of nine-<lb/>
teenth-century British and American collecting (with a few glimpses of <lb/>
earlier centuries and the European continent)—rich both in the number <lb/>
of individuals cited and in the analyses of the patterns and motives they <lb/>
display (not forgetting the role of literary criticism). The second part, <lb/>
“Method,” includes chapters on “Tools and Terminology,” “Bookshop <lb/>
and Auction Room,” “Rarity” (the longest chapter and a particularly <lb/>
impressive one), and “Condition.” Even the discussion of reference books <lb/>
(in the first of these), is enjoyable; and although it is inevitably dated in its <lb/>
citations, it is still worth reading for its astute comments on categories of <lb/>
reference works. In the same way, the fact that the examples drawn on in <lb/>
every chapter have to be from before 1949 does not make the book seem <lb/>
dated, for they so thoroughly document a wide range of situations that <lb/>
one can see their applicability to any period. And the awesome profusion <lb/>
of examples, one of the hallmarks of the book, is an extreme demonstra-<lb/>
tion of the feats of memory attainable by attentive booksellers.<lb/>
<lb/>
The final chapter is appropriately on “Condition,” for a subcategory <lb/>
of that topic, “original condition,” turns up throughout the book: the pri-<lb/>
mary movement, after all, in the story that Carter tells of the evolution <lb/>
of book collecting is the growing concern with preserving books in their <lb/>
original condition. The earlier interest in possessing books in fine bindings <lb/>
began changing in the late nineteenth century, with Wise as a principal <lb/>
instigator, to an emphasis on the historical significance of original condi-<lb/>
tion. Carter’s investigations of nineteenth-century publishers’ bindings is <lb/>
an indication of his firm belief in the importance of such condition. If the <lb/>
published forms of books are relatively easy to define after the introduc-<lb/>
tion of edition-binding, they are not obvious for earlier books. From his <lb/>
first article, entitled “Original Condition: An Appeal to Reason” (1930), <lb/>
Carter continually argued for a “reasonable” approach to this question. <lb/>
By that he meant that a collector should not hold out for a copy in the un-<lb/>
<pb n="22"/>
<p>bound or temporarily bound condition that occasionally survives; instead,<lb/>one should be satisfied with a contemporary bound copy (which could be<lb/>one of the copies originally offered for retail sale). For this period, in other<lb/>words, original condition could refer to any of the forms that might have<lb/>been encountered in a bookseller’s shop.<lb/></p>
<p>His position is indeed reasonable, but when he writes on this subject,<lb/>he is inclined to take one false step: to use, as a support for his point of<lb/>view, the idea that boards or wrappers were “by intention ephemeral” (p.<lb/>178), representing “the chrysalis stage of production” (p. 180). The print-<lb/>er’s or publisher’s assumption that wrappers or boards would be replaced<lb/>does not alter the historical fact that such a stage existed and is therefore<lb/>worthy of attention. Carter does recognize the value of the bibliographi-<lb/>cal evidence (as he always does), but there was no need to introduce, as<lb/>if it were relevant, the presumed expectations of the producers of the<lb/>books. To do so may be a consolation for collectors, but it is a rare lapse<lb/>in logic for Carter.<lb/></p>
<p>As usual, his prose is a delight (even though in the 1970 reprint he<lb/>claimed to detect “a certain stylistic dandyism” in it). The book should be<lb/>read slowly, so that each paragraph (and most of its constituent sentences)<lb/>can be savored. The richness of the texture is created by—to name some<lb/>of its elements—balanced syntax, precise but often surprising diction,<lb/>striking metaphors, a profusion of proper names and italicized titles, a<lb/>judicious sprinkling of foreign words (including untransliterated Greek),<lb/>and an affinity for colons. One cannot help but think that his love of<lb/>seventeenth-century prose, especially Thomas Browne’s, played its part.<lb/></p>
<p>Dipping into the book anywhere is likely to pull up a memorable, and of-<lb/>ten aphoristic, sentence, such as: “whenever expertise becomes an end in<lb/>itself instead of the means to an end, it results in empty virtuosity” (p. 81).<lb/>Or, on the fondness some collectors feel for books of their youth: this at-<lb/>traction “often reflects the unpredictable influence of some miscellaneous<lb/>shelf which the mere accident of propinquity at a receptive period has<lb/>endowed with an unforgotten magic” (p. 72). Or, for a more extended ex-<lb/>ample, dealing with one of Carter’s favorite, and most important, topics:<lb/></p>
<p>And if I return now to individuality of taste and the variety of approach involved<lb/>in breaking new ground—both healthy signs of originality, enterprise and intelli-<lb/>gence—it is for the purpose of emphasising the importance of a sense of balance in<lb/>the general structure. For although I have been, and remain, a proponent of idiosyn-<lb/>crasy, a warm supporter of the unusual approach in book-collecting, I have detected<lb/>in myself and have sometimes suspected among my book-collecting friends a ten-<lb/>dency to a certain esotericism of taste which is analogous to, and is indeed sometimes<lb/>allied with, that conscious virtuosity in technique to which I referred earlier. It is,<lb/>equally with the other, a perfectly legitimate tendency in the sophisticated collector,<lb/>as long as it is clearly recognised as such. But since it is the sophisticated collectors<lb/></p>
<pb n="23"/>
who most influence the unsophisticated, there is always a danger that their manner-<lb/>
isms, whether of taste or method, will be imitated (and usually exaggerated) while<lb/>
their underlying purpose remains unrecognised: just as many an architect who slaps<lb/>
on a swag here or a cupola there fondly supposes himself to be thereby qualifying for<lb/>
comparison with Wren or Brunelleschi. (pp. 88–89)<lb/>
The rhythms of this paragraph, the placement of its pauses, leading to-<lb/>
ward the summarizing simile, make it a characteristic performance.<lb/>
The personality that comes through is learned and humane—to use<lb/>
the adjectives that Carter applied on the first page to A. W. Pollard’s<lb/>
great essay on book collecting in the eleventh edition of the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia<lb/>Britannica.</hi> Carter’s scholarly temperament, and his consequent concern<lb/>
with history, are evident throughout, epitomized perhaps in his insistence<lb/>
that any “restoration” of a book be accompanied by a statement in which<lb/>
“the nature of the repairs made to it” are “recorded indelibly” (p. 185).<lb/>
He insisted that scholarly bibliographical analyses have “a strong claim<lb/>
on the attention of the average collector” (p. 114), and he recognized<lb/>
the role of collectors as scholars: “the ultimate value of the bibliophile<lb/>
to pure scholarship depends on his recognition as an active entity, not<lb/>
a mere appendix” (p. 99). In his discussion of Sadleir’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliographia</hi><lb/>
series, Carter observed that it was “marked by a scholarly appreciation<lb/>
of the importance of book-structure and publishing practice to the intel-<lb/>
ligent collector, whose acquiescence in this proposition was enlisted by<lb/>
being taken for granted” (p. 61). There could be no better description of<lb/>
Carter’s own book.<lb/>
The same mind is obviously at work in his journalism of the 1940s.<lb/>
For example, in reviewing J. D. Cowley’s<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Bibliographical Description and<lb/>Cataloguing</hi>, he said, “The<lb/>
principles of bibliography are valid for books<lb/>
of all periods, and even the chronicler of a living author is the better for<lb/>
having learned how to collate an incunable” (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, 16 March<lb/>
1940). And after the war, when he described the great Yale convocation<lb/>
of October 1946 to “mark the return of the University’s collections to<lb/>
peacetime use” (<hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi>, 23 November 1946), he concluded his<lb/>
highly laudatory account with these important reflections:<lb/>
Objects—books, pictures, or bones—are part of the stuff of scholarship, of culture,<lb/>
of ideas. It is axiomatic that it is the duty of institutions to acquire, preserve and<lb/>
catalog them; generally agreed, though not everywhere achieved, that they should<lb/>
be readily available to those who need to study them; but much less often recognized<lb/>
that they require to be actively injected into the thoughts and studies of the academic,<lb/>
and also of the wider, world outside their glass cases. Every year museums and librar-<lb/>
ies get fuller and the problem of exploiting their resources more formidable. The<lb/>
methods by which this can best be done vary with the circumstances; but the amount<lb/>
of imagination and enterprise being devoted in this country [the United States] to<lb/>
making such collections as Yale’s not a mere adjunct but an integral and living part<lb/>
<pb n="24"/>
of the world of taste and scholarship is something of which Americans may rightly <lb/>
be proud.<lb/>
That these enlightened ideas, and others like them, were expressed in a <lb/>
journal with the wide readership (mostly nonbibliographical) of <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> <lb/>
was fortunate; and one cannot help regretting that Carter’s voice <lb/>
was not much heard there after the rare-book department was ceded to <lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Antiquarian Bookman</hi> in 1948.<lb/>
Two other publications of the 1940s deserve mention. In 1941, Carter <lb/>
and Brooke Crutchley (of Cambridge University Press) produced a re-<lb/>
vised edition of Harry G. Aldis’s 1916 <hi rend="italic">The Printed Book</hi>. Although their <lb/>
edition is now superseded, it is significant for the role it played for a <lb/>
decade or two. Their contribution was to provide up-to-date coverage <lb/>
of the nineteenth-century revolution in book production, especially the <lb/>
introduction of publishers’ binding and new methods of printing and il-<lb/>
lustration. The book was one more element in Carter’s ongoing effort to <lb/>
promote the study of nineteenth-century books. And since it sold well <lb/>
(with reprintings occurring in 1947 and 1951), it served that purpose ef-<lb/>
fectively. At the other end of the decade, in 1948, another of Carter’s <lb/>
perennial concerns was represented in <hi rend="italic">The Firm of Charles Ottley, Landon &amp; Co.</hi> <lb/>
(the title-page authorship credited to Carter “with Graham Pollard”). <lb/>
As the subtitle indicated, it was a “footnote to <hi rend="italic">An Enquiry</hi>,” proving four <lb/>
more pamphlets fraudulent and serving as the first interim report on the <lb/>
continuing investigation of the Wise-Forman forgeries.<lb/>
<head>The 1950s</head><lb/>
The next decade was one of dramatic change in Carter’s life. In early <lb/>
1953 Scribner’s closed most of its London operations, thus ending Cart-<lb/>
er’s quarter-century association with the firm (during which time he had <lb/>
made thirty-six Atlantic crossings). And in October of 1955 he happily <lb/>
joined Sotheby’s book department as a half-time associate, with special <lb/>
responsibility for being the American representative (a particularly appro-<lb/>
priate appointment since he already knew the American scene so well); <lb/>
this arrangement left him free to engage at the same time in independent <lb/>
consulting for collectors and librarians, an activity that extended the in-<lb/>
fluence of his ideas.<lb/>
During the two and a half years in between (from April 1953 to Oc-<lb/>
tober 1955), he was based at the British Embassy in Washington as the <lb/>
personal assistant (with the rank of Counsellor) to the British ambassador, <lb/>
Sir Roger Makins (a service for which he was later named Commander of <lb/>
the Order of the British Empire). He was a perfect choice, with his wide <lb/>
knowledge of the United States and his elegance in manner and dress as <lb/>
<pb n="25"/>
<p>well as in speaking and writing. The job had a large social component,<lb/>
and Carter and his wife greatly enjoyed this period of their lives. (In her<lb/>
entertaining and perceptive 1974 autobiography, <hi rend="italic">With Tongue in Chic</hi>, she<lb/>
says, “The Washington years were golden years.”) The flavor of their<lb/>
Washington life is suggested by a thank-you note from T. S. Eliot written<lb/>
on 22 May 1955, after a luncheon party at the Carters’ Georgetown house<lb/>
(quoted from R. M. Smythe auction catalogue 157, 13 November 1996,<lb/>
lot 412, with one correction):<lb/></p>
<p>
<quote>Dear Ernestine<lb/>
I can’t leave Washington without writing to thank you &amp; John for your hospitality<lb/>
— for a delicious lunch beautifully served in perfect surroundings and in a company<lb/>
at once distinguished and sympathetic. And if you were leaving Washington in the<lb/>
autumn for any other destination than London, I should say how sorry I was not to<lb/>
be able to look forward to a similar occasion next year.<lb/>
<lb/>
Yours gratefully<lb/>
Tom Eliot<lb/></quote>
</p>
<p>The glamorous life implied here (or “glittering,” as Ernestine called it) was<lb/>
not an unaccustomed one for the Carters: given the connections Carter<lb/>
had made through the international world of collecting and the fact that<lb/>
Ernestine had been, before the move to Washington, an influential fash-<lb/>
ion journalist with the English <hi rend="italic">Harper’s Bazaar</hi> (becoming Women’s Editor<lb/>
of <hi rend="italic">The Sunday Times</hi> on their return to London, and later Associate Editor),<lb/>
their combined circle of celebrity acquaintances was impressive, as was<lb/>
their entertaining. I have remarked in the past on the interdependence<lb/>
of all parts of a person’s life and on how the scholarly (or bibliographical)<lb/>
and the social nourish each other. One illustration of this point that I have<lb/>
used is the life of Mary Hyde, and it happens that the Hydes were New<lb/>
York friends of Carter. When Carter was setting up a New York office for<lb/>
Sotheby’s, Donald Hyde provided space and secretarial help in his law<lb/>
firm’s financial-district premises at 61 Broadway. Carter’s writings, no less<lb/>
than his bookselling activities, benefited from the knowledge and contacts<lb/>
furnished by his full social life.<lb/></p>
<p>Eighteen months before Carter began at the embassy in Washington,<lb/>
he delivered one of the Windsor Lectures at the University of Illinois<lb/>
and produced for that occasion a landmark essay, “Some Bibliographical<lb/>
Agenda”—agenda, that is, for the study of nineteenth-century English<lb/>
books, which was the subject of this lecture series in October 1951. (The<lb/>
essay was published the next year in a volume that included the essays<lb/>
by the other two lecturers that year, Gordon N. Ray and Carl J. Weber;<lb/>
Carter also selected it for his 1956 collection, <hi rend="italic">Books and Book-Collectors</hi>.)<lb/>
In his essay, Carter set the stage for future work: after summarizing the<lb/>
revolutionary changes in book production in the nineteenth century that<lb/></p>
<pb n="26"/>
<p>complicate bibliographical research on books of that period and after <lb/>
outlining what little work had been done, he focused on a few of the <lb/>
complicating features, such as cancels, binding variants, and inserted ad-<lb/>
vertisements. His comments, as always, are grounded in an understanding <lb/>
of the importance of printing and publishing history for bibliographical <lb/>
analysis and description.<lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">A</hi>t the time, Fredson Bowers’s <hi rend="italic">Principles of Bibliographical Description</hi> was a relatively new book, having been published at the very end of 1949; but Carter had absorbed it, and he ended his essay with a gener-<lb/>
ally shrewd assessment. He was sympathetic, of course, with Bowers’s <lb/>
conception of bibliography as historical scholarship, and he welcomed <lb/>
Bowers’s efforts to systematize work on modern books. But he correctly <lb/>
noted that Bowers’s lack of experience (at that time) with nineteenth- and <lb/>
twentieth-century books weakened his treatment of them, which showed <lb/>
“signs of the rigidity natural to a cautious man operating in comparatively <lb/>
unfamiliar territory.” One result, as Carter recognized, is that Bowers <lb/>
inappropriately extended to the period of publishers’ bindings the idea <lb/>
that only the sheets (and not the binding) of a book could be a determi-<lb/>
nant of <hi rend="italic">issue</hi>. The one place where Carter slipped up was when he said <lb/>
that Bowers’s collation formula might be “unnecessarily elaborate” for <lb/>
nineteenth-century books, seemingly not recognizing that the formula <lb/>
was not elaborate for books with a simple structure and that the for-<lb/>
mulary had to be prepared to handle complex structures, which many <lb/>
nineteenth-century books certainly do have. But if we make allowance <lb/>
for this misjudgment, we can still read the essay with profit for its many <lb/>
helpful insights and its point of view.<lb/>
</p>
<p>About a year after Carter delivered this lecture, his <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi> for Book-<lb/>
Collectors (1952) was published—the book that has proved to be his most <lb/>
famous one. It has sold well throughout the English-speaking world for <lb/>
several generations and is now in its ninth edition (having been sensitively <lb/>
revised several times since his death by Nicolas Barker, most recently <lb/>
with Simran Thadani). The book was not the first glossary of book-world <lb/>
terms: a well-established one, <hi rend="italic">The Bookman’s Glossary</hi>, had been published <lb/>
in 1926 by R. R. Bowker, the publisher of the American edition of Carter’s <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Taste and Technique</hi>, and was in its third edition in 1952. Carter’s concern <lb/>
with improving it had been shown in a letter noted in <hi rend="italic">Publishers’ Weekly</hi> on <lb/>
11 August 1945; but the <hi rend="italic">Glossary</hi> was geared more toward librarians and <lb/>
publishers than collectors and dealers, and the <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi> was, as Carter says <lb/>
in his preface, the first “to deal comprehensively with the terminology of <lb/>
this particular subject and no other.” He benefited from the advice of an <lb/>
impressive group of consultants, enumerated in the preface as “a sort of <lb/>
Tenth Legion,” and the result was a remarkably thorough treatment. It <lb/>
included not only terms one encounters in dealers’ catalogues and basic <lb/>

</div>