<div type="section" n="2">
  <head>The Sources of the Sussex Declaration: A Reconsideration by John Bidwell</head>
<pb n="105"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">THE SOURCES OF THE SUSSEX DECLARATION:</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">A RECONSIDERATION</hi></head><lb/>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">John Bidwell</name></byline><lb/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">I</hi>n April&amp;nbsp;2017 several newspapers carried stories about the discovery of a manu-<lb/>
script Declaration of Independence. Conjectures about the political signifi-<lb/>
cance of the manuscript began to circulate in print and then proliferated on <lb/>
the web where the original announcements are still accessible. The discovery <lb/>
was sufficiently newsworthy that Prime Minister Theresa May and President <lb/>
Donald&amp;nbsp;Trump took time to look at it while Trump was making his UK state <lb/>
visit in&amp;nbsp;2019. Unfortunately, they and their advisors were misinformed. Basic <lb/>
assumptions about the date and origins of the manuscript are in error and have <lb/>
prompted unfounded claims about its historical importance. I hope to correct <lb/>
those errors here and set the record straight by reviewing the bibliographical <lb/>
arguments that made that manuscript a media sensation.</p>
<p>My main concern is with an article by Danielle Allen and Emily Sneff in <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi> (<hi rend="italic">PBSA</hi>). It serves as the definitive <lb/>
announcement of the discovery and a means of explaining the authors’ research <lb/>
methods. They describe and date the manuscript (see figure&amp;nbsp;1) in the article and <lb/>
suggest a route by which it came to its present location in the West Sussex Record <lb/>
Office (WSRO), Chichester, England. In brief this is how they present their find-<lb/>
ings: sometime between&amp;nbsp;1783 and&amp;nbsp;1790 a clerk made a copy of the Declaration <lb/>
of Independence, the manuscript that had been engrossed on parchment for the <lb/>
Continental Congress in&amp;nbsp;1776. The clerk had trouble reading the original, com-<lb/>
mitted errors of transcription, and even smudged the title, but was ambitious <lb/>
enough to write it out on a large sheet of parchment. Measuring&amp;nbsp;24 by&amp;nbsp;30½ inches, <lb/>
it was intended for display and was probably commissioned by the Pennsylva-<lb/>
nia lawyer James&amp;nbsp;Wilson&amp;nbsp;(1742–1798), one of the Founding Fathers who had <lb/>
signed the engrossed Declaration. Wilson played a prominent part in drafting <lb/>
the Constitution, which he also signed, and relied on this copy to argue for a <lb/>
strong national government founded on the will of the people rather than a loose <lb/>
confederation of semi-independent states. His concept of nationhood is evident <lb/>
in the way the clerk transcribed the fifty-six signatures in the engrossed Decla-<lb/>
ration, not grouped by states as in the original but intermingled in a seemingly <lb/>
</p>
<pb n="106"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 1.</head>
  <figDesc>The Sussex Declaration. West Sussex Record Office, Add Mss 8981. 24 × 30½ inches.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<pb n="107"/>
<p>random order, as if to express the personal convictions of the Signers instead of<lb/>
their duties to the states they represented.<note n="1">Danielle Allen and Emily Sneff, “The Sussex Declaration: Dating the Parchment Man-<lb/>uscript of the Declaration of Independence Held at the West Sussex Record Office (Chichester,<lb/>UK),” Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America 112 (2018), 357– 403. Andrea L. Immel, the<lb/>late William L. Joyce, Elizabeth K. Lynch, Philip S. Palmer, David L. Vander Meulen, Ted<lb/>Widmer, and Michael Winship very kindly provided advice and assistance while I was prepar-<lb/>ing the first drafts of this essay.</note><lb/>
After this preliminary overview, the authors explore the historical context in<lb/>
a second article published in the Georgetown Journal of Law &amp; Public Policy (GJLPP).<lb/>
Here they narrow down its dates to 1785–1787 and discuss how it figured in<lb/>
the deliberations of the Constitutional Convention. They note the possibility<lb/>
that it had belonged to Charles Lennox, third duke of Richmond (1735–1806),<lb/>
whose family seat was not far from Chichester. Richmond was an advocate of the<lb/>
American cause, a proponent of parliamentary reform, and a tenacious member<lb/>
of the opposition sympathetic to the ideals enunciated in the Declaration. Allen<lb/>
and Sneff make other conjectures in those two articles and expand on them in<lb/>
statements to the press. They refer to the manuscript as the Sussex Declaration<lb/>
and I will too, although I disagree with them about its origins and significance.<note n="2">Danielle Allen and Emily Sneff, “Golden Letters: James Wilson, the Declaration of<lb/>Independence, and the Sussex Declaration,” Georgetown Journal of Law &amp; Public Policy 17 (2019),<lb/>193–230. This issue contains the proceedings of a symposium on the life and career of James<lb/>Wilson.</note><lb/>
While the PBSA article was being prepared for publication, they issued a press<lb/>
release on 20 April 2017 in collaboration with a Communications Officer at Har-<lb/>
vard University. Within days, articles about the Sussex Declaration appeared in<lb/>
the New York Times, the Guardian, and the Washington Post. A CBS television crew<lb/>
showed up at the West Sussex Record Office to film the document on site. A<lb/>
Wikipedia article about the “physical history” of the Declaration cites two of the<lb/>
newspaper reports as well as the press release, which can still be found online in<lb/>
Danielle Allen’s Declaration Resources Project website. They elaborate on their<lb/>
hypotheses in a lecture at the National Archives broadcast by C-SPAN on 6 July<lb/>
2017 and recapitulated in the online National Archives News with a link to a You-<lb/>
Tube version of the lecture. There and in other media appearances they speculate<lb/>
that Thomas Paine may have been an intermediary responsible for bringing the<lb/>
Sussex Declaration to the duke of Richmond. Their claims are less explicit in the<lb/>
New York Times article, which only queries the connection with Paine and Rich-<lb/>
mond. Performing due diligence, however, the reporter consulted outside experts<lb/>
such as a legal historian who observed that even if their attribution to Wilson is<lb/>
wrong, an early manuscript of the Declaration is still “the discovery of a lifetime.”<note n="3">Kerri Lawrence, “Historians Discuss Their Discovery of ‘Sussex Declaration,’” National<lb/>Archives News (10 July 2017), https://www.archives.gov/news/topics/sussex-declaration (ac-<lb/>cessed 20 March 2023); Jennifer Schuessler, “Discovered: An Unknown Declaration,” New<lb/>York Times (22 April 2017), C1 and C4; Declaration Resources Project, https://declaration.fas.<lb/>harvard.edu (accessed 20 March 2023).</note><lb/>
At the end of the PBSA article Allen and Sneff consider an alternative<lb/>
hypothesis: their document was based on a miniature facsimile Declaration<lb/>
printed in Boston in or after 1836 (figure 2). I brought that facsimile to their<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="108"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 2.</head>
  <figDesc>The Lewis H. Bridgham miniature Declaration. Author’s collection. Reproduced<lb/>slightly enlarged, 5¾ × 4½ inches.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<pb n="109"/>
<p>
attention after they had sent me a preliminary draft of their article. No great <lb/>
amount of scrutiny was required to see that it was the source of the Sussex Dec-<lb/>
laration. The similarities in style and structure are obvious. In my view they are <lb/>
not dealing with a clerk who rearranged the signatures to fulfill Wilson’s politi-<lb/>
cal agenda but rather an amateur who transcribed the facsimile in an exercise of <lb/>
penmanship. But they submit that hypothesis only to dismiss it. Their rebuttal <lb/>
touches on several topics, mainly textual inconsistencies and a question of qual-<lb/>
ity: the facsimile was a mass-produced keepsake measuring no more than 5¾ by <lb/>
4½ inches. Why, they ask, would the clerk use such a paltry print to copy out a <lb/>
Declaration on this scale? They defend their position by pointing out anomalies <lb/>
in the layout of the facsimile not repeated in the manuscript, a transcription <lb/>
problem posed by the sequence of signatures. If the clerk had been copying the <lb/>
facsimile, they say, surely those anomalies would be present in the manuscript.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
So, what is the source of the Sussex Declaration: the parchment engrossed <lb/>
for the Continental Congress, signed by most of its members on 2 August 1776, <lb/>
the iconic document in the National Archives—or a cheap facsimile printed in <lb/>
Boston some sixty years later? What is the source of the Boston facsimile? In <lb/>
the following I will propose answers to those questions less glamorous than the <lb/>
hypotheses of Allen and Sneff but more consistent with the writing practices <lb/>
and design considerations involved in making a copy of the Declaration. Here, <lb/>
as in other bibliographical endeavors, the pure and simple physical evidence <lb/>
should prevail over less substantial arguments, no matter how many of them <lb/>
may be mustered against a few overriding objections. I will address the main <lb/>
arguments of the <hi rend="smallcaps">PBSA</hi> article, which is intended to establish the date of the <lb/>
Sussex Declaration. I will not be concerned with the <hi rend="smallcaps">GJLPP</hi> article, for it is <lb/>
entirely predicated on its predecessor and assumes that the alternative hypoth-<lb/>
esis has been refuted. If the dates they propose are not valid, then they cannot <lb/>
attribute it to James Wilson and cannot claim that Wilson used it during the <lb/>
Constitutional Convention.<lb/>
</p>
<head>I</head>
<p>
Allen and Sneff begin by recounting the provenance of the Sussex Declara-<lb/>
tion. They note that it was deposited in the <hi rend="smallcaps">WSRO</hi> by a local solicitor whose firm <lb/>
had done business with the Richmond family. A <hi rend="smallcaps">WSRO</hi> archivist told them that <lb/>
the solicitor once had his pick of the family papers that had been entrusted to the <lb/>
firm since the eighteenth century, but were discarded in bulk sometime before <lb/>
1956. Indeed, the finding list of the deposit mentions two or three items relating <lb/>
to the family but they are so scattered and insignificant that it is hard to believe <lb/>
that they came from a trove dating back to the eighteenth century. The deposit <lb/>
is clearly the gleanings of a local history collector who found a few curiosities in <lb/>
his office and kept anything else that caught his eye. The finding list relegates the <lb/>
Sussex Declaration to a miscellaneous section at the end where it is accompanied <lb/>
by an 1828 legal opinion about a conveyance to the duke of Richmond’s trustees, <lb/>
checks drawn on a London bank in the 1840s and 1850s, an advertisement of a <lb/>
London dyer active ca. 1844, a list of the kings and queens of England, and a <lb/>
</p>
<pb n="110"/>
<p>
1750 letter from the bell ringers of Chichester. With the exception of the letter,<lb/>
nothing in this section has a secure date earlier than 1825. Nonetheless a WSRO<lb/>
archivist dated the Declaration in the late eighteenth century, an educated guess<lb/>
for cataloguing purposes, but Allen and Sneff make it a starting point of their<lb/>
exposition in PBSA.<lb/>
They find additional evidence in the physical features of the Sussex Declara-<lb/>
tion. They note that it was written on a large size of parchment suitable for ex-<lb/>
hibition and that it has nail holes in the corners as if it had been displayed at one<lb/>
point. On the advice of conservators they concede that the nails might have been<lb/>
meant to restrain the parchment for other purposes. They view the square shape<lb/>
of the nail holes as evidence for a date in the eighteenth century, but the source<lb/>
they cite contradicts their conclusions. Yes, early hand-wrought iron nails were<lb/>
square but so were the cut nails produced in British and American factories dur-<lb/>
ing the first half of the nineteenth century. Wire nails, which would have made<lb/>
round holes in the parchment, were not introduced until the 1850s in America or<lb/>
a bit earlier in England. The parchment was made of a middling-quality sheep-<lb/>
skin. They contend that it was “well prepared,” which may be so, but a Library<lb/>
of Congress conservation report graded it below a more prepossessing calfskin<lb/>
document they had brought in for comparison.<hi rend="sup">4</hi><lb/>
The Sussex Declaration may have been put on view, but then it was filed<lb/>
away and forgotten. It was folded twice for storage, in which state it became<lb/>
severely soiled on one side, badly abraded along the folds with loss of text, and<lb/>
seriously damaged on the outer edge of the four leaves with loss of parchment.<lb/>
As to the edge damage, Allen and Sneff admit that a rodent could be to blame<lb/>
but believe it is more likely that a seal had been removed (PBSA, p. 362). In that<lb/>
case, however, the two outer leaves would have suffered more than the two in-<lb/>
ner leaves. When I saw it at the WSRO, the depredations seemed to me to be<lb/>
uniform on each of the four leaves. They do not explain what function a seal<lb/>
would have served and why it would have been removed. But those conjectures<lb/>
are beside the point because the parchment was then folded a third time as if<lb/>
it had been demoted to an even smaller storage space. These signs of abuse<lb/>
and neglect are hard to square with their contention that it was a “ceremonial”<lb/>
manuscript, a word used repeatedly in the PBSA article to signify the ambitious<lb/>
intentions of those who produced it. In the GJLPP article they use the word even<lb/>
more frequently to express its iconic function and the innovative ideas of James<lb/>
Wilson, who used it to elaborate his views on the Constitution. If it was owned<lb/>
by Richmond, then it must have fallen out of favor in a bad way to end up in<lb/>
that ignominious condition.<lb/>
The title has some words in black letter, but the text is mostly in a utilitar-<lb/>
ian round hand, which Allen and Sneff attribute to a clerk employed by Wilson.<lb/>
It cannot be assigned to a prominent politician although they have examined<lb/>
the writings of likely candidates and their amanuenses as well. They notice the<lb/>
</p>
<p>
4. Preservation Directorate, Library of Congress, “Advanced Image Processing of Mul-<lb/>
tispectral Images of the Sussex Declaration,” Declaration Resources Project website; Lee H.<lb/>
Nelson, “Nail Chronology as an Aid to Dating Old Buildings,” History News 23 (1968), 203–14.<lb/>
See also “Among the Nail-Makers,” Harper’s New Monthly Magazine 21 (1860), 161–63.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="111"/>
<p>absence of the long s prevalent in manuscripts of this period, but they believe<lb/>
that the clerk was one of the “stylistic radicals” who had dropped that usage.<lb/>
They do not mention that Wilson sometimes used a long s in his drafts of the<lb/>
Constitution, apparently more conservative in his writing practices than his hired<lb/>
hand. Arguing for the American origins of the manuscript, they compare it with<lb/>
contemporary deeds and indentures, some reproduced in the <hi rend="italic">PBSA</hi> article, some<lb/>
in the Declaration Resources Project website. They detect stylistic features more<lb/>
likely to be local than to come from England, but to my mind the sample is too<lb/>
small to be convincing. Their morphological analysis of the document has been<lb/>
more useful for their purposes than the script itself, which is difficult to date.<lb/>
Allen and Sneff assert that the clerk made several drafts before completing<lb/>
the “final fair copy” of this manuscript (<hi rend="italic">PBSA</hi>, p. 367). They perceive a certain<lb/>
amount of effort expended to produce a symmetrical composition, uniform line<lb/>
endings, no word breaks, and other artistic touches worthy of a document in-<lb/>
tended for display. Nonetheless the clerk botched the job at the beginning and<lb/>
made it worse while trying to correct it. He began to write a date in the same<lb/>
size and style of the black letter “In Congress” on the first line of the title but<lb/>
then thought better of it and began to rub out his mistake. His erasure merely<lb/>
smudged his work leaving remnants of that date easily apparent at first sight. For<lb/>
Allen and Sneff this was an opportunity for further scientific investigation, the<lb/>
results of which are posted on the Declaration Resources Project website and<lb/>
summarized in the <hi rend="italic">PBSA</hi> article. They commissioned various tests using imaging<lb/>
techniques and other digital technologies to scrutinize the erasure. In the docu-<lb/>
mentation they received they see evidence that the erased date referred to when<lb/>
the clerk was working on the manuscript: either “July 4, 178” or “July 4, 179,”<lb/>
the last digit indecipherable. Starting on the fair copy, forgetting the momentous<lb/>
date of Independence, the clerk made an absent-minded slip of the pen as if he<lb/>
was thinking about his present circumstances instead of his assignment to rein-<lb/>
terpret the Declaration.<lb/>
The technical reports on the website are inconclusive and are mostly about<lb/>
methodology. A Library of Congress conservator considered the possibility that<lb/>
the third digit in the erased date might be an 8 or 9 but was not willing to com-<lb/>
mit to that reading. I believe there is an easier explanation. Yes, the clerk made<lb/>
a mistake but when and why did he try to fix it? It is more likely that the clerk<lb/>
forgot the July 4, 1776, date while copying out the text, and then went back to<lb/>
write it on the first line next to “In Congress.” Then he realized that this stopgap<lb/>
measure would spoil the symmetrical composition and erased his work, decid-<lb/>
ing instead to insert the missing date between the first and second lines, obvi-<lb/>
ously an afterthought. He had to break it up at either end of the title and cut it<lb/>
down to a size that would fit between the lines. He used a similarly compressed<lb/>
cursive to mend a mistake in the fifth line of text, correcting the word “when”<lb/>
to “whenever.” This sequence of events explains the smudged title, the inserted<lb/>
date, and the amateurish script. Other mistakes provide opportunities for Allen<lb/>
and Sneff to devise an elaborate argument for the early origins and historical<lb/>
significance of the Sussex Declaration. These too can be explained by viewing<lb/>
them in a bibliographical context, a means of understanding the copying process<lb/>
in manuscript and print.</p>
<pb n="112"/>
<p>
The bibliographical record begins in 1776 with the broadside printed in the shop<lb/>
of John Dunlap and continues through the eighteenth century with its letter-<lb/>
press progeny in newspapers and broadsides. In the nineteenth century, however,<lb/>
Americans turned to the engrossed Declaration for a validation of their republi-<lb/>
can beliefs and an affirmation of their national identity. They could buy copies<lb/>
of the manuscript reproduced the way they wanted to see it, more as an object of<lb/>
veneration than an artifact of history. They expected the text to be accurate, of<lb/>
course, but they also sought to enhance its meaning with patriotic imagery, ar-<lb/>
tistic interventions maybe strange to our eyes yet perfectly compatible with their<lb/>
concept of a facsimile. New and improved intaglio, letterpress, and lithographic<lb/>
printing technologies helped them to realize its iconic potential in copiously or-<lb/>
namented allegorical compositions, some intended to be works of art, others di-<lb/>
rected toward the bottom of the market. Good and bad, each of these prints has<lb/>
a publication history, which can tell us why some were not reliable, what went<lb/>
wrong with them, and how they caused the mistakes in the Sussex Declaration.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
Benjamin Owen Tyler and John Binns were the first to issue facsimiles of the<lb/>
Declaration. Tyler was a writing master, Binns a newspaper publisher, each in<lb/>
his own way well qualified to produce and market patriotic prints. Tyler stole a<lb/>
march on Binns, who had issued proposals in March 1816 but allowed his artists<lb/>
to take their time and did not finish his version until October 1819. Tyler issued<lb/>
his in May 1818 at half the price his rival had announced. And as a further provo-<lb/>
cation, he launched an advertising campaign capitalizing on an endorsement he<lb/>
had received from Thomas Jefferson. Binns took the bait and complained about<lb/>
the interloper’s exploitive tactics. Quick to take offense, eager for publicity, the<lb/>
facsimilists fought a newspaper war extolling the beauty and accuracy of their<lb/>
products while attacking the character, honesty, and patriotism of their adversar-<lb/>
ies. Both obtained impressive certificates of authenticity, Tyler from the Acting<lb/>
Secretary of State Richard Rush, Binns from Secretary of State John Quincy<lb/>
Adams. Both embellished the text in styles fashionable at that time. Tyler showed<lb/>
off his skills in penmanship by transcribing the text in ornamental scripts, some<lb/>
more elaborate than others but reaching a rhetorical crescendo in the “emphati-<lb/>
cal words” at the end. Binns opted for an allegorical design, an oval “cordon of<lb/>
honor” composed of state seals surrounding the text and surmounted by symbols<lb/>
of prosperity next to medallion portraits of Washington, Hancock and Jefferson.<lb/>
The fifty-six signatures beneath the text were the only portions of these prints<lb/>
rendered in what we would consider a facsimile, Tyler’s truer to the original than<lb/>
Binns’s, both with distinctive traits that make them easily identifiable. The writ-<lb/>
ing master improved some of the signatures, unconsciously correcting marks of<lb/>
infirmity and haste. The signatures in the allegorical print had to be truncated<lb/>
in places to fit in that crowded composition.<hi rend="sup">5</hi><lb/>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="sup">5.</hi> Benjamin Owen Tyler, <hi rend="italic">Declaration of Independence: A Candid Statement of Facts</hi> (1818),<lb/>
pp.&amp;nbsp;6 and&amp;nbsp;15; John Binns, <hi rend="italic">Recollections of the Life of John Binns</hi> (1854), pp.&amp;nbsp;234–37; “Declaration of<lb/>
Independence,” <hi rend="italic">Niles’ Weekly Register</hi> (6&amp;nbsp;July&amp;nbsp;1816), 310–11; “Declaration of Independence,” <hi rend="italic">Daily<lb/>
National Intelligencer</hi> (23&amp;nbsp;October&amp;nbsp;1819), 2.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="113"/>
<p>In 1823 John Quincy Adams commissioned an official government facsimile <lb/>
of the entire manuscript, a state-of-the-art replica expertly engraved by William <lb/>
J. Stone. It is the definitive record of the original, which suffered so much mis-<lb/>
treatment and neglect that it is now barely legible. Printed on parchment in a <lb/>
limited edition, the Stone facsimile did not circulate as widely as the Binns and <lb/>
Tyler facsimiles, which were copied, imitated, and adapted well into the 1890s. <lb/>
Even a restrike on imitation parchment could not compete with prints deco-<lb/>
rated with allegorical vignettes, patriotic emblems, and portraits of Founding <lb/>
Fathers. As much as one would expect these decorations to defeat the function <lb/>
of a facsimile, this style did not go out of fashion until the end of the century. <lb/>
Then, finally, the unadorned Stone facsimile came into its own and became the <lb/>
standard visualization of the document, the source of reproductions published <lb/>
by the government, expounded in textbooks, sold as souvenirs, and printed on <lb/>
Independence Day in the New York Times.<hi rend="sup">6</hi><lb/></p>
<p>Facsimile signatures derived either from Binns or Tyler appear in more than <lb/>
ninety prints during the nineteenth century. The chain of transmission can be <lb/>
complicated, a multistage process with some prints acting as intermediaries, oth-<lb/>
ers deriving the signatures from reproductions in illustrated books. Nonetheless, <lb/>
they all belong to those two families. With one exception, publishers paid no <lb/>
attention to the Stone signatures until just before the Centennial. At least eighty <lb/>
prints have an ornamental border of state seals directly or indirectly based on <lb/>
Binns’s “cordon of honor,” a versatile design motif easily adapted to include <lb/>
additional pictorial matter. No less popular, Tyler’s “emphatical” rendition of <lb/>
the text inspired at least twenty-seven imitations in letterpress, intaglio, and <lb/>
lithography. The New York map and print publisher Horace Thayer incorpo-<lb/>
rated Tyler’s lettering in lithographs ca. 1859–1863, large allegorical composi-<lb/>
tions including state seals, the American eagle, and a miniature reproduction <lb/>
of John Trumbull’s painting <hi rend="italic">The Declaration of Independence</hi>. W. Duke Sons &amp; Co.<lb/></p>
<note n="6" place="foot">6. Printed in or after 1833, the restrike was issued as a folding plate in Peter Force’s Ameri-<lb/>
can Archives, 5th ser., vol. 1 (1848). Force approved a payment to Stone for this printing job in <lb/>
1839. Most surviving copies are on folded imitation parchment, although some are unfolded, <lb/>
possibly because Stone or Force sold them separately. The American Antiquarian Society has a <lb/>
copy on paper watermarked J WHATMAN TURKEY MILL 1850. The Department of State <lb/>
had a stock of restrikes on hand in 1893, one of which is at the Massachusetts Historical Society. <lb/>
Electrotype reprints could have been made during the nineteenth century—but probably not <lb/>
until 1894 or 1895, when the United States Coast and Geodetic Survey produced electrotype <lb/>
plates for that purpose. For more on the Stone facsimile and its restrikes, see Leonard Rapport, <lb/>
“Fakes and Facsimiles: Problems of Identification,” <hi rend="italic">American Archivist</hi> 42 (1979), 23–26; Cath-<lb/>
erine Nicholson, “Finding the Stones: National Archives Discovers Several Engravings of the <lb/>
Declaration,” <hi rend="italic">Prologue Magazine</hi> 44 (Summer 2012), https://www.archives.gov/publications/ <lb/>
prologue/2012/summer/stone.html (accessed 20 March 2023). Full-size reproductions were <lb/>
priced at thirty cents and forty-five cents in the <hi rend="italic">Catalog of U.S. Government Publications</hi> during <lb/>
the 1950s. At the other end of the scale, a copy of the original limited edition Stone facsimile <lb/>
recently sold for $4,420,000 (Freeman’s, Philadelphia, 1 July 2021, lot 1), a record-breaking <lb/>
price due to the provenance of that copy, formerly owned by the Signer Charles Carroll.<lb/></note>
<pb n="114"/>
reproduced the Tyler print in its entirety above an advertisement for cigarettes <lb/>
ca. 1887–1890.<hi rend="sup">7</hi><lb/>
Beginning in the 1830s Boston publishers experimented with combinations <lb/>
of the Binns border and the Tyler text. The earliest attempt to my knowledge is <lb/>
a letterpress broadside produced by the Boston Bewick Company around 1834–<lb/>
1836. A compositor copied Tyler’s title inasmuch as the first words <lb/>
In Congress, July 4, 1776 are set in a curve at the top of the print. The facsimile signatures <lb/>
are part of that family as well as the text, which is printed in a script type inter­<lb/>
spersed with ornamental types imitating the “emphatical words.” The display <lb/>
faces include black letter, a bold Antique, and two sizes of open shaded caps. The <lb/>
state seals are in the style of the Binns print and its derivatives, although they are <lb/>
shaped like a rectangular frame rather than an oval border. But here too the seals <lb/>
provide a symbolic entourage for the text, each occupying a compartment inside <lb/>
intertwining oak-leaf and olive garlands with the national seal at the center. It <lb/>
easily outdoes other letterpress broadsides in design and execution but it was <lb/>
intended to be cheap. One version was priced 12½ cents in the imprint. Another <lb/>
version was published by Prentiss Whitney, a Boston auctioneer who had a small <lb/>
printmaking business on the side. The Bewick firm had it stereotyped, no doubt <lb/>
as a steady selling product but also as a giveaway specimen of its fancy job print­<lb/>
ing and stereotyping services. The New York print dealers Phelps &amp; Squire ob­<lb/>
tained a stereotype copy of the state seals frame, replaced the national seal with <lb/>
a portrait of Washington, and reset the text in the same style for an adaptation <lb/>
issued around 1835–1837. Phelps in another partnership, Phelps &amp; Ensign, used <lb/>
a stereotype plate of the entire print to replenish his stock of Declarations around <lb/>
1838–1842. Stationers’ Hall, an office supplies store in Boston, published a letter­<lb/>
press imitation with the same script type, a similar title design, and a rudimentary <lb/>
border of state seals jumbled together with portraits, ornaments, and recycled <lb/>
illustrations on patriotic themes. No doubt other reprints and imitations have yet <lb/>
to be identified. Boston Bewick’s intermarriage of two Declaration families must <lb/>
have had numerous offspring through the stereotyping endeavors of the firm.<hi rend="sup">8</hi><lb/>
<note place="foot">
7. These figures are based on a checklist in <hi rend="italic">The Declaration in Script and Print: A Visual <lb/>
History of America’s Founding Document</hi> (2024), published while this essay was in its final stages of <lb/>
editing and revision. The checklist describes nearly two hundred prints and broadsides pub­<lb/>
lished between 1816 and 1900. I made an initial attempt to account for the nineteenth-century <lb/>
facsimiles in “American History in Image and Text,” <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the American Antiquarian <lb/>
Society</hi> 98 (1988), 247–302. At that time I was able to describe forty-eight typical examples, not <lb/>
just the facsimiles but also broadside editions of the Declaration. So far the only instance of the <lb/>
Stone signatures I have found before the Centennial period, besides the restrikes mentioned <lb/>
above, is an anastatic transfer print published in 1846. Copies are in the Library of Congress, <lb/>
the Boston Athenaeum, and the Independence National Historical Park.<lb/>
</note>
<note place="foot">
8. A consortium of artists founded the Boston Bewick firm in March 1834 by an act of <lb/>
incorporation allowing them to hold assets amounting to $120,000. Underinsured, they failed <lb/>
to recover from a fire in September 1835 and withdrew in favor of the senior partner Abel <lb/>
Bowen, who continued to practice “Fancy Job Printing” at the same address (William Henry <lb/>
Whitmore, “Abel Bowen,” <hi rend="italic">Bostonian Society Publications</hi> 1 [1886–1888]: 44; <hi rend="italic">Boston Daily Advertiser <lb/>
and Patriot</hi>, 25 September 1835, 2; [Boston] <hi rend="italic">Columbian Centinel</hi>, 20 April 1836, 3). The Boston <lb/>
Bewick Company and Phelps &amp; Squire prints are described in the <hi rend="italic">PAAS</hi> article, items 13 and 14, <lb/>
and in <hi rend="italic">The Declaration in Script and Print</hi>, items 33 and 36. A copy of the Stationers’ Hall print <lb/>
is at the American Antiquarian Society. A copy of the Phelps &amp; Ensign print is in the Daniel <lb/>
Hamelberg collection.<lb/>
</note>
<pb n="115"/>
<p>
<lb/>Lewis H.&amp;nbsp;Bridgham&amp;nbsp;(1808–1883) oversaw the moulding and casting opera-<lb/>tions&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;Boston&amp;nbsp;Bewick’s stereotype foundry.&amp;nbsp;He had a long career in job print-<lb/>ing,&amp;nbsp;beginning&amp;nbsp;around&amp;nbsp;1828 in&amp;nbsp;Providence,&amp;nbsp;RI.&amp;nbsp;He first appears in Boston city<lb/>directories&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;1835 identified as a stereotype founder and then drops out of sight<lb/>after the company closed down in&amp;nbsp;1836.&amp;nbsp;He reappears in the&amp;nbsp;1840s as a printer,<lb/>for a while successful enough to obtain a steam power press and exercise the right<lb/>to display his name in Boston imprints.&amp;nbsp;In the&amp;nbsp;1850s he moved to Brooklyn and<lb/>made his living as a reporter in the office of the Associated&amp;nbsp;Press.&amp;nbsp;After just over<lb/>ten years in journalism,&amp;nbsp;he resumed the printing business,&amp;nbsp;taking on small jobs<lb/>at various New&amp;nbsp;York addresses until he died in&amp;nbsp;1883.&amp;nbsp;An obituary indicates that<lb/>he had been more than a mere journeyman and was “well-known” for his print-<lb/>ing work in Boston.&amp;nbsp;He was prominent enough to have taken out the copyright<lb/>for one of Boston Bewick’s stereotype ventures.&amp;nbsp;Among other achievements he<lb/>published an engraved miniature facsimile of the Declaration very popular in<lb/>its day.&amp;nbsp;It reached a wide public in Boston and New&amp;nbsp;York—and may have even<lb/>gone as far as England.&amp;nbsp;I believe it to be the source of the Sussex Declaration.<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
</p>
<head>III</head>
<p>
<lb/>Dated&amp;nbsp;1836,&amp;nbsp;the copyright statement in Bridgham’s facsimile contains his name,<lb/>but otherwise it is difficult to determine what role he took in its design and pro-<lb/>duction.&amp;nbsp;Perhaps he had the idea to make a miniature facsimile,&amp;nbsp;a tour&amp;nbsp;de&amp;nbsp;force<lb/>of lettering and engraving printed on coated paper,&amp;nbsp;all the better to display the<lb/>precision craftsmanship of the artists he employed.&amp;nbsp;He probably knew about pre-<lb/>vious attempts to sell Declaration novelties in unusual formats such as prints on<lb/>silk or satin and,&amp;nbsp;most notably,&amp;nbsp;a commemorative handkerchief priced at a dollar<lb/>in&amp;nbsp;1826.&amp;nbsp;Other types of pocket curiosities had already found a ready market in<lb/>America—portrait miniatures,&amp;nbsp;miniature silver toys,&amp;nbsp;and thumb&amp;nbsp;Bibles,&amp;nbsp;just to<lb/>mention a few examples.&amp;nbsp;By catering to this fashion,&amp;nbsp;he started a trend soon to<lb/>be taken to an extreme by the Philadelphia bank-note engraver Charles&amp;nbsp;Toppan,<lb/>who downsized the Declaration to fit inside a 2 by 3 inch card on coated stock,<lb/>a promotional keepsake first issued in&amp;nbsp;1840.<hi rend="sup">10</hi>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>9.&amp;nbsp;[Providence] Rhode-Island American (20 June 1828), 4;&amp;nbsp;American&amp;nbsp;Magazine&amp;nbsp;of&amp;nbsp;Useful&amp;nbsp;and En-<lb/>tertaining Knowledge 1,&amp;nbsp;no.&amp;nbsp;4 (December 1834), advertisements;&amp;nbsp;[Boston] Daily Evening Transcript<lb/>(29 July 1847), 2;&amp;nbsp;Richard A.&amp;nbsp;Schwarzlose,&amp;nbsp;The Nation’s Newsbrokers,&amp;nbsp;Volume 1:&amp;nbsp;The Formative Years,<lb/>from Pretelegraph to 1865 (1989), p.&amp;nbsp;178;&amp;nbsp;New-York Tribune (30 October 1883), 2.&amp;nbsp;Perhaps acting on<lb/>his own account,&amp;nbsp;Bridgham obtained the copyright for Worship God and Keep His Commandments<lb/>(1835), an illustrated broadside “stereotyped and printed by the Boston Bewick Company.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>10.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">In Congress, July 4th.&amp;nbsp;1776.&amp;nbsp;The Unanimous Declaration of the Thirteen United States of<lb/>America</hi>, Boston:&amp;nbsp;L.&amp;nbsp;H.&amp;nbsp;Bridgham,&amp;nbsp;1836.&amp;nbsp;Copies in this state are common and can be found<lb/>in the American Antiquarian Society,&amp;nbsp;the New York Public Library,&amp;nbsp;the Library Company of<lb/>Philadelphia,&amp;nbsp;and other libraries.&amp;nbsp;They frequently come up for sale at modest prices,&amp;nbsp;viz.&amp;nbsp;Swann<lb/>Auction Galleries sales 21 June 2016,&amp;nbsp;lot 132 ($344), and 26 September 2019,&amp;nbsp;lot 94 ($219).&amp;nbsp;The<lb/>commemorative handkerchief was advertised in the Georgetown Gazette (14 July 1826), 1;&amp;nbsp;copies<lb/>are described in Herbert Ridgeway Collins,&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Threads of History: Americana Recorded on Cloth 1775<lb/>to the Present</hi> (1979), nos.&amp;nbsp;23 and 58.&amp;nbsp;For the fame of the Toppan facsimile,&amp;nbsp;“the Smallest Engrav-<lb/>ing in the world,” see Cincinnati Daily Gazette (21 September 1871), 4; (23 September 1871), 1.
</p>
<pb n="116"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">B</hi>ridgham’s design is almost entirely based on the Boston Bewick Company <lb/>facsimile. The most obvious borrowings can be seen in the facsimile signatures, <lb/>the state seals in an oak-leaf and olive-wreath border, the curvature of the title, <lb/>and the “emphatical words” in the text. Some adjustments had to be made to <lb/>extrapolate these design elements from a large letterpress broadside, and there <lb/>was one change in iconography—a portrait of Washington was substituted for <lb/>the national seal—but Bridgham was clearly indebted to his former employer <lb/>for the concept and layout of his facsimile. Surely it is no coincidence that he <lb/>published it just after he left that firm. Intaglio was not his medium, but he would <lb/>have learned about it while on the job and would have understood its potential <lb/>for delineating fine detail in miniatures. His model, the letterpress broadside, he <lb/>would have known from hands-on experience in the stereotype foundry or the <lb/>pressroom. The Boston Bewick Company gave him the means and the motiva-<lb/>tion to take on this project at a turning point in his career.</p>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he timing of his publication could not have been better. In 1837 a Boston <lb/>gallery presented a life-size tableau of mannequins reenacting the ratification <lb/>of the Declaration, each of the fifty-six Signers dressed in period costume. A <lb/>broadside advertisement assured the public that it was not a painting, although <lb/>the scene seems to have been based on Trumbull’s <hi rend="italic">Declaration of Independence</hi>. The <lb/>Committee of Five takes center stage, Franklin to the left of Jefferson, Adams to <lb/>his right, Livingston and Sherman behind them, while Jefferson submits the com-<lb/>mittee’s text to the president of Congress. This inspiring spectacle could be seen <lb/>for twenty-five cents, children half price, from eight in the morning until ten at <lb/>night. If anyone wanted to take away a souvenir, the Bridgham facsimile would <lb/>have been easily available at that time and just the right size for that purpose. <lb/>Indeed it was reprinted in 1839 with the border reworked yet again to change the <lb/>title and replace the Washington portrait with Trumbull’s <hi rend="italic">Declaration</hi>.<hi rend="sup">11</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he text portion of Bridgham’s print determined the lettering in another <lb/>Boston edition, which also incorporated Trumbull’s <hi rend="italic">Declaration</hi>. Published by <lb/>the Franklin Print Company in 1838, this one was more than twice the size of <lb/>the miniature, with a more elaborate oak-leaf border containing twenty-six state <lb/>seals, the national seal, and portraits of the presidents. It contains a competent <lb/>reproduction of the Asher B. Durand print after Trumbull’s first version of the <lb/>painting (to be precise, the painting now in the Yale University Art Gallery, not <lb/>the second version in the Capitol Rotunda or the third version in the Wadsworth <lb/>Atheneum) as well as a key to the print consisting of forty-eight numbered outline <lb/>figures. Numbered facsimile signatures identify each of the figures. The Franklin <lb/>Print Company credited the pictorial part to the engraver Denison Kimberly, <lb/>the lettering to John&amp;nbsp;B. Bolton. Although reformatted for different proportions, <lb/></p>
<note place="foot">
11. The Great National Exhibition of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence, Boston: W.&amp;nbsp;W. <lb/>Clapp, 1837; <hi rend="italic">In the Continental Congress, of 1776, on the 4th.&amp;nbsp;of July, The Unanimous Declaration of <lb/>the Thirteen United States of America</hi>, Boston: Published by N. Dearborn &amp; Son—53 Washington <lb/>St. Boston, &amp; 164 Broad Way, New&amp;nbsp;York, 1839. As yet the only copy I have found in this state <lb/>is at the New-York Historical Society, although the Library Company of Philadelphia has an <lb/>undated variant with the imprint: Published by N. Dearborn. No. 53 Washington St. Boston. <lb/>
</note>
<pb n="117"/>
<p>the lettering is close in style to that of the Bridgham miniature and imitates<lb/>
almost all of the “emphatical words” in size and shape. Conceivably Bolton<lb/>
wrote the text for Bridgham, but he does not appear in Boston city directories<lb/>
until 1838, and I have not found other examples of his calligraphic writing that<lb/>
might confirm this supposition. By trade, however, he was an engraver, perhaps<lb/>
a specialist in script. He arrived in Boston in 1831 age twenty after emigrating<lb/>
from Halifax, Nova Scotia, and started to make his living from engraving in 1836,<lb/>
when Bridgham’s print was published. Whatever his connection with Bridgham<lb/>
and the Franklin firm, both prints were successful, and both were reworked for<lb/>
reprint editions. The latter reappeared with additional illustrations and furnished<lb/>
Declaration lettering reduced to Bridgham dimensions in maps with patriotic<lb/>
motifs published by the New York print dealers who had reprinted the Boston<lb/>
Bewick facsimile.<hi rend="sup">12</hi></p>
<p>Broadening his horizons, Bridgham may have brought copies of the miniature to<lb/>
England. My sole evidence for this conjecture is a passenger list of the <hi rend="italic">Great<lb/>
Western</hi> steamship arriving in New York from Bristol in August 1838. His<lb/>
name is on the list along with merchants, men of the cloth, New York notables,<lb/>
wives, children, and servants. What business he might have had in England is<lb/>
impossible to ascertain, but he managed to travel in style on a recently launched<lb/>
Atlantic liner renowned for its size and speed. Perhaps his trip had something<lb/>
to do with a change in career during the late 1830s when he dropped out of the<lb/>
Boston directories. While exploring opportunities abroad, he could use his miniature<lb/>
as a means of self-promotion, a calling card that could be carried about in<lb/>
quantity and presented as an example of American achievements in the graphic<lb/>
arts. With that in mind, Binns had already sent copies of his print to friends and<lb/>
customers in England, where it made “a highly favorable impression.”<hi rend="sup">13</hi></p>
<head>IV</head>
<p>Someone was sufficiently impressed by the Bridgham print to try to copy it on<lb/>
parchment. I will call that person a copyist rather than a clerk, for I doubt that a<lb/>
professional could have been responsible for the layout and script of the Sussex<lb/>
Declaration. I have already mentioned the amateurish mistakes the copyist made<lb/>
in the transcription of the title. The text has none of the elegant modulation and<lb/>
</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">12.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Declaration of Independence, with Fac-similies of the Signatures and Likenesses of the<lb/>
Signers; the Arms of the States and of the United States, and Portraits of the Presidents</hi>, Boston:<lb/>
Published by the Franklin Print Compy., 46 Court Street, 1838. A copy in this state is reproduced<lb/>
as fig. 5 in the <hi rend="smallcaps">PAAS</hi> article. Six later editions and adaptations are described in <hi rend="italic">The Declaration<lb/>
in Script and Print</hi>, item 38, including the maps with the repurposed lettering: <hi rend="italic">Phelps &amp; Ensign’s<lb/>
Travellers’ Guide, and Map of the United States</hi> (1840) and <hi rend="italic">Ensign’s Travellers’ Guide, and Map of<lb/>
the United States</hi> (1845). Bolton noted his immigration status when he applied for citizenship,<lb/>
4 September 1847, Circuit Court, Massachusetts, Naturalization Records, 1845 – 1850 (Ancestry.com). <hi rend="italic">Leading<lb/>
Manufacturers and Merchants of the City of Boston</hi> (1885), p. 316, contains a short account of his career<lb/>
commending his “artistic elegance and originality of design.”</p>
<p><hi rend="sup">13.</hi> Binns, <hi rend="italic">Recollections</hi>, p. 236. The passenger list is printed in the <hi rend="italic">Evening Post</hi><lb/>
(6 August 1838), 2.</p>
<pb n="118"/>
<p>sober grace one would expect to see in a specimen of eighteenth-century running<lb/>
round hand. In the following, I will consider other aspects of his or her work, all<lb/>
of which must have come from Boston rather than the other way around. These<lb/>
remarks are not intended to be a point-by-point refutation of the <hi rend="smallcaps">PBSA</hi> article,<lb/>
but they counter the main arguments and provide a more convincing sequence<lb/>
of cause and effect.<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Emphatical Words.</hi> The copyist wrote out in a larger script sixty-eight<lb/>
words of special significance, beginning, for example, with “Nature” and<lb/>
“Nature’s<lb/>
God” and ending with “Lives,” “Fortunes,” and “Honor.” Allen and Sneff notice<lb/>
that forty-four of those words correspond to Tyler’s “emphatical words,” a 65 %<lb/>
correlation, a reason why they consider the Sussex manuscript to be a source<lb/>
for the facsimile. In a footnote they observe an almost one-to-one correspon-<lb/>
dence of “emphatical words” between the manuscript and the Bridgham print,<lb/>
a correlation I calculate at nearly 90 %. Surely that is a more revealing statistic<lb/>
and demands an explanation, but they draw no conclusions in the footnote and<lb/>
concentrate on Tyler instead. They trace the fashion for the “emphatical words”<lb/>
back to the original 1776 engrossed Declaration, which capitalizes most of the<lb/>
substantives as a matter of course and sometimes switches from round hand to<lb/>
black letter for extra effect in the last paragraph. One could go back one step fur-<lb/>
ther and say that the black letter was a stylistic decision on the part of the scribe,<lb/>
Timothy Matlack, who sought to transpose in script some of the letterspaced caps<lb/>
and small caps he encountered in his source document, the Dunlap broadside.<lb/></p>
<p>In any case Allen and Sneff assume that the ornamental scripts in Tyler’s<lb/>
print were beyond his powers. They surmise that he must have consulted their<lb/>
manuscript or a now lost descendant of their manuscript while deciding which<lb/>
words to emphasize. They call him an engraver although he styles himself Profes-<lb/>
sor of Penmanship in the imprint, which states explicitly that the engraving had<lb/>
been done by Peter Maverick. This division of labor helps to explain the advertis-<lb/>
ing function of Tyler’s <hi rend="italic">Declaration</hi>. He intended it to be a specimen of calligraphic<lb/>
skill, not just the utilitarian running hand he taught his students but also the<lb/>
decorative lettering he proffered as his professional credentials. American writing<lb/>
masters drummed up business by publishing engraved copybooks with title pages<lb/>
couched in a multitude of plain and fancy scripts. In 1815, while teaching in New<lb/>
York, Tyler promoted his system of instruction in a patriotic print also engraved<lb/>
by Maverick, <hi rend="italic">Eulogium Sacred to the Memory of the Illustrious George Washington.</hi> The<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Eulogium</hi> changes tone and tempo with calligraphic enhancements in selected<lb/>
passages of the text as well as embellished black letter in the title. He perfected<lb/>
that approach three years later when he produced his <hi rend="italic">Declaration</hi>, fully capable<lb/>
of choosing the “emphatical words” on his own.<hi rend="sup">14</hi><lb/></p>
<p>This style of decorating the Declaration caught on immediately and remained<lb/>
in fashion throughout the nineteenth century. We have seen the succession of<lb/>
Boston editions, a step-by-step transmission of “emphatical words” from Tyler<lb/>
to Bridgham. If we are to accept that Tyler referred to the Sussex Declaration or<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="sup">14.</hi> Ray Nash, <hi rend="italic">American Penmanship, 1800–1850: A History of Writing and a Bibliography of<lb/>
Copybooks from Jenkins to Spencer</hi> (1969), nos. 83–88.<lb/></p>
<pb n="119"/>
<p>a lost descendant when writing out his “emphatical words,” a 65% correlation,<lb/>
how are we to explain the 90% correlation in the Bridgham print? Bridgham’s<lb/>
artist would have had to be even more dependent on the Sussex Declaration,<lb/>
which would have somehow re-emerged in Boston eighteen years after coming<lb/>
into the hands of Tyler. Here again we should seek an easier explanation: the<lb/>
Bridgham print is the source of the Sussex Declaration. The copyist acknowl-<lb/>
edged its rhetorical effects by writing out in a larger script almost every one of<lb/>
its distinctive words.<lb/></p>
<head>Textual variants.<lb/></head>
<p>Allen and Sneff relegate to a footnote a discussion of tex-<lb/>
tual variants that appear only in the Bridgham print and the Sussex Declaration<lb/>
(PBSA, p. 398). In fact, the same readings also occur in the Franklin Print<lb/>
Company facsimile, the last in the succession of Boston editions. They are all ordinary er-<lb/>
rors although the spelling “paralelled” in the phrase “scarcely paralleled in the<lb/>
most barbarous ages” might be justified by precedents in that period. Binns and<lb/>
Tyler adopt a primarily British usage in the spelling “connexion,” which they<lb/>
employ in the phrases “interrupt our connections” and “all political connection.”<lb/>
This variant, not mentioned by Allen and Sneff, occurs in all of the Boston edi-<lb/>
tions but not in the Sussex Declaration. That could be an argument in favor of<lb/>
a direct relationship with the engrossed Declaration, although one could just as<lb/>
easily surmise that the copyist opted for the “connection” spelling, which was also<lb/>
prevalent in England in the 1830s. Perhaps more to the point, the variant spell-<lb/>
ing “paralelled” in the Sussex Declaration becomes significant because it did not<lb/>
originate in the Tyler facsimile but in the Bridgham facsimile. Bridgham’s artist<lb/>
had to cope with the spelling “parallelled” in the Boston Bewick edition, an obvi-<lb/>
ous mistake, but guessed wrong when he tried to fix it. The Sussex copyist did not<lb/>
have any better ideas.<lb/></p>
<head>The sequence of signatures.<lb/></head>
<p>For Allen and Sneff, the signatures are the<lb/>
most important part of the Sussex Declaration. They perceive a pattern in the<lb/>
signatures, a “hidden ordering principle” devised by the copyist in accordance<lb/>
with James Wilson’s aspirations for a strong federal government (PBSA, p. 386).<lb/>
That pattern breaks a precedent they detect in other government documents and<lb/>
other Declarations, beginning with the engrossed parchment. There the signa-<lb/>
tures are grouped by states (excepting that of Matthew Thornton, who signed it<lb/>
at a later date when there was no more room to put it in the proper place). The<lb/>
state groupings are even more explicit in the “authenticated Copy” printed by<lb/>
order of Congress in 1777 and some of the letterpress broadsides issued in the era<lb/>
of Binns and Tyler. By changing the order of the signatures, they say, the Sussex<lb/>
Declaration downgrades the prominence of the states and asserts the supreme<lb/>
power of the central government prescribed by the Constitution. Wilson’s role in<lb/>
framing the Constitution provides additional evidence for dating the manuscript.<lb/>
If that date is valid, and if Wilson was involved, the Sussex Declaration would be<lb/>
a bridge between the two great founding documents of the United States and a<lb/>
means of explicating the political precepts behind them.<lb/></p>
<p>The “hidden ordering principle” is based on a cipher system used in en-<lb/>
crypted correspondence during the Revolutionary War. Allen and Sneff con-<lb/>
sulted with a codebreaking expert who confirmed that a system can be discerned<lb/>
in the sequence of signatures. I will not try to describe it in detail except to say<lb/></p>
<pb n="120"/>
<p>that the copyist chose names from different columns in the engrossed Declara-<lb/>
tion, first concentrating on one column, then another, while interspersing the <lb/>
names of the Georgia, Pennsylvania, and Delaware delegates to make it harder <lb/>
to crack the code. Nowhere do they explain why the code was predicated on <lb/>
columns rather than some other ordering principle, an alphabetical system for <lb/>
example, or a geographical progression from state to state, which might at least <lb/>
have some regional significance. Nowhere do they define the purpose of the code <lb/>
unless it was a means of randomizing the names while ensuring that none of them <lb/>
would be omitted. One would expect a code to contain a confidential message in <lb/>
danger of falling into the wrong hands, but it is unclear what needed to be kept <lb/>
secret on this occasion. The names were not protecting classified information. <lb/>
Instead of making complications, it is better to look for precedents and similar <lb/>
examples, a simple comparison of layout techniques and production methods. <lb/>
An easier explanation can be found in the field of graphic design, a basic skill of <lb/>
the artists who copied the Declaration.</p>
<p>Design considerations often dictated the sequence of signatures. Allen and <lb/>
Sneff are not correct in saying that the Sussex Declaration was the only one to <lb/>
interfere with the state groupings before the publication of the Bridgham print in <lb/>
1836. The printers of the Boston Bewick facsimile rearranged the states to save <lb/>
on space and make room for the oak and olive frame. A Philadelphia printer <lb/>
moved the signatures out of order in an 1832 broadside reconfigured in a three-<lb/>
column format. After 1836 the signatures frequently appear in random order for <lb/>
no other reason than to fill an area predetermined by the decorative apparatus <lb/>
and the proportions of the page. Just to take one example, an 1845 letterpress <lb/>
broadside starts out with the state groupings but then switches out the signatures <lb/>
to rank them in a five-column format within a border of state seals. The printers <lb/>
disbanded the Maryland delegation and put each of the signatures in a different <lb/>
column.<hi rend="sup">15</hi></p>
<p>Like others who made those design decisions, Bridgham’s artist sought to <lb/>
achieve a harmonious balance between image and text, a pleasing composition <lb/>
comprising the border of state seals, the calligraphic lettering, and the facsimile <lb/>
signatures. The lettering above and the signatures below were aligned to form <lb/>
two rectangular blocks, each even in weight, each fitting neatly inside the bor-<lb/>
der. The artist allowed a tendril to extend beyond the border to complete the <lb/>
last line of text, a grace note following the phrase “our <hi rend="smallcaps">LIVES</hi>, our <hi rend="smallcaps">FORTUNES</hi>, <lb/>
and our sacred <hi rend="smallcaps">HONOR</hi>.” Likewise, the signatures were spaced out to make the <lb/>
line endings flush with the text, even though the emblematic John Hancock had <lb/>
to be compressed, and some signatures lost their final flourishes. Signatures at <lb/>
the beginning and the end of the last line retained their flourishes for a decora-<lb/>
</p>
<note n="15" place="foot">Declaration of Independence, and Geographical Chart of the U.&amp;nbsp;States of America, <lb/>
Philadelphia: Published by Thomas Morrison, C.&amp;nbsp;A.&amp;nbsp;Elliott, printer, 1832; <hi rend="italic">In Congress July&amp;nbsp;4th. 1776. The <lb/>
Unanimous Declaration of the Thirteen United States of America</hi>, New&amp;nbsp;York: Published and for sale <lb/>
by Humphrey Phelps, No.&amp;nbsp;4 Spruce-St., opposite City Hall, N.&amp;nbsp;York, 1845. Copies of the Mor-<lb/>
rison broadside are in the Library of Congress, the American Philosophical Society, the Daniel <lb/>
Hamelberg collection, and the Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University <lb/>
of Virginia. Nine different versions of the Phelps broadside dating from 1845 to ca.&amp;nbsp;1854–1863 <lb/>
are described in <hi rend="italic">The Declaration in Script and Print</hi>, item&amp;nbsp;47.</note>
<pb n="121"/>
&lt;tive purpose, both looping down to fill hollow portions of the border. The state<lb/>
 groupings would have had no meaning in this graphic concept and would have<lb/>
 prevented the artist from placing the signatures in an even array, although ves-<lb/>
 tiges can be detected in sequences of Maryland, North Carolina, and New Jersey<lb/>
 delegates. Symmetry was the top priority of the artist. By a simple computation,<lb/>
 he found a way to accommodate the fifty-six signatures in a graphic construct<lb/>
 composed of six columns and nine rows with the exception of the first and last<lb/>
 columns, which have ten signatures instead of nine.<lb/>
 Allen and Sneff argue against the priority of the Bridgham print on the grounds<lb/>
 that the Sussex copyist could not have replicated its sequence of signatures. They<lb/>
 believe that he would have had to backtrack between columns if he started the<lb/>
 transcription process by reading across the rows. Diagrams in the <hi rend="italic">PBSA</hi> article<lb/>
 (pp. 401 and 402) intimate that he would have been confused by the extra names<lb/>
 in the first and last columns and could not have dealt with them to arrive at the<lb/>
 sequence in the Sussex Declaration. The transcription process does not seem all<lb/>
 that difficult to me. The copyist proceeded through the six rows of names, one<lb/>
 name after another left to right, allowing the first and last columns to be slightly<lb/>
 staggered. He then inserted the two extra names, Roger Sherman and Elbridge<lb/>
 Gerry, to restore the alignment between the inner and outer columns. Then he<lb/>
 resumed the regular progression from left to right in the last three lines.<lb/>
 Turning that argument around, I question why Bridgham’s artist would have<lb/>
 replicated the sequence in the Sussex Declaration. Why would he use it as a start-<lb/>
 ing point and then go off and consult some other source to turn those round hand<lb/>
 names into facsimile signatures? In the manuscript, the names occupy six rows<lb/>
 and then spill over to a seventh row containing a name and a half. What value<lb/>
 would he have seen in that haphazard arrangement? He would have been much<lb/>
 more interested in creating his own sequence to make a block of signatures in<lb/>
 pleasing proportions. Let’s say he knew about the hidden ordering principle and<lb/>
 wished to preserve it. But why would he be privy to the secret rather than anyone<lb/>
 else in the Declaration business? There are too many loose ends and coincidences<lb/>
 in this scenario. It is much more likely that he began with the Boston Bewick let-<lb/>
 terpress broadside, an easily adaptable model for the layout and decoration. He<lb/>
 then reconceived it as an engraved miniature and decided on a symmetrical com-<lb/>
 position in accordance with the aesthetic of that genre. To achieve the “neatness”<lb/>
 highly prized in that period, he changed the order of the signatures to fit them<lb/>
 in a rectangular block, nine rows deep, six columns across. Neatness, uniformity<lb/>
 and symmetry were his goals and the real reasons for rearranging the signatures.<lb/>
 Misspelled signatures. Allen and Sneff note that the copyist misspelled<lb/>
 some of the signatures. They cite eight problematic names, three of which might<lb/>
 be excused as alternatives: Pinn for Penn, Rutlidge for Rutledge, Hayward for<lb/>
 Heyward. A ninth could be added to their list, a garbled superscript in the signa-<lb/>
 ture of Samuel Huntington: Sam<sup>u</sup>. for Sam<sup>el</sup>. More egregious errors occur in four<lb/>
 names: Floys for Floyd, Harnson for Harrison, Witherspoare for Witherspoon,<lb/>
 and M. Keap for M: Kean. The <hi rend="italic">PBSA</hi> article includes a series of thumbnail il-<lb/>
 lustrations juxtaposing the Sussex Declaration versions with the signatures in<lb/>
 the Stone facsimile, the best record of the originals in the engrossed Declara-<lb/>
 tion. It is true that some of the originals are barely legible and that ignorant<lb/>
<pb n="122"/>
<p>compositors got them wrong in books and broadsides even in the eighteenth <lb/>
century. Otherwise Allen and Sneff do not dwell on the Sussex misspellings and <lb/>
do not try to explain them except to observe that they are more likely to stem <lb/>
from manuscripts than printed matter.<lb/>
The facsimile signatures in Bridgham’s miniature Declaration were respon-<lb/>
sible for the spelling mistakes in the Sussex Declaration. The signatures were <lb/>
already corrupted in transmission when Bridgham’s artist copied them from the <lb/>
Boston Bewick broadside but were distorted even more when he cut them down <lb/>
to fit in his rectangular composition (figure 3). Tyler can be blamed for a cal-<lb/>
ligraphic lilt he gave to the d in Floyd, which was nudged downward in his print <lb/>
and tilted even more in the miniature. The copyist read it as an s followed by <lb/>
a flourish. Samuel Huntington customarily abbreviated his first name as Sam<hi rend="sup">el</hi>. <lb/>
with a flourished superscript, sometimes writing two identifiable letters but more <lb/>
often just a double loop. The Boston Bewick Company’s facsimilist closed the <lb/>
double loop or allowed it to be closed while making the transition from intaglio <lb/>
to letterpress. Bridgham’s artist read the altered superscript as a u instead of <lb/>
el, a good guess but wrong nonetheless as can be seen in other examples of that signa-<lb/>
ture before and after 1776. As far as the copyist was concerned, the superscript u <lb/>
was a legitimate abbreviation, an easy choice to make in comparison to the less <lb/>
legible names. The n in McKean, for example, was gradually twisted out of shape <lb/>
in the prints of Tyler, the Boston Bewick Company, and Bridgham, whose artist <lb/>
compressed and elongated it in such a way that the copyist opted for a p in the <lb/>
Sussex Declaration. Copying the c in Stockton, Bridgham’s artist made a slip of <lb/>
the pen interpreted by the copyist as a cursive r, that too a plausible assumption <lb/>
although Storkton is not a common name. The name Witherspoare is unknown <lb/>
to genealogists and that mistranscription can only be explained by Tyler’s deci-<lb/>
sion to make an a out of the second o in the original and tidy up the final flourish, <lb/>
which was coarsened and then retrenched in the Boston facsimiles. I could cite <lb/>
other errors, mostly faults of the writing master and the miniaturists.<lb/></p>
<p>They were not the only ones to go astray in their attempts to transcribe <lb/>
the names. Printers of letterpress broadsides sometimes used facsimiles as their <lb/>
source documents with the best of intentions but with regrettable results. As <lb/>
one might expect, those farther removed from the original were more likely <lb/>
to make mistakes. A Philadelphia broadside published in 1855 repeats one of <lb/>
the names, misspells five of them, and gratuitously includes the Philadelphian <lb/>
Thomas Willing, who voted against the Declaration and did not sign the docu-<lb/>
ment. Lithographic artists encountered the same problems when they tried to <lb/>
make sense of the facsimile signatures. None of the Declarations I have seen to <lb/>
date is more delinquent in the spelling of the signatures than a lithographic map <lb/>
of New York City published ca. 1855 by Charles Magnus. A German immigrant, <lb/>
Magnus may not have been familiar with American proper names or with the <lb/>
English language, for he even had problems with the title, which commemorates <lb/>
the seventy-ninth year of “Indepedence.” The map is decorated with a view of <lb/>
City Hall, steamships in the harbor, and the Declaration in the usual border of <lb/>
state seals, the text in a uniform cursive, and the signatures in a “gothic” all caps <lb/>
sans serif script. Magnus or his artist used the Binns print or one of its derivatives <lb/>
as a model for the border and a source for the text, which contains the same <lb/></p>
<pb n="123"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 3.</head>
  <figDesc>Progressive degradation of signatures in Declaration facsimiles. The signatures are reproduced the same size as each other to show changes in letterforms.</figDesc>
  <!-- Image link to be added during image export workflow -->
</figure>
<pb n="124"/>
<lb/>words emphasized in special scripts. The Binns signatures, however, mystified<lb/>
<lb/>the lithographer who misspelled fourteen of the fifty-six names, mainly those that<lb/>
<lb/>were hard to read. The New York lithographer committed mistakes not unlike<lb/>
<lb/>those of the Sussex copyist: WITHERSPOART for Witherspoon, HOYG for<lb/>
<lb/>Floyd, PINN for Penn, and M KEAN for M: Kean. Both had to contend with<lb/>
<lb/>facsimile signatures, but even an immigrant poorly schooled in English was able<lb/>
<lb/>to construe common names such as Harrison and Stockton.<hi rend="sup">16</hi><lb/>
<lb/>The copyist’s mistakes are easier to explain if they can be imputed to the il-<lb/>
<lb/>legibility of his source and his failure to find a remedy. Some delegates scrawled<lb/>
<lb/>their signatures in such a way as to make them difficult to read even in a full-size<lb/>
<lb/>facsimile. Bridgham’s miniature exacerbated the problem. Published sixty years<lb/>
<lb/>after the fact, it was conceived as a novelty and was never intended to be an<lb/>
<lb/>authoritative text, but it circulated widely and could easily come into the hands<lb/>
<lb/>of someone whose notions of the American Revolution were more sentimental<lb/>
<lb/>than scholarly. The copyist transcribed it by rote and relied on his imagination<lb/>
<lb/>to interpret the parts he did not understand. He was unwilling or unable to find<lb/>
<lb/>a better source for this display of penmanship and did not worry overmuch about<lb/>
<lb/>the accuracy of his work.<lb/>
<head>Complications.</head><lb/>
<lb/>A line of reasoning should follow the shortest distance<lb/>
<lb/>between two points. That common-sense rule is a deciding factor for testing<lb/>
<lb/>hypotheses in bibliographical investigations—or any field of intellectual inquiry.<lb/>
<lb/>The complications in Allen and Sneff’s arguments undercut their claims for the<lb/>
<lb/>priority of the Sussex Declaration. If it came first and served as a source for<lb/>
<lb/>the Bridgham facsimile, we would have to believe that the Bostonians copied the<lb/>
<lb/>same order of names while consulting another source to render them in facsimile.<lb/>
<lb/>We would have to believe that they took the oversize words in that manuscript<lb/>
<lb/>as cues to execute the same words in ornamental penmanship even though they<lb/>
<lb/>had the Boston Bewick edition easily at hand and could use that as a model for<lb/>
<lb/>the “emphatical words.” We would have to accept the hypothesis that the Sussex<lb/>
<lb/>Declaration or a derivative manuscript influenced Tyler’s choice of “emphatical<lb/>
<lb/>words” sometime around 1818 and then resurfaced eighteen years later to guide<lb/>
<lb/>the work of the Bostonians. If we follow that line of reasoning, we would have to<lb/>
<lb/>imagine that James Wilson was willing to overlook the atrocious spelling of the<lb/>
<lb/>names even though he depended on them to affirm his position during the de-<lb/>
<lb/>bates on the Constitution and could have corrected them on the basis of personal<lb/>
<lb/>16. Declaration of Independence. In Congress, at Philadelphia, July 4th, 1776, Philadelphia:<lb/>
<lb/>Published by I. Kohler, No. 104 North Fourth Street, 1855; New-York City &amp; County Map with<lb/>
<lb/>Vicinity Entire Brooklyn Williamsburgh Jersey City &amp;c. in the 79th. Year of the Indepedence of the United<lb/>
<lb/>States, New-York: Published by Chs. Magnus, 12. Frankfurt Street, ca. 1855. A copy of the<lb/>
<lb/>Kohler broadside is at the American Antiquarian Society; copies of a German version with the<lb/>
<lb/>same mistakes are at the Library Company of Philadelphia and in the Daniel Hamelberg col-<lb/>
<lb/>lection. Magnus also issued the Declaration in a two-leaf brochure. A copy of the map is in the<lb/>
<lb/>Princeton University Library; copies of the brochure are at the American Antiquarian Society,<lb/>
<lb/>the Library Company of Philadelphia, and the Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections<lb/>
<lb/>Library, University of Virginia.
<pb n="125"/>
<lb/>acquaintance. A few loose ends may be permissible when plying disparate strands <lb/>of evidence, but these are too many to be believed.
<p>We do not have to work so hard if we allow the Bridgham miniature to be the <lb/>source of the Sussex Declaration. If we accept that hypothesis, we do not have <lb/>to explain away the damage in the title, the errors in the text, the absence of the <lb/>long s, and the profusion of misspelled names. We do not need a secret code to <lb/>understand the reordering of the signatures. We are not obliged to excuse the <lb/>poor quality of parchment, the marks of neglect, and the amateurish work of the <lb/>copyist if he was engaged in a penmanship exercise rather than a “ceremonial” <lb/>commission. We can even dispense with the provenance research if the manu-<lb/>script came to the West Sussex Record Office by way of a local history collector <lb/>who had only a tangential relationship with the Richmond family. At this point <lb/>we can only guess where the collector obtained it, but we could consider the <lb/>possibility that Bridgham brought copies of the miniature to England and that <lb/>one of them piqued the curiosity of the copyist. After the novelty wore off, the <lb/>parchment was folded up and filed away until it was retrieved by the collector. <lb/>Speculation along those lines may be tempting but is not necessary to vouch for <lb/>the priority of the miniature.</p>
<p>Allen and Sneff published their findings in a bibliographical journal and then <lb/>used that publication as the premise for their account of the Constitutional Con-<lb/>vention. They are political historians who want to get the dating questions out <lb/>of the way so they can do what they do best, a study of James Wilson’s political <lb/>philosophy. Allen is James Bryant Conant University Professor at Harvard Uni-<lb/>versity, director of the Allen Lab for Democracy Renovation, and author of Our <lb/>Declaration: A Reading of the Declaration of Independence in Defense of Equality (2014). <lb/>Sneff worked at the Declaration Resources Project before completing a doctor-<lb/>ate in American history with an emphasis on material culture and history of the <lb/>book. By no means are they the first to use bibliographical analysis as an avenue <lb/>for research in other fields, but this approach has obstacles and limitations that <lb/>can be overcome only by observing its rules and regulations. Every field has its <lb/>own methodology and this one is no exception: a rigorous routine is needed to <lb/>ensure the orderly analysis of texts produced in quantity.</p>
<p>Bibliographers have learned the hard way about the dangers of examining <lb/>documents in isolation. High spots deserve extra effort, but it is not enough to <lb/>focus on milestones of history, landmarks in philosophy, breakthroughs in sci-<lb/>ence, and canonical works of literature. The context is important too if only <lb/>as a gauge of value and a basis for comparison. In fact, Allen and Sneff do <lb/>have a bibliographical context for their work. Along with the documentation <lb/>about the Sussex manuscript, the Declaration Resources Project website offers <lb/>a pdf catalogue of Declaration editions and manuscripts listing 747 items from <lb/>1776 through 1826, plus an additional manuscript appended in June 2023. The <lb/>catalogue tracks the dissemination of this text in different formats—books, peri-<lb/>odicals, prints, and broadsides—a commendable attempt to be comprehensive. <lb/>It helps, for example, to explain the patriotic mindset of the printmaker John <lb/>Binns, who featured the text in his newspaper long before he produced the print.</p>
<pb n="126"/>
<p>
It is, however, an enumerative bibliography with minimal descriptions mainly<lb/>
based on secondary sources. It covers only the first fifty years of the Declara-<lb/>
tion, not long enough to account for the surge of patriotic publications in the<lb/>
nineteenth century.<hi rend="sup">17</hi><lb/>
</p>
<p>
If it had gone on for ten more years it would have brought Allen and Sneff<lb/>
up to the Bridgham miniature. But even then a brief listing of this kind would<lb/>
not show the facsimile’s relevance to their concerns or its relationship to the<lb/>
other Boston editions. Worthy in other ways, an enumerative bibliography is not<lb/>
intended to answer questions about form and content. It does not describe physi-<lb/>
cal objects with the details that might disclose the influence of one artifact on<lb/>
another, the information that might reveal resemblances in production methods,<lb/>
textual elements, and stylistic motifs. To make their claims for the Sussex Decla-<lb/>
ration, Allen and Sneff looked hard for this kind of information but only looked<lb/>
in one place and did not consider the commercial context. The manuscript they<lb/>
found deserves bibliographical scrutiny, but if I am correct about its sources, it<lb/>
has nothing to do with James Wilson and the Constitution. Rather, it should be<lb/>
dated at least fifty years later, when someone copied Bridgham’s engraving in an<lb/>
attempt to emulate the engrossed Declaration. If not an entirely successful effort,<lb/>
it is an interesting byproduct of the trade in patriotic prints and a good example<lb/>
of a text entangled in transcriptions large and small.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
17. Many of the catalogue entries are derived from Stephen M. Matyas, Jr.’s<lb/>
Declaration of<lb/>
Independence: A Checklist of Books, Pamphlets, and Periodicals Printing the U.S. Declaration of Indepen-<lb/>
dence, 1776–1825 (2009). The Matyas checklist has transcriptions of titles, collation statements,<lb/>
contents notes, and locations of copies examined but does not include prints and broadsides.<lb/>
A pdf version can be downloaded at http://usdeclarationofindependence.com (accessed 20<lb/>
March 2023).<lb/>
</p>
</div>