<div type="section" n="5">
  <head>The Engravings of Pope&rsquo;s Works II (1735): “Envy Must Own, I Live among the Great” by James McLaverty</head>
<pb n="187"/>
<head>THE ENGRAVINGS OF POPE’S WORKS II (1735):<lb/>
‘ENVY MUST OWN, I LIVE AMONG THE GREAT’</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">James McLaverty</name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">O</hi>n 24 April 1735, or perhaps a little earlier, Pope published the second volume of his Works.<note n="1">I am deeply grateful to David Vander Meulen for his corrections and advice, and for providing the illustrations for this essay from his own copies. A preliminary version of the essay was read for me by Dr Corrina Readioff at a session at the ISECS conference in Edinburgh in 2019. I am indebted to her for her generous assistance and for her report of the session’s discussion.</note> It contained: ‘Ethic Epistles to Henry St. John L. Bolingbroke’ (An Essay on Man), ‘Ethic Epistles, the Second Book. To Several Persons’, imitations of Horace and Donne, and the <hi>Dunciad Variorum</hi>.<note n="2">Reginald Harvey Griffith quotes the advertisement from the <hi>Grub-street Journal</hi> of 24 April 1735 in <hi>Alexander Pope: A Bibliography</hi>, 2 vols (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1922–7), 2:287–8. His accounts of the folio (370), large-paper folio (371), and quarto (372) are still valuable. Subsequent references are to Griffith and item number.</note> Like the first volume of Works, which had been published just after his twenty-ninth birthday, on 3 June 1717 (Griffith 79–86), the second volume was issued in the formats of his Homer translations – small folio, large folio, and quarto – and both the large folios and the quartos had illustrative headpieces, tailpieces, and initials. The engravings of 1717 have been subject to lively critical engagement, and the thematic importance of the illustrations, symbolizing and reflecting on the poems, has been recognized.<note n="3">For comments on the illustrations, see David Foxon, <hi>Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991), 44, 81–5; Vincent Carretta, ‘“Images Reflect from Art to Art”: Alexander Pope’s Collected Works of 1717’, in Neil Fraistat (ed.), <hi>Poems in Their Place: The Intertextuality and Order of Poetic Collections</hi> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1986), 195–233; and James McLaverty, <hi>Pope, Print, and Meaning</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2001), 61–6, 70–4. A recent valuable probing of the illustrations of <hi>The Rape of the Lock</hi> is by Allison Muri, ‘Of Words and Things: Image, Page, Text, and <hi>The Rape of the Lock</hi>’, in Donald W. Nichol (ed.), <hi>Anniversary Essays on Alexander Pope’s The Rape of the Lock</hi> (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2016), 167–217.</note> But the engravings in the second volume of Works have until recently been largely neglected. Close attention to them reveals that they were part of a considered, though hesitantly executed, plan to emphasize Pope’s</p>
<pb n="188"/>
<p>
place in a group that, though it was out of power, was politically and socially distinguished – an opposition aristocracy.<note n="4">The Dunciad illustrations in the Works are examined by Elias F. Mengel, Jr, ‘The Dunciad Illustrations’, Eighteenth-Century Studies, 7:2 (1973 – 4), 161–78, repr. in Maynard Mack and James A. Winn (eds.), Pope: Recent Essays by Several Hands (Brighton: Harvester Press, 1980), 749 –73, and by Nicholas Savage, ‘Kent as Book Illustrator’, in Susan Weber (ed.), William Kent: Designing Georgian Britain, (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2014), 413 – 47.</note><lb/>
The incomplete success of the plan for the Works II illustrations arose paradoxically from Pope’s gaining more direct control over the printing and publishing of his work.<lb/>
The 1717 volume, though closely supervised by Pope, was published by one of the trade’s most successful booksellers, Bernard Lintot, and printed by one of its most distinguished printers, William Bowyer.<lb/>
It everywhere shows signs of generous investment.<lb/>
In comparison the 1735 volume was something of a scramble.<lb/>
By the time Works II was published Pope was financing his own publications and working with the young bookseller Lawton Gilliver and the experienced but unspectacular printer John Wright.<note n="5">Foxon explains and reflects on these relationships in Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade, 102 – 44.</note><lb/>
As money-sparing as he was paper-sparing, Pope’s aim seems to have been to publish his poems first individually but with extra sheets printed so that they could be used for the Works.<lb/>
That project was, however, at odds with his constant itch to revise, and the resulting volumes of Works are combinations of new printings and sheets published at various earlier times.<lb/>
Their incoherent collations reflect their piecemeal assemblage, and the texts in the three formats can be significantly different.<lb/>
The engravings show the consequences of this cheese-paring approach.<lb/>
There were to be new engravings for the Dunciad, where Gilliver owned the copyright and would have had to pay, but the general money-saving plan was to decorate the book with the plates that had been prepared by William Kent and Paul Fourdrinier for Pope’s translation of the Odyssey (1725 – 6).<lb/>
Pope eventually proved willing to pay for modification of the Odyssey engravings and for some new ones to emphasize the thematic unity of the two books of ‘Epistles’, but the reuse of the Odyssey plates draws attention away from what was potentially a coherent plan for illustration of the Works.<lb/>
</p>
<head>The Plan for<lb/>Works II (1735)</head>
<p>
The Works falls into four sections, marked by heraldic headpieces and tailpieces.<lb/>
Pat Rogers has demonstrated that some of the early work in Pope’s career had a heraldic underpinning, especially the imagery in Windsor-Forest (1713), which Rogers connects with the Stuart claim to the throne.<note n="6">Pope and the Destiny of the Stuarts: History, Politics, and Mythology in the Age of Queen Anne (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005), 5 – 6, 200 – 6.</note><lb/>
In 1735 heraldry was used to mark Pope’s social status and commitments.<lb/>
The first section consists of the four epistles of An Essay on Man, addressed to Henry St. John, Viscount Bolingbroke, the leader of the opposition to Sir Robert Walpole’s ministry.<lb/>
It begins with an engraving including his coat of arms.<note n="7">Heraldic designs accompanying these epistles and those noted in the next paragraph are illustrated below: Essay on Man (figs 6–7); To Cobham (figs 8–9); To Burlington (fig. 10); To Oxford (fig. 11); To Arbuthnot (fig. 12).</note><lb/>
</p>
<pb n="189"/>
<lb/>The second section has four main epistles (those that became known through the Twickenham edition as the <hi rend="italic">Epistles to Several Persons</hi>), plus a further three.<lb/>
Four of the seven are addressed to dissident aristocrats (Richard Temple, Viscount Cobham; Allen, Baron Bathurst; Richard Boyle, Earl of Burlington; and Robert Harley, Earl of Oxford), one is addressed to a woman from an ancient Roman Catholic family, Martha Blount, one to Joseph Addison, and one to the Queen’s physician, Dr Arbuthnot.<lb/>
Addison stands outside this group through his role in the Whig government, but the poem celebrates him for his attempt to recover the values of ancient Rome and for his friend, James Craggs, Jr.<lb/>
The engravings reinforce the social and historical standing of this group, illustrating the arms of Cobham, Burlington, Oxford, and, most strikingly, at the end of <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi>, those Pope imagined to be his father’s.<lb/>
In the third section that follows these epistles, Pope finds space to explore and justify his oppositional stance in relation to court and ministry, laying out precedents through his imitations of Horace and Donne.<lb/>
Both Horace and Donne, we are to understand, satirized the powerful, treating vice and folly with contempt:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Both these Authors were acceptable to the Princes and Ministers under whom they lived: The Satires of Dr. Donne I versify’d at the Desire of the Earl of Oxford while he was Lord Treasurer, and of the Duke of Shrewsbury who had been Secretary of State; neither of whom look’d upon a Satire on Vicious Courts as any Reflection on those they serv’d in.</hi> (‘Advertisement’, ‘Satires of Horace’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, italics reversed)<lb/>
The most important of these imitations was <hi rend="italic">The First Satire of the Second Book of Horace Imitated</hi>, a poem that in the title page to its first edition (Griffith 288) first named Pope esquire (‘Alexander Pope in Com. Midd. Esq;’) and that closed with a careful evocation of Pope’s social circle.<lb/>
The circle is aristocratic – ‘Envy must own, I live among the Great’ (line 133) – but these men enjoy a special oppositional distinction; they are ‘Chiefs out of war, and Statesmen out of place’ (line 126).<note n="8">Imitations of Horace, ed. John Butt, Twickenham Edition of the Poems of Alexander Pope, vol.&amp;nbsp;4, 2nd edn (London: Methuen, 1953), 16–17. In subsequent references these editions will be referred to as <hi rend="italic">Twickenham</hi>.</note><lb/>
This praise of Pope’s association with men out of power had been anticipated in the ‘Letter to the Publisher’ signed by William Cleland in the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi>, where Pope was commended because ‘his Panegyricks’ were ‘bestow’d only on such persons as he had familiarly known, only for such virtues as he had long observ’d in them, and only at such times as others cease to praise if not begin to calumniate them, I mean when out of Power or out of Fashion.’<note n="9"><hi rend="italic">The Dunciad</hi> (1728) &amp; <hi rend="italic">The Dunciad Variorum</hi> (1729), ed.&amp;nbsp;Valerie Rumbold, Longman Pope, III (Harlow: Pearson Longman, 2007), 133–4. Subsequent references will be to this edition.</note><lb/>
In a footnote Pope gave the names of Wycherley, Walsh, Trumbull, Bolingbroke, Oxford, and Craggs, but in the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> he expanded the focus to include significant aristocratic and political figures such as Cobham, Bathurst, and Burlington.<lb/>
In this third section the dignity of Pope’s friendships is represented not by engravings but by a motto, a line of the poem, distinguished by capitals, in both Horace’s Latin and Pope’s English:<lb/>
<pb n="190"/>
<p>Uni Æquus virtuti atque ejus amicis<lb/>
To Virtue only and her friends, a friend<note n="10">Twickenham, 4:17–19, line 121 [Latin 70]; in this case presentation has been adjusted to conform to the text of the quarto Works.</note><lb/></p>
<p>But the motto had already been given its engraving, which is to be found on the title page of the Works. The medallion of Pope’s head, embraced by putti representing poetry and painting, that had closed the Odyssey, is now made the title page vignette, with the motto of virtue and friendship engraved round it.<lb/></p>
<p>In the fourth and final part of the Works, the Dunciad, the heraldry of friendship gives way to the heraldry of folly. The serious use of coats of arms in the Epistles in new engravings or modified Odyssey headpieces is replaced by a mock-heroic one. The mock-heraldic quality of these engravings has been well established in the accounts by Elias&amp;nbsp;F.&amp;nbsp;Engel, Jr., and Nicholas&amp;nbsp;Savage. New headpieces complement the one with an owl and asses that was originally designed for the Dunciad Variorum and is now reused as a tailpiece. They are modelled on the lines of the Odyssey’s headpieces, but show those motifs being abused: the heraldic supporters become asses; asses play lyres and harps; the characteristic central medallion is occupied by Orator Henley or Harlequin; and the royal motto ‘Nemo me impune lacessit’ is given to these emblems of folly. The Dunciad heraldry indirectly reflects on the monarch and edges him into the satire<note n="11">J.&amp;nbsp;Paul Hunter has suggested, rightly in my view, that George&amp;nbsp;II is represented by the Ass frontispiece to the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi>, which picks up a central motif of the headpieces: ‘From Typology to Type: Agents of Change in Eighteenth-Century English Texts,’ in Margaret&amp;nbsp;J.&amp;nbsp;M. Ezell and Katherine O’Brien&amp;nbsp;O’Keeffe (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Cultural Artifacts and the Production of Meaning: The Page, the Image, and the Body</hi> (Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press, 1994), 41–69.</note>. Lurking in the background – it came to realization in the author’s ‘Declaration’ in the Dunciad in Four Books in 1743 – was the possible mockery of the royal arms themselves as they represented the Hanoverian dynasty. George&amp;nbsp;II’s heraldic home was in the Dunciad rather than in the ‘Epistles’.<lb/></p>
<p>Although I believe Pope had a plan of this sort in mind for Works&amp;nbsp;II, it was not straightforwardly realized. In the remainder of this essay I try to trace the development of the engravings from the Odyssey, through the Dunciad Variorum and some individually published epistles, into Works&amp;nbsp;II, noting changes as the project developed. I examine some of the detail of Pope’s conception, but also the difficulty he experienced in realizing it in the books themselves.<lb/></p>
<head>The Odyssey Engravings <lb/>(1725–6)</head>
<p>The contract between Pope and Lintot for the Odyssey had specific provisions for the engravings, making them Pope’s responsibility:<lb/></p>
<p>And it is farther Covenanted Concluded and Agreed by and between the Said Alexander Pope and Bernard Lintott that the Said Alexander Pope Shall be at the whole Expense and Charge of the Copper Plates for the Head peices, Tail peices and Initial Letters,<lb/>Except only the Charge of working the Same at the rolling Press which Charge He the Said Bernard Lintott Shall be at And Farther that the Said Copper Plates Shall always after remain to Him the Said Bernard Lintott and his Assignes But that notwithstanding<lb/></p>
<pb n="191"/>
<p>the Said Bernard Lintott and his Assignes Shall at any time or times permit the Said Al-<lb/>exander Pope or his Assignes to have the Use of the Said Copper Plates for the Printing <lb/>of any other Book or Books which He the Said Alexander Pope Shall think fit He the <lb/>said Alexander Pope or his Assignes being at the charge of touching up the Said Plates if <lb/>Occasion Shall So require<note n="12">George Sherburn, <hi rend="italic">The Early Career of Alexander Pope</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1934), 315–16. I have represented the enlarged writing by <hi rend="bold">bold</hi> rather than by black letter.</note> <lb/>Lintot, therefore, kept the engravings after they had been used in the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, <lb/>but Pope had the right to use them. In the summer of 1732 he had discussions <lb/>with Samuel Buckley about whether they could be used in the edition of Jacques <lb/>Auguste de Thou’s <hi rend="italic">Historiarum Sui Temporis</hi> (1733), a large showy book on excep-<lb/>tionally thick paper that Buckley, the printer of the <hi rend="italic">London Gazette</hi> and govern-<lb/>ment informant, had been planning since before January 1728.<note n="13"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Alexander Pope</hi>, ed. George Sherburn, 5 vols (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1956), 3:294. Sherburn says Buckley’s <hi rend="italic">A Letter to Dr. Mead, Concerning a New Edition of Thuanus’s History</hi> had circulated very early in 1728 (<hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>, 2:471n3).</note><lb/>In a letter of 16 June [1732], Pope said he had had the articles of his contract checked <lb/>and could now confirm his offer to lend the engravings to Buckley. These discussions with <lb/>Buckley probably alerted Pope to the possibility of using the same engravings when later <lb/>that year he made plans for collecting his works. In an agreement with Lawton Gilliver on <lb/>1 December 1732, he said he was planning to publish a series of epistles (<hi rend="italic">To Burlington</hi> <lb/>had been published a year before, on 14 December 1731) and was willing to sell the publishing <lb/>rights of each one to Gilliver for one year for £50, the rights then to revert to Pope. In a <lb/>memorandum that was most probably written at the same time, Pope recorded his intention <lb/>of allowing Gilliver to collect all these epistles and the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> (of which Gilliver owned <lb/>the copyright and had an edition in quarto and folio ‘lying by’) in ‘The Works of Mr <lb/>Alexander Pope. Volume the Second’.<note n="14">BL Egerton MS 1951, f. 12; printed in Robert W. Rogers, <hi rend="italic">The Major Satires of Alexander Pope</hi> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1955), 119.</note> <lb/>The full range of the plan for the epistles was originally printed at the end of the first <lb/>collected edition of <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi>, published 20 April 1734, and is recorded by Spence.<note n="15">See Foxon, <hi rend="italic">Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade</hi>, 120–8; Joseph Spence, <hi rend="italic">Observations, Anecdotes, and Characters of Books and Men</hi>, ed. James M. Osborn, 2 vols (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1966), 1:132. A monograph on the topic is Miriam Leranbaum’s <hi rend="italic">Alexander Pope’s ‘Opus Magnum’, 1729–1744</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977).</note><lb/>The engravings from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> (headpieces, initials, and tailpieces) that <lb/>Pope lent to Buckley and decided to reuse himself were designed by William <lb/>Kent and engraved by Paul Fourdrinier.<note n="16">Whereas in the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> (like the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi>) only the quartos (Griffith 151, 155, 159, 166, 170) had engravings, in the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> both the quarto and the large-paper folio had them.</note> <lb/>They have recently been subjected to a detailed and appreciative analysis by Nicholas <lb/>Savage.<note n="17">‘Kent as Book Illustrator’, 419–25. In addition to the work he did for Pope, who was a personal friend, Kent illustrated Gay’s <hi rend="italic">Fables</hi> (1727) and <hi rend="italic">Poems on Several Occasions</hi> (1720), Thomson’s <hi rend="italic">The Seasons</hi> (1730), and Thomas Birch’s edition of Spenser’s <hi rend="italic">Faerie Queene</hi> (1751).</note> <lb/>I share his admiration for them. The headpieces are not deep, with the height a little more <lb/>than a third of the width (the image approx. 6 cm high by 16 wide), but these propor-<lb/>tions worked well on the quarto page of the subscription editions. Figure 1 is an</p>
<pb n="192"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 1.</head>
  <figDesc>Headpiece to Epitaphs, Works II quarto; adopted from Odyssey I.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<pb n="193"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 2.</head>
  <figDesc>Tailpiece to To a Lady, Works II quarto; from Odyssey VII.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<p>example from Odyssey, Book I, reused for the Works II Epitaphs. These headpieces<lb/>
have a central circle (3.5&amp;nbsp;cm in diameter), which usually depicts a figure from the ac-<lb/>
tion of the poem. To either side of the circle are placed objects that evoke the world<lb/>
of the epic, either symbols of war (spears, shields, helmets) or of peace (lyres, goblets,<lb/>
bowls), often enwrapped by fertile vegetation. The whole is contained in a decorative<lb/>
frame. Usually the initials ‘W.K. inv.’ and ‘P.F. sc.’ appear on opposite sides of the foot<lb/>
of the plate. Savage argues persuasively for the close relation between the headpieces<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="194"/>
<p>and the action that is to follow in the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, both in the scene depicted and in the surrounding objects.<lb/>The engraved initials that accompany the headpieces are simple but with a frame that echoes that of the headpiece.<lb/>The tailpieces are more freely imaginative, representing fantastic, sometimes grotesque, creatures or decorated ob-<lb/>jects. Figure 2 is an example from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, Book VII, reused in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>, p.&amp;nbsp;24, and <hi rend="italic">To a Lady</hi>, p.&amp;nbsp;71.<lb/>They are excessively splendid in the way that Kent’s decorations of aristocratic homes are splendid, and they are sometimes too big for the quarto page.<note n="18">William Kent: <hi rend="italic">Designing Georgian Britain</hi> illustrates many objects that have something in common with the engravings: the Prince of Wales’s barge with its mermaids and dolphins (fig.&amp;nbsp;12.1); the mermaids at the base of a settee in Wanstead House (fig.&amp;nbsp;17.10); a figure very like Leucothea in a chandelier for the King (fig.&amp;nbsp;19.8); mermaids at the foot of girandoles for the Leineschloss, Hanover (fig.&amp;nbsp;19.10); putti are pervasive.</note></p>
<head>The <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> (1728) and The <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi> (1729)</head>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1735) seems to have been printed by 3&amp;nbsp;January&amp;nbsp;1733, a date given at the end of its mock declaration signed by John&amp;nbsp;Barber.<lb/>Although its notes were moved to the end of the volume, it was in other respects very dependent on the presentation of the <hi rend="italic">Variorum</hi> in 1729.<note n="19">David&amp;nbsp;Foxon, <hi rend="italic">English Verse, 1701–1750</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975), gives the date of publication as 13&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1729 (P771–2).</note></p>
<p>That in turn drew on the model of the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> engravings.<lb/>Both Engel and Savage have pointed to a drawing of an owl at Chatsworth, most probably by Kent, as the basis for the owl that formed the frontispiece to the first <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> (1728).<note n="20">Published 18&amp;nbsp;May&amp;nbsp;1728 (Foxon, <hi rend="italic">English Verse</hi>, P764–5). There is a distinguished facsimile edition: <hi rend="italic">Pope’s Dunciad of&amp;nbsp;1728: A History and Facsimile</hi>, ed.&amp;nbsp;David&amp;nbsp;L. Vander&amp;nbsp;Meulen (Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia for the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1991).</note><lb/>In that frontispiece, the owl, which Engel suggests is ‘from the medieval art of heraldry’, stands on a column of books (a mockery of a Greek altar).<note n="21">For discussion of this frontispiece, see Engel, ‘The Dunciad Illustrations’, 164; Savage, ‘Kent as Book Illustrator’, 427.</note><lb/>The central pillar is an extraordinarily thick volume, stamped with <hi rend="smallcaps">OGILBY</hi> on the spine and on the front with something resembling a coat of arms.<lb/>The allusion is to a passage in the poem on Theobald’s library that has a surprising relevance to Pope’s own books.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">He roll’d his eyes that witness’d huge dismay,<lb/>
Where yet unpawn’d, much learned lumber lay,<lb/>
Volumes, whose size the space exactly fill’d;<lb/>
Or which fond authors were so good to gild;<lb/>
Or where, by Sculpture made for ever known,<lb/>
The page admires new beauties, not its own.<lb/>
Here swells the shelf with Ogleby the great,<lb/>
There, stamp’d with arms, Newcastle shines compleat . . .</hi><lb/>(I.105–12, <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> 1728 &amp; 1729, 29–30)</p>
<pb n="195"/>
<p>In this context ‘Sculpture’ means engraving, and, contrary to the ridicule implicit <lb/>in these lines, Pope had a childhood love for John Ogilby’s translation of Homer <lb/>– ‘It was that great edition with pictures’ – even though he did not admire the <lb/>translation.<note n="22">Spence, 1:14. Pope’s reading was ‘at eight or nine years old’.</note> David Foxon has argued that Ogilby’s illustrations even helped <lb/>shape those of Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi>.<note n="23">Foxon, Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade, 76–81.</note> I suspect Pope had a similar ambivalent relationship <lb/>to the stamping of arms by Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of Newcastle, referred <lb/>to in the next line. Pope added a note to the <hi rend="italic">Variorum</hi> edition explaining, ‘Lang-<lb/>baine reckons up eight Folio’s of her Grace’s; which were usually adorn’d with <lb/>gilded Covers, and had her Coat of Arms upon them’ (<hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> 1728 &amp; 1729, <lb/>193). The covers of her books are regularly stamped with gold fleurons in the <lb/>corners just like the book in Pope’s owl frontispiece, but I have not found a cover <lb/>stamped with her arms.<note n="24">Her arms are not found in Liza Blake, ‘Margaret Cavendish’s University Years: Batch Bindings and Trade Bindings in Cambridge and Oxford’, PBSA, 111:1 (2022), 21–91. They are discussed in relation to her monument in Westminster Abbey: http://westminster-abbey.org/our-history/people/william-and-margaret-cavendish (22 March 2024). Those on Pope’s frontispiece (a chevron with three martlets) are not hers.</note><lb/></p>
<p>What the Duchess of Newcastle does do, and in this she was followed in <lb/>1735 by Pope, is use coats of arms in headpieces. Ogilby in his <hi rend="italic">Homer</hi> (1660) <lb/>and Tonson in the subscription edition of Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Virgil</hi> (1697) included plates <lb/>that at their foot contained the coat of arms of a subscriber. The coat of arms <lb/>proclaimed the aristocratic patronage of the volume. But in the Duchess’s books <lb/>the arms in the headpieces advertised not the patron’s but the author’s status. In <lb/><hi rend="italic">Philosophical Letters: or, Modest Reflections upon Some Opinions in Natural Philosophy</hi> <lb/>(London, 1664), a woodblock headpiece of the royal arms of England appears <lb/>above the first poem, ‘To Her Excellency The Lady Marchioness of Newcastle, <lb/>on her Book of <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Letters</hi>’ and is then used several more times. The <lb/>deployment of heraldry is more sophisticated in the Latin translation of her life <lb/>of her husband, <hi rend="italic">De Vita et Rebus Gestis Nobilissimi Ilustrissimique Principis, Guilielmi,</hi> <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ducis Novo-Castrensis</hi> (London, 1668), where elements of the Ogle (a star and cres-<lb/>cent) and Cavendish (simplified bucks’ heads caboshed [without neck]) arms are <lb/>combined with differing supporters to represent different aspects of his career. <lb/>How far this practice may have influenced Kent in preparing Pope’s headpieces <lb/>(they similarly deploy central arms with putti supporters) it is difficult to deter-<lb/>mine, but the illustrations in the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1735) show a similar <lb/>complexity, exploring the ways heraldry might be used not only to decorate a <lb/>book but to reinforce its themes.<lb/></p>
<p>When it came to designing the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi>, the splendid engraving <lb/>on the title page – an ass carrying a burden of books – was supplemented by <lb/>a headpiece for Book I modelled on the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> headpieces and later used in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (figure 3). I agree with Savage that this headpiece, like the owl, it <lb/>is likely to be Kent’s work (‘Kent as Book Illustrator’, 427). Such engagement <lb/>is very much in keeping with his patron Burlington’s support for the publica-<lb/>tion of the <hi rend="italic">Variorum</hi>. In a letter George Sherburn dates 23 December 1728, <lb/>Pope reveals that Burlington has acted for him by showing some papers to the <lb/></p>
<pb n="196"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 3.</head>
  <figDesc>Tailpiece to<lb/>Dunciad II, Works II quarto; from headpiece to<lb/>Dunciad Variorum I.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<pb n="197"/>
<p>
<lb/>lawyer Nicholas Fazakerley and is to pass on something else, ‘these’, probably 
<lb/>engravings, to Kent. It is highly likely that while Burlington was helping Pope 
<lb/>protect himself from prosecution, Kent was illustrating his book. A letter from 
<lb/>the same period suggests that the Burlingtons had pre-publication knowledge 
<lb/>of the frontispiece, Pope interpreting it as a representation not of the King but 
<lb/>of himself: ‘I beg my Lady Burlington’s Patronage of the Ass &amp; the Dunciad, 
<lb/>me and my burden.’<note n="25">Correspondence, 1:532–3 and 2:4.</note> When the three lords (Burlington, Oxford, and Bathurst) 
<lb/>protected Pope by temporarily buying the copyright to the <hi rend="italic">Variorum</hi>, a later as-
<lb/>signment makes it clear that Burlington was the leading figure, while Kent was 
<lb/>one of the witnesses.<note n="26">BL MS Egerton 1951, f. 7; Rogers, <hi rend="italic">Major Satires</hi>, 116. Pope had himself assigned the copy to Lords Burlington, Oxford, and Bathurst. It strikes me that Burlington’s later resignation of his court offices, in May 1733, may have been connected with Pope’s breach with the court over the response to <hi rend="italic">To Burlington</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">First Satire of the Second Book of Horace Imitated</hi> in February of that year.</note>
<lb/>In the centre of the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi> headpiece, later used in the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, 
<lb/>where an action of the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> might be depicted, is the head of an owl, crowned 
<lb/>with a jester’s cap; his supporters are two asses; the foliage that customarily links 
<lb/>the design consists of thistles. J. Paul Hunter points to the proximity of the asses’ 
<lb/>ears to the ‘Ear of Kings’ in the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi> just below the headpiece, in the 
<lb/>second line of the poem. A multivalent indication of Pope’s attitude lies in the 
<lb/>motto ‘Nemo me impune lacessit’: no one attacks me with impunity. The motto 
<lb/>is that of the Order of the Thistle. Pope had shown an interest in the thistle 
<lb/>as a symbol in his first Pastoral, in a riddle that marked the union of Scotland 
<lb/>and England, the thistle having replaced the French lily in the first and fourth 
<lb/>quarters of the national shield.<note n="27">‘Spring’, lines 89–90, <hi rend="italic">Pastoral Poetry and An Essay on Criticism</hi>, ed. E. Audra and Aubrey Williams (London: Methuen, 1961), Twickenham, 1:69.</note> Pope’s riddle was possibly designed to honour 
<lb/>Queen Anne, who had revived the Order of the Thistle in 1703, but she was 
<lb/>only repeating the more significant revival of her father, James II of England 
<lb/>and VII of Scotland, in 1687. This was inescapably a Scottish and, in origin, a 
<lb/>Stuart order. Mengel notes the suitability of the thistle as an emblem for satire 
<lb/>and suggests possible connection with ideas of Scottish stupidity, but the motto 
<lb/>fits as uncomfortably with George II as it does with the owl dunce, both of 
<lb/>whom were being attacked with impunity. Pope claimed in the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> that the 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Dunciad Variorum</hi> had been presented to the King: ‘We are willing to acquaint 
<lb/>posterity that this Poem (as it here stands) was presented to King George the 
<lb/>Second and his Queen, by the hands of Sir R. Walpole, on the 12th of March 
<lb/>1728/9’ (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>, 87). William Kupersmith points to Erasmus ‘<hi rend="italic">Similes 
<lb/>habent labra lactusas</hi>’, which is equivalent to the English ‘A thistle is a fat 
<lb/>salad for an ass’s mouth’.<note n="28">William Kupersmith, ‘Asses, Adages, and the Illustrations to Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>’, <hi rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 8:2 (1974–5), 206–11.</note> A bad patron (including the King) and bad writers 
<lb/>go together.
</p>
<pb n="198"/>
<head>Collected Horatian Satires and<lb/>Essay on Man</head>
<p><lb/><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he first opportunity to try out William Kent’s Odyssey engravings as accompa-<lb/>niments to Pope’s poems came with the collected editions of <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi> <lb/>(Foxon P850 –3, published 20 April 1734) and of the Horatian Satires II.i and <lb/>II.ii (Foxon P893 –5, 4 July 1734). The collections seem to have been planned <lb/>together, with some <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> engravings being retouched to suit their new role <lb/>and some left unchanged. Both collections were printed with reissue in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Works</hi> in mind, and, though in some cases that plan did not come to fruition, the en-<lb/>gravings did reappear when <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II was published a year later. Although the <lb/>two Satires were published over two months later than <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi>, it was <lb/>one of their engravings that proved most significant for the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> the following <lb/>year.<note n="29">Foxon, <hi rend="italic">English Verse</hi>, P893 – 5, gives the date of publication as 4 July 1734. Although the collected <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> was issued in the usual three formats, I suspect there were no large-paper folios of the <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> issued. The ESTC does not record one and Foxon’s possible example, P895, has no engravings.</note> There are no headpieces to the Satires, only tailpieces to mark the ends of <lb/>the parallel Latin and English texts, and there is no room for a tailpiece at the <lb/>end of the Latin of Satire II.ii. Of the three illustrations, two were simply taken <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>: the Latin of Satire II.i closes on p. 18 with an altar adorned <lb/>with the image of the helmeted Minerva,<note n="30">I have followed Pope’s practice, using the Latin names in his Index.</note> an ornament that originally appeared <lb/>at the end of <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> Book XVII; the English of Satire II.ii closes on p. 40, with <lb/>the goblet Mulius ‘crown’d / With purple juice’ at the end of <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> Book XVIII. <lb/>Neither engraving seems particularly appropriate to its poem, though they are <lb/>concerned with wisdom and feasting. But the vignette at the end of the English <lb/>of Satire II.i (p. 19) — the one that was to find its way to the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> title page <lb/>— is appropriate and changes had been made to enforce its significance (figure <lb/>4). It had originally appeared at the end of the last book of the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, where <lb/>Kent abandoned the usual task of illustrating the poem in order to symbolize <lb/>his friendship and collaboration with Pope. Two putti, representing poetry and <lb/>painting, embrace above a medallion of Pope’s head. One putto holds a lyre, and <lb/>a sheet of text and a palette lie below the medallion. The paper is marked ‘W. <lb/>Kent inv.’ while below it is ‘P. Fourdrinier sc.’<note n="31">The engraving is No. 17 in William Kurtz Wimsatt, <hi rend="italic">The Portraits of Alexander Pope</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1965), 125 – 6. Wimsatt traces Pope’s subsequent use of the image.</note> For the collected edition of the <lb/>Satires the symbolism of the vignette was broadened to include all Pope’s friends. <lb/>Added to the medallion is a quotation from the poem, ‘<hi rend="smallcaps">UNI ÆQVVS VIRTVTI ATQ. EIVS AMICI</hi>’, the words Pope had capitalized in the text since its first <lb/>publication on 15 February 1733, and imitated as ‘to Virtue only and her friends <lb/>a friend’. Pope had found in Kent’s affectionate commemoration a visual rep-<lb/>resentation of friendship founded on virtue. This symbolism proved of growing <lb/>importance in shaping the illustration of Pope’s books in the next few years. We <lb/></p>
<pb n="199"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 4.</head>
  <figDesc>Vignette on title page of Works II quarto; adapted from tailpiece to Odyssey XXIV.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<p>find the medallion again on the pages of the collected Essay on Man and then on<lb/>
 the title page of the Works<note n="32">Both the image and the plate were reduced in size for the Works title page. The end of Fourdrinier’s name has been lost, and there remains some smudging bottom left where the ma-<lb/>terial has not quite been cleared away. The change would be similar to the more radical adjust-<lb/>ments to some of the headpieces. An exceptionally full account of changing a plate, though for a<lb/> later period, is given in Roy J.&amp;nbsp;L. Cooney, ‘Chart Engraving at the Admiralty’s Hydrographic<lb/> Department, 1951–1981’, Journal of the Printing Historical Society, 25&amp;nbsp;(1996), 31–46. I suspect in<lb/> Pope’s case the alteration could be made without heating or beating the plate flat, and that the<lb/> new designs were created with the minimum intervention necessary.</note>.<lb/></p>
<p>Pope had published the four epistles of An Essay on Man in folio indepen-<lb/>
 dently at intervals between February&amp;nbsp;1733 and January&amp;nbsp;1734, but he published<lb/>
 all four together in quarto and large and small folio in April&amp;nbsp;1734<note n="33">David Foxon, English Verse, gives the dates as 20&amp;nbsp;February&amp;nbsp;1733 (P822), 29&amp;nbsp;March<lb/>1733 (P833), 8&amp;nbsp;May&amp;nbsp;1733 (P840), 24&amp;nbsp;January&amp;nbsp;1734 (P845), and, for the collected edition 20&amp;nbsp;April&amp;nbsp;1734 (P850–3).</note>.<lb/></p>
<p>The single epistles were decorated with simple woodblock printer’s ornaments, but the col-<lb/>
 lected edition, perhaps because the aim was to reuse it in the Works, called for<lb/>
 something more elaborate. The quarto and the large-paper folio have the same<lb/>
 illustrations in the preliminaries, but differ in the body of the text. After each<lb/>
 epistle the quarto has one of the tailpieces from the Odyssey: Epistle&amp;nbsp;I the mermaid<lb/>
 fountain from the end of Odyssey&amp;nbsp;VII (from the gardens of Alcinous); Epistle&amp;nbsp;II<lb/></p>
<pb n="200"/>
<milestone unit="horizontalRule" rend="hr"/>
<figure>
  <head>Figure 5</head>
  <figDesc>Tailpiece to Essay on Man IV, Works II quarto; from title page of first edition of collected Essay on Man.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<p>Leucothea from the end of Odyssey V (a feathered creature, though I am not very<lb/>
confident of the identification); Epistle III a winged siren from the end of Odyssey<lb/>
VI; and Epistle IV a repetition of the specially designed vignette from the title<lb/>
page. Savage perceptively connects these images of water creatures with the close<lb/>
of Pope’s introductory ‘Design’ to the Essay, discussing the epistles that are to<lb/>
come: ‘Consequently, these Epistles in their progress will become less dry, and<lb/>
more susceptible of Poetical Ornament. I am here only opening the Fountains,<lb/>
and clearing the passage; To deduce the Rivers, to follow them in their Course,<lb/>
and to observe their Effects, will be a task more agreeable. [italics reversed]’<lb/>
Perhaps, the fountains engraving was chosen to support this metaphor, and the<lb/>
others because they were adjacent in the Odyssey. The text left no room for these<lb/>
engravings in the large-paper folio, but that would have made production easier.<lb/>
The quarto sheets would have had to go separately through the rolling press in<lb/>
order for the engravings to be impressed.<lb/>
</p>
<p>The engravings the quarto and large folio shared in the preliminaries were<lb/>
inventive in a way the quarto’s tailpieces were not. The title page was provided<lb/>
with a new engraving especially designed for An Essay on Man: the head of Apollo<lb/>
emerges in glory from clouds, cobwebs, and old manuscripts. Around the head is<lb/>
the motto ‘ΓΝΩΘΙ ΣΕΑϒΤΟΝ’ (know thyself), one of the maxims of the temple<lb/>
of Apollo at Delphi (figure 5). The injunction is of central thematic importance to<lb/>
An Essay on Man. Pope begins his second epistle with a couplet that summarizes<lb/>
the first and defines his approach:<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="201"/>
<p>Know then thy‑self, presume not God to scan;<lb/>
The proper Study of mankind is Man.<note n="34">An Essay on Man, ed. Maynard Mack (London: Methuen; New&amp;nbsp;Haven: Yale University Press, 1951), Twickenham, 3.1:53, lines&amp;nbsp;II.1–2. I have used the typography of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II quarto.</note></p>
<p>Buried in the surrounding debris in the title‑page engraving are contrary maxims,<lb/>
largely taken from scholasticism, though not without reference to contemporary<lb/>
debates. The reasons for rejection of the tag furthest left, and most important, ‘a<lb/>
priori’, are made clear by Warburton’s note on those who take the ‘high Priori<lb/>
road’ in the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>: ‘those who, instead of reasoning from a visible World to an<lb/>
invisible God, took the other road; and from an invisible God (to whom they had given<lb/>
attributes agreeable to certain metaphysical principles formed out of their own<lb/>
imaginations) reasoned downwards to a visible world in theory, of Man’s Creation’.<note n="35">The Dunciad in Four Books, ed. Valerie Rumbold (Harlow: Longman, 1999), 331–2, line&amp;nbsp;IV.471n. Subsequent references will be to this edition.</note><lb/>
The next phrase is ‘substantiae immateriales’ (immaterial substances), an impor-<lb/>
tant idea in the first part of Aquinas’s <hi rend="italic">Summa Theologiae</hi>, the centre of a series of<lb/>
questions about men and angels.<note n="36">Thomas Aquinas, <hi rend="italic">Summa Theologiae</hi> (Alba: Editiones Paulinae), 426–8 (Part&amp;nbsp;1; quest.&amp;nbsp;88; arts.&amp;nbsp;1–2).</note><lb/>
Next comes ‘locus [est] ubi’, which I suspect,<lb/>
on the basis of the sketchy skulls that lie beneath, is short for ‘Hic locus est ubi<lb/>
mors gaudet succerre vitae’ (this is the place where death delights in aiding the<lb/>
living), the inscription over the University of Padua’s anatomical theatre. Then<lb/>
comes ‘universale a parte rei’ (the universal part of the thing), a much despised<lb/>
position in the debate about universals, and said by Bayle to be ‘a mere subtlety<lb/>
of Metaphysics, and . . . generally exploded now by the best Philosophers as a<lb/>
dispute about words only’; it is also mocked in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Martinus Scriblerus</hi>.<note n="37">Pierre Bayle, <hi rend="italic">A General Dictionary, Historical and Critical</hi> (London: J.&amp;nbsp;Roberts, 1734), 1:396; <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Extraordinary Life, Works, and Discourses of Martinus Scriblerus</hi>, ed.&amp;nbsp;Charles Kerby-Miller (New&amp;nbsp;Haven: Yale University Press, 1950), 120–2, 124.</note><lb/>
Finally come ‘ens rationis’ (an abstract logical entity) and ‘Essentia intelligibil[es]<lb/>
(intelligible essences), both instances of the abstract knowledge rejected here by<lb/>
Pope and by Bolingbroke in his philosophy.<note n="38">G.&amp;nbsp;Anderson mentions the attitude to ‘a&amp;nbsp;priori’ (passim) and both ‘universale a&amp;nbsp;parte rei’ and ‘ens rationis’ in his <hi rend="italic">A&amp;nbsp;Remonstrance against Lord Viscount Bolingbroke’s Philosophical Religion</hi> (London, 1756), 20.</note><lb/>
The engraving is well proportioned<lb/>
in relation to its pages, but neither inventor nor engraver is identified, and, in<lb/>
comparison with its companions by Kent, it lacks boldness and clarity; the mot-<lb/>
tos seem to testify to a lack of confidence in the visual symbols’ ability to speak<lb/>
to the reader. I suspect Pope was the inventor and that he may have had help<lb/>
from Bolingbroke.</p>
<p>At the end of the ‘Design’, explaining his conception of the poem, Pope<lb/>
placed the vignette that had been adapted from the end of the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> to illustrate<lb/>
Satire&amp;nbsp;II.i with the motto ‘<hi rend="smallcaps">UNI ÆQVVS VIRTVTI ATQ. EIVS AMICI</hi>’. That<lb/>
symbol of friendship complemented and highlighted the meaning of the head-<lb/>
piece that then appeared on the first page of the poem. The early editions of the<lb/>
epistle, with the title <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man. Address’d to a Friend</hi>, had begun ‘Awake!<lb/>
my Lælius’, the name Laelius being used to declare the importance of friendship.</p>
<pb n="202"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">G</hi>aius Laelius, the friend of Scipio Aemilianus, was famed for wisdom and friend<lb/>ship. His name prefixes the title of <hi rend="italic">De Amicitia</hi>, a work in whose dialogue he plays a leading part.<lb/>The name also provided a further link between <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi> and Horace’s <hi rend="italic">Satire</hi> II.i,<lb/>where Laelius appears with Scipio, listening happily to Lucilius’ satires (lines 62–74). In Pope’s imitation<lb/>Scipio becomes the Earl of Peterborough and Laelius Lord Bolingbroke (Pope himself immodestly supplying<lb/>the place of both Lucilius and Horace, lines 127–32). The appearance of Bolingbroke’s name, instead of<lb/>Laelius’s, in the first line of the new collected poem, therefore, made specific the connections that already<lb/>existed between the two poems. It must nonetheless have been a shock to those who had not seen Pope as<lb/>willing to ally himself with opposition to Walpole and the Hanoverian court to read the first lines:<lb/>Awake! my St. John! leave all meaner things<lb/>To low Ambition and the Pride of Kings.<lb/>In the new context, it is difficult to see how ‘the Pride of Kings’ can avoid reflect<lb/>ing on George II.</p>
<p>The declaration of Bolingbroke’s importance to the poem is reinforced by the headpiece, which takes one of<lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> engravings and places Bolingbroke’s coat of arms at its centre (figure 6). This headpiece had<lb/>been the first to ap<lb/>pear in the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, with a profile of Homer in the centre, heading ‘A General View of the Epic Poem’ on p. i.<lb/>The alteration stands out through its white background (no hatching), and faintness. The accompanying initial<lb/>‘A’ is from <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, IV. Bolingbroke is not, of course, being accorded quite the same status as Homer held in<lb/>Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, but he is the aristocratic friend who is to share the new investigation: ‘Let Us . . . expatiate free,<lb/>o’er all this Scene of Man’ (lines 3–5). In 1715 Bolingbroke had lost his titles and property as punishment for<lb/>his flight to the court of the Pretender at St Germains, but they had been restored after his pardon in 1723,<lb/>though he was not allowed to take his place in the House of Lords.<note n="39">Illustrations of his arms are to be found in John Guillim, <hi rend="italic">A Display of Heraldry</hi>, 6th edn (London, 1724), after p. 2104, no. 2, and, with a discussion, in Anthony R. Wagner, <hi rend="italic">Historic Heraldry in Britain</hi> (London: Oxford University Press, 1939), p. 86, no. 104.</note> He was at this time leading the opposition to Walpole and symbolized in<lb/>himself the friend who in his independence presented a challenge to the new order. The arms in the engraving<lb/>projected the public as well as the private man.</p>
<p><hi rend="smallcaps">Works II (1735)</hi><lb/>When Pope came to plan the details of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, probably sometime in the au<lb/>tumn of 1734, he recognized that the theme of aristocratic friendship symbolized by the headpiece to<lb/><hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi> could be used to shape the first half of his volume and offer an illuminating contrast to the<lb/>second half. A major decision was to place the ‘<hi rend="smallcaps">UNI ÆQVVS VIRTVTI ATQ. EIVS AMICI</hi>’ vignette on the<lb/>title page. In 1717 a large poster-sized portrait of Pope had served as a frontis<lb/>piece; now the author was presented as a classic by a simple medallion in which</p>
<pb n="203"/>
<figure>
  
  <figDesc>
    <hi rend="smallcaps">figure</hi> 6. Headpiece to Essay on Man I, Works II folio; adapted from the ‘General View’ of<lb/>
    the Odyssey.<lb/>
  </figDesc>
</figure>
<figure>
  
  <figDesc>
    <hi rend="smallcaps">figure</hi> 7. New headpiece to Essay on Man I, Works II quarto.<lb/>
  </figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="204"/>
<p>his image was surrounded by the profession of virtuous friendship. Initially Pope <lb/>
may have intended to follow up this design with heraldic headpieces for his friends <lb/>
adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> headpieces, but at a later stage, while various poems <lb/>
were in press, he obtained fresh engravings of these arms from Kent and included <lb/>
them instead. When the ‘large Quarto’ was advertised in the <hi rend="italic">Grub-street <lb/>
Journal</hi> on 24 April 1735, it was with ‘Copper Plates, design’d by Mr. Kent’ <lb/>
(Griffith, 2:287).<lb/></p>
<p>Different engravings show up in the different formats of the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>. In the case <lb/>
of the first poem in the collection, <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi>, the large-paper folios used the <lb/>
sheets of the collected edition of 1734 (Foxon P851). I suspect that by this point in <lb/>
his career Pope had recognized that large-paper folios were difficult to sell. The <lb/>
subscription editions of the Homer translations had been in quarto and readers <lb/>
who needed to make up large folio sets would have been difficult to identify. For <lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi>, 250 large-paper folios were printed, but I should be surprised if Pope <lb/>
and Gilliver persisted with so many. From the number of surviving copies, it <lb/>
seems that the large-folio edition of the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> was quite small.<note n="40">Few copies <lb/>
survive. The British Library has one (Ashley 5235), as apparently from ESTC T5391 <lb/>
do six North American libraries. The two copies listed in Oxford libraries <lb/>
(26 September 2016) are actually quartos. The ESTC T222362 and Foxon, <hi rend="italic">English <lb/>
Verse</hi>, P851 between them list four copies of the related <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>.</note> For the quarto, <lb/>
however, <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Man</hi> was newly printed, and Pope took the opportunity to <lb/>
replace the modified <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> headpiece with a new one (figure 7). The result is <lb/>
bolder and clearer. The supporting falcons have been removed and the motto <lb/>
has been taken out of the central oval and placed on an outside ribbon. The <lb/>
lyres are still there but the foliage is wrapped gracefully in circles round them. <lb/>
Pope clearly liked the heraldic effect of the original <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> adaptation and was <lb/>
prepared to pay for an engraving that presented it more clearly. I suspect the <lb/>
design was Kent’s, though only Fourdrinier has signed it.<note n="41">The <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> quarto <lb/>
does not use the Leucothea tailpiece at the end of Epistle II of the collected <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi> <lb/>
but substitutes the siren of Epistle III instead. The other engravings are the same.</note></p>
<p>The poem that follows the <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> and introduces the second sequence <lb/>
of epistles also starts with variant forms of the heraldic headpiece. <hi rend="italic">To Sir Richard <lb/>
Temple Lord Viscount Cobham</hi> begins in the quarto (figure 8) with another adapted <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> engraving (from Book V), and in the folio with a new specially designed <lb/>
one (figure 9). In the thick-paper copy of the enhanced <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II (Griffith 514) that <lb/>
Pope seems to have published in 1739, the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> headpiece appears unaltered. <lb/>
Presumably the sheet containing the first page must have been printed first back <lb/>
in 1735 (the most expensive copies impressed while the type was clean), and sent <lb/>
off to the rolling press, where the unaltered engraving was used. Before the ap-<lb/>
propriate sheet of the ordinary paper quarto arrived, the engraving must have <lb/>
been altered (perhaps all this activity was in Fourdrinier’s shop), and before the <lb/>
large folio was impressed the new engraving must have been prepared.<lb/></p>
<p>Pope changed his mind about the order of the four epistles that begin this <lb/>
second section. They ended up <hi rend="italic">To Cobham</hi>, <hi rend="italic">To a Lady</hi>, <hi rend="italic">To Bathurst</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">To <lb/>
Burlington</hi>, but in the quarto Cobham’s second page is numbered ‘48’ and Bathurst’s <lb/>
‘8’. The folio was tidied up and impressed later, but it was from the same setting <lb/>
of type and its first page number in this section, ‘8’, suggests a merely partial.<lb/></p>
<pb n="205"/>
<figure>
  
  <figDesc>figure 8.<lb/>Headpiece to To Cobham, Works II quarto; adapted from Odyssey V.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure>
  
  <figDesc>figure 9.<lb/>New headpiece to To Cobham, Works II folio.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="206"/>
<p>correction of the quarto’s page numbering.<lb/>There are many oddities of signatures and paper in this sequence in the quarto<lb/>but it is noteworthy that all the poems except <hi>To a Lady</hi> begin with a single leaf.<lb/>The reason must be that the numbers of the epistles on the dropped heads (‘<hi rend="smallcaps">EPISTLE I</hi>’ etc.<lb/>as in figure 8) had to be changed, and that was done by supplying a new leaf.<note n="42">Possibly the ‘Taste’ poems were originally to precede the ‘Characters’ ones (though the ‘Opus Magnum’ list, published by mistake in some copies of <hi>An Essay on Man</hi> on 2 May 1734, has the present order). <hi>To a Lady</hi> was not published until 8 February 1735 and so its printing in the <hi>Works</hi> could be run on from <hi>To Cobham</hi> with the appropriate number.</note><lb/>The present first page of quarto <hi>To Cobham</hi>, therefore, was printed at a late stage, but before the type was rearranged for the folio.<lb/>The page lacks line numbers on both recto and verso and it has two readings corrected in the Errata: line 9 ‘the fate of all Extremes are such’ and line 14 ‘those from Guess’.<lb/>The large paper folio catches and corrects the first but not the second of these.<lb/>The quarto page must then have been printed just too early to catch the revised headpiece.<lb/>If it had not been printed quite so hastily, we might never have seen the adapted <hi>Odyssey</hi> ornament.</p>
<p>The adapted headpiece in the quarto <hi>To Cobham</hi> (figure 8) comes from <hi>Odyssey</hi> Book V.<lb/>Savage is surely right in suggesting that Kent’s original decision to represent Calypso’s cave as a grotto was intended as a tribute to Pope; his own sketches of Pope and his grotto are celebrated.<note n="43">Nos.&amp;nbsp;14–16 in W.&amp;nbsp;K.&amp;nbsp;Wimsatt, <hi>The Portraits of Alexander Pope</hi>, 119–25.</note><lb/>The central circle in which Ulysses was building his ship has been replaced by a simplified version of Cobham’s arms, though Mercury, flying to bring Jupiter’s message, is still visible to the left.<lb/>The replacement engraving (figure 9), which does bear Kent’s initials, is more straightforwardly heraldic.<lb/>Whereas in the adapted engraving the shield has only one eagle displayed, the new one has quartered arms with the eagles displayed in the first and fourth quarter.<lb/>Although it is not altogether clear, the second and third quarters have two bars each, charged with three martlets.<lb/>Sir Bernard Burke says these are the arms of the kingdom of Mercia, borne by the family since the Temples were earls of Mercia.<note n="44"><hi>The General Armory of England, Scotland, Ireland and Wales</hi> (London: Harrison, 1884), s.n. The arms were illustrated in Guillim, <hi>A Display of Heraldry</hi>, after p.&amp;nbsp;2120, no.&amp;nbsp;11.</note><lb/>But although the shield is heraldically correct, the supporters are not.<lb/>The lions rampant on the adapted <hi>Odyssey</hi> headpiece have been replaced by the putti of the ‘<hi rend="smallcaps">UNI ÆQVVS VIRTVTI ATQ. EIVS AMICI</hi>’ ornament.<lb/>Temple’s aristocratic dignity is playfully surrounded by symbols of friendship.</p>
<p>The putti will reappear as supporters on the ornament that concludes <hi>To Oxford</hi>, but the next two poems.<lb/><hi>To a Lady</hi> and <hi>To Bathurst</hi> lack heraldic ornaments, though <hi>To a Lady</hi> concludes with the <hi>Odyssey</hi> fountain engraving.<lb/>I have no explanation for the non-appearance of Bathurst’s arms.<lb/>His poem has no engravings, and neither does <hi>To Burlington</hi> in the quarto, but in the large-paper folio <hi>To Burlington</hi> concludes with an ornament that was obviously designed by Kent (who initials it) as a headpiece (figure 10).<lb/>The Greek key molding that provides a platform for the design is characteristic of many of the <hi>Odyssey</hi> headpieces, including figure 6, as is the firm oblong shape of the plate, occupying the width of the page.<lb/>I think Pope uses this headpiece (and the one for <hi>To Oxford</hi>) as a tailpiece in order</p>
<pb n="207"/>
<p>to prepare for the presentation of his father’s arms at the end of To Arbuthnot, <lb/>where it constitutes a conclusion to his argument and self-presentation. Although <lb/>the Burlington ornament lacks the putti as supporters, Kent has again substituted <lb/>his own ideas. Burlington’s funerary monument at Londesborough church shows <lb/>the same shield but the supporters are a rampant lion and a dog.<note n="45">45. There is a good image (accessed 22&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;2024) at http://www.britainexpress.com/ <lb/>attractions.htm?attraction=4631 <lb/>The Burlington arms are illustrated in simplified form in Guillim, Art of Heraldry, after p.&amp;nbsp;104, no.&amp;nbsp;32. Kent includes the motto of the Order of the Garter (‘Honi soit qui mal y pense’) <lb/>to reflect Burlington’s knighthood in the order (June&amp;nbsp;1730).</note> Here in the Works, where the supporters should be, are wreathed roundels containing heads <lb/>in profile. Pope’s poem celebrates Burlington’s publication of Palladio’s Designs of <lb/>the Baths, Arches, Theatres, &amp;c. of Ancient Rome, that is, Fabbriche antiche disegnate da <lb/>Andrea Palladio Vicentino (1730), and Kent balances Andrea Palladio on the left <lb/>with Inigo Jones on the right, just as the outer staircase at Chiswick House does, <lb/>with statues.<note n="46">46. Toby Barnard and Jane Clark (eds.), Lord Burlington: Architecture, Art and Life (London: Hambledon Press, 1995), figs.&amp;nbsp;1a and 1b.</note> Burlington, very much the aristocrat, takes his place at the centre <lb/>of a trio of architects, their status as artists balanced by his authority as a scholar. <lb/>Although the image of Jones bears some resemblance to the much-copied por- <lb/>trait by Van Dyck in the Hermitage, that of Palladio bears closer resemblance <lb/>to Kent himself.<note n="47">47. The National Portrait Gallery has many engravings based on Van Dyck, of which NPG&amp;nbsp;D28334 is typical, while Kent is in his familiar turban in NPG&amp;nbsp;1557.</note></p>
<figure>
  <head><hi rend="smallcaps">figure&amp;nbsp;10.</hi></head>
  <figDesc>New tailpiece to To Burlington, Works&amp;nbsp;II folio.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<pb n="208"/>
<figure>
  <head><hi rend="italic">figure 11</hi>. New tailpiece to <hi rend="italic">To Oxford</hi>, Works II quarto.</head>
  
  <figDesc>Engraved tailpiece showing a heraldic shield flanked by two cherubs with the motto “VIRTUTE ET FIDE”, reproduced from Pope’s Works II quarto.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">‘To Mr. Addison’</hi>, which in the quarto immediately follows the poem to Bur-<lb/>
lington, has a preceding row of flowers and a concluding tailpiece from <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi><lb/>
Book I. The engraving represents an eagle with Minerva’s spear and helmet,<lb/>
evoking lines quoted by Nicholas Savage:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Abrupt, with eagle-speed she cut the sky;<lb/>
Instant invisible to mortal eye . . .</hi><note n="48"><hi rend="italic">The Odyssey</hi>, ed. Maynard Mack, et al., 2 vols (London: Methuen, 1967), Twickenham, 9:52, lines 413–14.</note><lb/>
Although <hi rend="italic">To Addison</hi> has a line on eagles, ‘And little Eagles wave their wings in<lb/>
gold’ (30), the tailpiece eagle is not little and if an engraving was to be chosen to<lb/>
reflect the poem it would surely have been <hi rend="smallcaps">UNI ÆQVVS VIRTVTI ATQ. EIVS<lb/>
AMICI</hi>, where Pope is himself depicted on a medal and the embracing cherubs<lb/>
reflect the relationship in the poem’s most famous lines:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The verse and sculpture bore an equal part,<lb/>
And Art reflected images to Art.</hi><note n="49">‘To Mr. Addison, Occasioned by his Dialogue on Medals’, lines 51–2, in <hi rend="italic">Minor Poems</hi>, ed. Norman Ault and John Butt (London: Methuen, rev. repr. 1964), Twickenham, 6:204. ‘Sculpture’ here refers to engraving and shaping of medals.</note><lb/>
I suspect the choice of <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> tailpiece on this occasion was casual.<lb/>
The tailpiece to the following poem, <hi rend="italic">To Oxford</hi>, however, is one of the new<lb/>
Kent headpieces functioning as a tailpiece (<hi rend="italic">figure 11</hi>). As usual Kent does not</p>
<pb n="209"/>
<figure>
  <figDesc>Figure 12. New tailpiece to <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II quarto.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
include a crest (in Oxford’s case it would have been, rather excessively, a castle,<lb/>
triple-towered, with a lion emerging from the middle tower) but he does keep<lb/>
both the Garter motto, encircling the shield, as in Burlington’s arms, and Ox-<lb/>
ford’s own motto. In the most striking adjustment, however, he has replaced<lb/>
the tall, adult angels who are formally supporters with the two putti that have<lb/>
become customary for the volume. Oxford too is embraced as a friend.<note n="50">Oxford’s arms are illustrated by Guillim, <hi rend="italic">A Display of Heraldry</hi>, after p. 2104, no. 62. In this image he has only the bend cotised and not the lions passants, but they appear in a gold seal ring, the image of which (accessed 22&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;2024) is to be found here: https://www.pinterest.com/pin/458874649513741270/?from_navigate=true. The Mortimer arms, which consisted of fesses, or horizontal stripes, seem not to be present.</note><lb/>
The final poem in the second book of epistles, <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi>, brings the serious<lb/>
heraldry of the volume to a close with a large engraving of Pope’s father’s arms,<lb/>
or Pope’s idea of them (figure 12). This heraldic engraving reveals the purpose of<lb/>
the others by including Pope himself in the distinguished group of friends. The<lb/>
<pb n="210"/>
<p>general nature of this engraving was first identified by Howard Erskine-Hill, who<lb/>
suggested it was ‘heraldically competent, but does not purport to be Pope’s own<lb/>
coat of arms’<note n="51">‘Review of James McLaverty, <hi rend="italic">Pope, Print, and Meaning</hi>’, <hi rend="italic">Review of English Studies</hi>, 220 (2004) 462–5 (465).</note>. I am sympathetic to the desire to absolve Pope from the sin of<lb/>
misrepresentation – he was not using it formally or claiming he had approval<lb/>
from the College of Heralds – but I think this must nevertheless be a serious and<lb/>
important claim about his family and its status. Sir Anthony Wagner in his study<lb/>
of the arms of outstanding figures from the history of the United Kingdom names<lb/>
Pope as one of those who were not armigerous, but he also points to Joshua<lb/>
Reynolds and John Locke as among those who used arms ‘but without apparent<lb/>
right.’<note n="52">Wagner, <hi rend="italic">Historic Heraldry of Britain</hi>, 13. I am most grateful to Mr David White, then Somerset Herald, now Garter King of Arms, who in a short correspondence kindly directed me to this reference and also pointed out that the arms in <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi> were those of a married man. However, Wagner’s recording of Jonathan Swift’s armigerous uncle Godwin as his brother suggests Wagner’s is not an altogether thorough study of literary figures.</note> Pope used them, I suspect, only in the specific context of this poem, and<lb/>
it may not have mattered to him at all that they were not ratified by a College<lb/>
that served a regime he did not respect. In so advertising his family, Pope may<lb/>
have recollected the introduction by Caleb D’Anvers to his family history in<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Craftsman</hi> 28 (13 March 1727): ‘Though it is generally esteem’d an indecent, as<lb/>
well as an invidious Task, for a Man to mention himself, or extol his own Fam-<lb/>
ily; yet in some Cases it becomes not only excusable, but even praise-worthy;<lb/>
especially when it is made necessary for our Self-defence’. D’Anvers goes on to<lb/>
associate his family’s place in ‘Books of Heraldry’ with a patriotism ‘exposed to<lb/>
“Obloquy and Reproach”’<note n="53"><hi rend="italic">The Craftsman</hi>, 14 vols (London, 1731), 1:166.</note>.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi> clearly responds to the attacks on Pope by Lord Hervey, or Lady<lb/>
Mary Wortley Montagu, or both, in <hi rend="italic">Verses Address’d to the Imitator of Horace</hi> (March<lb/>
1733) and by Hervey in <hi rend="italic">An Epistle from a Nobleman to a Doctor of Divinity</hi> (November<lb/>
1733). Pope says as much in the ‘Advertisement’ prefixed to the first edition; his<lb/>
notes to <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi> refer to the <hi rend="italic">Verses</hi>; and a new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Verses</hi> seems to<lb/>
have been printed especially to accompany <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi> in January 1735. The<lb/>
heraldic image at the end of <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi> responds to a particular attack on him<lb/>
in the <hi rend="italic">Verses</hi>:<lb/>
none thy crabbed Numbers can endure,<lb/>
Hard as thy Heart, and as thy Birth obscure.<note n="54"><hi rend="italic">The Collected Verse of John, Lord Hervey (1696–1743)</hi>, ed. Bill Overton et al. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2016), 182, lines 16–17.</note><lb/>
In an ‘Advertisement’ prefixed to the first edition of <hi rend="italic">An Epistle from Mr. Pope to<lb/>
Dr. Arbuthnot</hi> which was substantially repeated in the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> Pope says he had no<lb/>
thought of publishing the poem<lb/>
till it pleas’d some Persons of Rank and Fortune to attack in a very extraordinary manner,<lb/>
not only his <hi rend="italic">Writings</hi>, but his <hi rend="italic">Morals</hi>, Person, and <hi rend="italic">Family</hi>: of which he therefore thought<lb/>
himself obliged to give some account. (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, 212)<note n="55">John Butt prints the ‘Advertisement’ to the first edition in <hi rend="italic">Twickenham</hi>, 4:95.</note><lb/>
</p>
<pb n="211"/>
<p>
And to the lines<lb/>
Let the two Curls of Town and Court, abuse<lb/>
His Father, Mother, Body, Soul, and Muse (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, 76, lines 372–3)<lb/>
he added a long note:<lb/>
In some of Curl’s and other Pamphlets, Mr. Pope’s Father was said to be a Mechanic, a Hatter, a Farmer, nay a Bankrupt. But what is stranger, a Nobleman (if such a Reflection can be thought to come from a Nobleman) has dropt an Allusion to this pitiful Untruth, in his Epistle to a Doctor of Divinity: And the following Line,<lb/>
Hard as thy Heart, and as thy Birth Obscure,<lb/>
has fallen from a like Courtly pen, in the Verses to the Imitator of Horace. Mr. Pope’s Father was of a Gentleman’s Family in Oxfordshire, the Head of which was the Earl of Downe, whose sole Heiress married the Earl of Lindsey—His Mother was the Daughter of William Turnor, Esq; of York: she had three Brothers, one of whom was kill’d, another died in the Service of King Charles; the eldest following his Fortunes, and becoming a General Officer in Spain, left her what Estate remain’d after the Sequestrations and Forfeitures of her Family. —Mr. Pope died in 1717, aged 75; She in 1733, aged 93, a very few Weeks after this Poem was finished. The following Inscription was placed by their Son on their Monument, in the Parish of Twickenham, in Middlesex.<lb/>
D. O. M.<lb/>
Alexandro Pope Viro Innocuo,<lb/>
Probo, Pio, Qui vixit annos Lxxv, ob. Mdccvii.<lb/>
Et EdithÆ Conjungi Inculpabili, PientissimÆ,<lb/>
QuÆ vixit annos Xciii, ob. Mdccxxxiii.<lb/>
Parentibus Benemerentibus Filius Fecit, et Sibi.<lb/>
(<hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II, 214)<lb/>
The impression given by Pope’s note is reinforced by the engraving. The central shield is quite a small part of the design. On it the arms of his father’s family are impaled with those of his mother’s, as those families are identified in the note to the poem. The dextra has the arms of the Oxfordshire Pope family to which the Earl of Downe belonged. In Guillim’s <hi rend="italic">A Display of Heraldry</hi> (1724), 183, they appear under Baronets: ‘Sir William Pope of Wilcot in Oxfordshire, Kt. since an Irish Earl, viz. Earl of Downe. Parted per Pale [halved vertically], Or and Azure [gold and blue], on a Chevron between three Griffins Heads erased [torn off], four Fleurs de Lys, all Counterchanged [reversing colours]’. The engraving has only three fleurs-de-lis, but Kent probably felt pressed for space.<note n="56">Sir Bernard Burke, <hi rend="italic">The General Armory of England, Scotland, Ireland, and Wales</hi> (London, 1884), s.n. agrees about the four fleurs-de-lis and adds a crest of griffins’ heads.</note><lb/>
The sinister has the arms of the Turnor or Turner family. They are illustrated and described<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="212"/>
<p>in Guillim, 323: ‘He beareth Ermines, on a Cross quarter pierced Argent [silver],<lb/>four Fer-de-molines sable [black millrind crosses], by the Name of Turner; and is<lb/>the Coat-Armour of Sir Edward Turner of Parendon in Essex, Kt. Chief Baron of<lb/>his Majesty’s Court of Exchequer’. Sir Bernard Burke in the <hi rend="italic">General<lb/>Armory</hi> has similar arms for the Turnor family of Stoke Rochford in Lincolnshire<lb/>but has five fers-de-molines for the Turner family of York. Again, Pope and Kent<lb/>may not have been concerned for details; no crest has been supplied for the coat of<lb/>arms.<note n="57">Sir Bernard Burke has a crest with a lion holding a fer-de-moline, s.n.</note><lb/><lb/>Kent has supplied his design with the usual foliage, but the putti are absent. This<lb/>is a memorial to Pope’s parents and to right and left are what I take to be torches,<lb/>signifying Pope’s devotion to his family home and values, flames that he keeps<lb/>alive. The motto, ‘HEU PIETAS HEU PRISCA FIDES’, is a quotation from Book VI<lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi> (line 878) where Anchises laments the early death of<lb/>Marcellus, ‘a youth of passing beauty in resplendent arms’. The Loeb translation is<lb/>‘Alas for his goodness! alas for his chivalrous honour’, but in this context it might<lb/>be ‘Alas for faithfulness to natural ties and duty! Alas for old faith!’<note n="58">Virgil, trans. H. Rushton Fairclough, rev. G. P. Goold, 2 vols (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1999), 1:594, lines VI.861 and 878. Unfortunately the engraver for the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> has misunderstood his instructions: all the copies seen read ‘PLETAS’.</note><lb/><lb/>The engraving unquestionably represents Pope’s commitment to his family, its<lb/>values, and its religion, even though he and his friends find themselves in a form<lb/>of internal exile. The original context of the quotation gives it a curious<lb/>doubleness: the lament is for Pope’s parents but also, through the allusion to<lb/>Marcellus, for their love of him. The motto and the grandeur of the engraving<lb/>counterbalance the simple ‘Et Sibi’ designed for Pope’s own place on his parents’<lb/>monument in Twickenham church. Ironically, in a poem famous for its<lb/>condemnation of Addison, the words had been used as the epigraph for the<lb/><hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> paper recording the death of Sir Roger de Coverly.<note n="59"><hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, ed. D. F. Bond, 5 vols (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1965), 4:339 (No. 517, 23 October 1712).</note><lb/><lb/>The two Horatian satires that follow <hi rend="italic">To Arbuthnot</hi> have the same<lb/>illustrations as in the separate quarto, Satire II.i bringing its picture of Pope’s life<lb/>to a close with the ‘UNI ÆQVVS VIRTVTI ATQ. EIVS AMICI’ vignette. The Donne<lb/>satires that follow have simply two closing tailpieces from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>,<lb/>Proteus from Book IV, here half a boar (lines 617–18), and the familiar siren. The<lb/>section <hi rend="italic">Epitaphs</hi> that comes between the epistles and satires and the<lb/><hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>, however, has an appropriate headpiece from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, that<lb/>from Book I (the initial from Book IV) where Phemius is depicted singing ‘the<lb/>direful woes Which voyaging from Troy the Victors bore’ and is rebuked by<lb/>Penelope, ‘ev’ry piercing note inflicts a wound’ (Twickenham, 9:53, lines I.422–3,<lb/>440). It now has on it ‘DIS MANIBUS’, short for ‘dis manibus sacrum’, meaning<lb/>‘sacred to the ghost gods’ or ‘in memory of ’. This is a case of skilful<lb/>appropriation. Two pages later a tailpiece of an altar with a bucranium and<lb/>trident evokes ‘King Nestor’s sacrifice of a heifer to Pallas Athene’<note n="60">Savage, ‘Kent as Book Illustrator’, 423. The tailpiece comes from <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, Book III.</note> and<lb/>reinforces the sombre mood.<lb/><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> that begins the fourth and final main section of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi><lb/>II quarto provides new illustrations developing the motifs found in the<lb/>Variorum edition of<lb/></p>
<pb n="213"/>
<p><lb/>These engravings provide the heraldry of the dunces, as Mengel and Savage have demonstrated in their important essays. The headpiece to the first book of the Dunciad Variorum is now used again as a tailpiece at the end of the Arguments, at the end of Book I, at the end of Book II, and at the end of the notes to Book II. Each book of the quarto, however, has a new headpiece. The first picks up the asses and owl motif from the Variorum headpiece, and, in a mockery of the Odyssey’s harps and lyres, has asses playing their instruments with their hoofs, while an owl in a bow tie admires himself in a mirror. The engraving, in an Odyssey-like elaborate frame – the Variorum headpiece did not have a frame – conjures up a world of elaborate narcissistic self-congratulation. In the nearby initial, repeated in Book III, a creature Engel and Savage take to be a mole attempts to read with the help of spectacles.<note n="61">I am inclined to think it is a monkey, modelled on Dürer’s watercolour in the monastery of El Escorial.</note> At the beginning of Book II comes a headpiece with its central circle devoted to one of Orator Henley’s medals, with Henley or Curl pictured in the stocks. The initial on this page has Mercury’s caduceus crowned with a fools’ cap. The final headpiece refers to the pantomimes criticized in the poem, with harlequin submitted by a monster to a perverse pattern of death and birth. Dr. Joseph Hone, of the University of Newcastle, points out to me with characteristic generosity that the monster is modelled on that of Hogarth’s ‘Masquerades and Operas’ (1724). Kent, himself Hogarth’s butt in that engraving, joins himself to the critique of popular culture.<lb/><lb/>The story of the engravings to Works II is, then, a sad one of missed opportunity. Pope had a theme for his collection that could be represented first by heraldic headpieces and then by mock-heraldry. He had a brilliant if eccentric designer in William Kent, who was willing to share his interests and to celebrate their collaboration, but because of the hand-to-mouth way of proceeding with the compilation of the volume – Lawton Gilliver and John Wright were very closely supervised and afflicted with changes of plan and improvised solutions – Pope’s conception was not fully realized. And the Odyssey tailpieces, bold and ingenious as they were, distracted attention from the thematically conceived illustrations. If Pope and Lintot had not quarrelled so seriously over the Odyssey, we might have had a better book.<lb/></p>
<head>Postscript: The Afterlife of a Mercury Plate</head>
<p><lb/>Pope’s use of these engraved ornaments did not end with the 1735 edition of Works II. They appeared in individual publications and in the prose works, and the treatment of a Mercury tailpiece (figure 13), shown here from its appearance in Pope’s quarto Prose Works II, 1741 (Griffith 531), p. 1, is particularly intriguing. This engraving was not actually used in the Odyssey. It might have been intended originally as the tailpiece to conclude the final book (which begins with Mercury leading the souls of the suitors ‘to the eternal shades’), only to be replaced by the Pope medallion. It appears without a ribbon or lettering at the end of The First Epistle of the First Book of Horace in Poems and Imitations of Horace (Griffith 504),<lb/></p>
<pb n="214"/>
<figure>
 <figDesc>figure 13. Mercury engraving (no ribbon); headpiece (p. 1) to The Works of Mr. Alexander<lb/>Pope in Prose, Volume II, quarto (1741).</figDesc>
 
</figure>
<figure>
 <figDesc>figure 14. Mercury engraving (ribbon with inscription); headpiece (Preface) to<lb/>Letters of Mr. Alexander Pope and Several of His Friends, quarto (1737).</figDesc>
 
</figure>
<figure>
 <figDesc>figure 15. Mercury engraving (blank ribbon); tailpiece to Key to the Lock in The Works of<lb/>Mr. Alexander Pope in Prose, Volume II, quarto (1741).</figDesc>
 
</figure>
<pb n="215"/>
<p>published, Griffith says, on 11 January 1739, but dated 1738. There it faces the<lb/>
second Bolingbroke headpiece from the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, which was appropriate because<lb/>
Bolingbroke was the <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi>’s addressee. That volume (Griffith 504) was designed<lb/>
to enable purchasers of the 1735 <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> quarto to update their collection, and<lb/>
used sheets from Griffith 490 (<hi rend="italic">Epistles of Horace Imitated</hi>), which Griffith thinks was<lb/>
published in May 1738.<note n="62">The first edition, Griffith 480, which does not have the engravings (perhaps because there is no room for them) and does not begin with St.&amp;nbsp;John’s name, has 1737 on the title page and was published on 7 March.</note> There are only two surviving copies of Griffith 490,<lb/>
so it may be unwise to allow it too much weight, but other evidence points to<lb/>
these sheets having been printed by May 1737. The Mercury engraving appears<lb/>
again above the Preface to the quarto and large-paper folio <hi rend="italic">Letters of Mr.&amp;nbsp;Alexander Pope, and Several of his Friends</hi> (Griffith 454 and 456), the official edition of<lb/>
Pope’s correspondence, published on 19 May 1737, but here the engraving has<lb/>
been given a ribbon running across the bottom of the image, with the inscription<lb/>
‘Vellem Nescire Litteras!’, Nero’s response when required to sign a death war-<lb/>
rant, ‘Would that I had never learned to write’ (figure 14).<note n="63">The story is told by Suetonius, ‘Nero’, <hi rend="italic">Suetonius</hi>, trans.&amp;nbsp;J.&amp;nbsp;C.&amp;nbsp;Rolfe, 2 vols (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1914), 2:101 (§X).</note> The Preface ends<lb/>
with more evidence of the willingness to change engravings at this point, with an<lb/>
adaptation of the Oxford tailpiece from the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, the putti now supporting a<lb/>
central circle that once held Oxford’s arms but now has an inscription in capitals,<lb/>
the oddity of the breaks showing the space was not designed for the inscription:<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">CVM.DESIDE.<lb/>
RIO.VETERES.<lb/>
REVOCAMVS.AMO<lb/>
RES.<lb/>
ATQUE.OLIM.MIS<lb/>
SAS.&amp;nbsp;FLEMVS.<lb/>
AMICITIAS.</hi><note n="64">‘The regret with which we recall our old loves, and weep for long-lost friendships’, <hi rend="italic">Catullus</hi>, XCVI [‘Ad Calvum de Quintilia’], lines 3–4 (<hi rend="italic">Catullus, Tibullus, Pervigilium Veneris</hi>, trans.&amp;nbsp;F.&amp;nbsp;W.&amp;nbsp;Cornish, J.&amp;nbsp;P.&amp;nbsp;Postgate, and J.&amp;nbsp;W.&amp;nbsp;Mackail, 2nd edn, rev.&amp;nbsp;G.&amp;nbsp;P.&amp;nbsp;Goold (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1962), 168–9). The Loeb text and others I have consulted read ‘renovamus’ (renew, give new life to).</note><lb/>
<lb/>
The same engraving is repeated above the first letter.<lb/>
<lb/>
By May 1737, therefore, the Mercury ornament had been changed, which<lb/>
means that the quarto sheets of the <hi rend="italic">First Epistle of the First Book</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Epistles of<lb/>
Horace Imitated</hi> must have been printed before that date. So too had been the<lb/>
version of the <hi rend="italic">Key to the Lock</hi> that appeared in <hi rend="italic">The Works of Mr.&amp;nbsp;Alexander Pope in<lb/>
Prose, Volume II</hi> in 1741 (Griffith 530–1), where the Mercury engraving appears<lb/>
at the end of the piece in an intermediate state, with its ribbon but without the<lb/>
lettering (figure 15). The <hi rend="italic">Key</hi> was printed, therefore, after the sheets of <hi rend="italic">Epistles of<lb/>
Horace Imitated</hi>.</p>
<pb n="216"/>
<p><lb/>Horace Imitated but before the Preface to the 1737 Letters.<note n="65">David Foxon thinks it was intended with other prose pieces for the 1735 Works (Pope and the Early Eighteenth-Century Book Trade, 133), but that now seems unlikely. The First Epistle of the First Book of Horace would not have been ready in 1735.</note><lb/>But by far the most surprising appearance of this Mercury engraving is in its original unribboned<lb/>and unlettered state at the beginning of the letters in the 1741 volume, The Works<lb/>of Mr. Alexander Pope in Prose, Volume II (Griffith 530–1) (figure 13). It would be<lb/>expected to appear in the same revised state as it had at the beginning of the<lb/>1737 Letters. It forms the headpiece to a letter from Pope to Swift of 18 June 1714.<lb/>Lord Orrery had left Dublin on 5 July 1737, according to Sherburn, bringing<lb/>with him Pope’s letters to Swift. He wrote to Swift saying Pope had the letters on<lb/>23 July 1737.<note n="66">Correspondence, 4:81.</note> But this evidence of the plain engraving suggests that Pope had<lb/>already started printing his letters to Swift before the engraving appeared in its<lb/>enhanced form in the Letters on 19 May 1737. In a case like this, the engraving<lb/>affords valuable bibliographical evidence. Examination on the Traherne collator<lb/>does not suggest there were two engravings, and such duplication would in any<lb/>case be most unlikely. The whole affair of the publication of the Pope and Swift<lb/>letters clearly invites further investigation, as does the rest of Pope’s printing in<lb/>quarto and folio in the summer of 1737, but it is difficult to avoid the conclusion<lb/>that Pope had printed some of his letters to Swift before July 1737; perhaps he<lb/>had saved copies of them; perhaps he made them up.</p>
<pb n="217"/>
<pb n="218"/>
<p>
<lb/>Location Format Design and Source
<lb/>Burlington, p. 49 (44) 4o No engraving
<lb/>2o New tailpiece with Burlington arms in central circle [Fig. 10]
<lb/>Addison, p. 53 (48) 4o, 2o Helmeted eagle Tailpiece from Odyssey I
<lb/>Oxford, p. 56 (51) 4o, 2o New tailpiece with Oxford arms in central circle [Fig. 11]
<lb/>Arbuthnot, p. 78 (72) 4o, 2o New tailpiece with arms of Pope’s father [Fig. 12]
<lb/>Satires
<lb/>Horace, Satire 2:1
<lb/>p. 18 (16) 4o Altar with Minerva Tailpiece from Odyssey XVII
<lb/>2o No engraving
<lb/>p. 19 (17) 4o Oval vignette, 69mm Works title page
<lb/>2o No engraving
<lb/>Horace, Satire 2:2
<lb/>p. 40 (36) 4o, 2o Mulius’s goblet Tailpiece from Odyssey XVIII
<lb/>Donne, Satire 4
<lb/>p. 86 (90) 4o, 2o Proteus Tailpiece from Odyssey IV
<lb/>p. 87 (91) 4o, 2o Siren Tailpiece from Odyssey VI
<lb/>Epitaphs
<lb/>Trumbal, p. 3 (3) 4o, 2o Harpist Headpiece from Odyssey I; initial ‘A’ (48 x 48mm) from Odyssey IV [Fig. 1]
<lb/>Dorset, p. 5 (5) 4o Altar Tailpiece from Odyssey III
<lb/>2o No engraving
<lb/>Dunciad
<lb/>Argument, p.19 (‘81’) 4o Owl and asses ‘Nemo’ headpiece from Dunciad Variorum (Foxon P771 etc.), used as tailpiece
<lb/>2o Burdened ass Title page of Dunciad Variorum (Foxon P771 etc.)
<lb/>Book I, p. 1 (1) 4o, 2o Owl &amp; harping asses New headpiece; new initial ‘B’ with mole reading
<lb/>Book I, p. 14 (13) 4o Owl and asses ‘Nemo’ headpiece from Dunciad Variorum (Foxon P771 etc.), used as tailpiece
<lb/>2o Burdened ass Title page of Dunciad Variorum (Foxon P771 etc.)
</p>
<pb n="219"/>
<p>
<lb/>Book II, p. 15 (14) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Head in stocks New headpiece; new initial ‘H’
<lb/>with fool’s cap on caduceus
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> No engraving
<lb/>Book II, p. 35 (32) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Owl and asses ‘Nemo’ headpiece from
<lb/>Dunciad Variorum (Foxon P771
<lb/>etc.), used as tailpiece [Fig. 3]
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> No engraving
<lb/>Book III, p. 36 (33) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Harlequin New headpiece; initial ‘B’ with
<lb/>mole reading, from Book I
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> No engraving
<lb/>Book III, p. 54 (49) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Boar Tailpiece from Odyssey XIV
<lb/>Declaration, p. 56 (52) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Eagle carrying bird Tailpiece from Odyssey XV
<lb/>Scriblerus, p. 61 (57) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> No engraving
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Owl &amp; harping asses Headpiece from Book I
<lb/>Notes, p. 115 (107) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Boar Tailpiece from Odyssey XIV
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Burdened ass Title page of Dunciad Variorum
<lb/>(Foxon P771 etc.)
<lb/>Notes, p. 149 (138) 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Owl and asses ‘Nemo’ headpiece from
<lb/>Dunciad Variorum (Foxon
<lb/>P771 etc.), used as tailpiece
<lb/>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> No engraving
</p>
<pb n="220"/>
</div>