<div type="section" n="6">
  <head>Jonathan Richardson, Charles Chauncy, & the Manuscripts of Pope by John Considine</head>
<pb n="221"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">JONATHAN RICHARDSON, CHARLES CHAUNCY, AND<lb/>THE MANUSCRIPTS OF POPE</hi></head><lb/>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">John Considine</name><note n="*">I am grateful to Karen Thomson, who helped me to start thinking about this topic, and to James McLaverty, for his valuable comments on a draft.</note></byline><lb/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">A</hi>s for his <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>’, recalled the man of letters Jonathan Richardson the younger, in a volume of reflections published in&amp;nbsp;1776, five years after his death,<lb/>I was witness to the whole conduct of it in writing, and actually have his original MSS. for it, from the first scratches of the four books, to the several finished copies, (of his own neat and elegant writing these last) all which, with the MS. of his <hi rend="italic">Essay on Criticism</hi>, and several of his other works, he gave me himself, for the pains I took in collating the whole with its printed editions, at his request, on my having proposed to him the ‘making of an edition of his works in the manner of <hi rend="italic">Boileau</hi>’<note n="1">Jonathan Richardson, <hi rend="italic">Richardsoniana, or, Occasional Reflections on the Moral Nature of Man</hi> (London: Printed for J.&amp;nbsp;Dodsley, 1776), 264; for Pope and the Richardsons, see William Kurtz Wimsatt, <hi rend="italic">The Portraits of Alexander Pope</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1965), 73–89 and 137–222, esp.&amp;nbsp;142–143; Helene Koon, ‘Pope’s First Editors’, <hi rend="italic">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 35.1 (1971), 19–27; and James McLaverty, <hi rend="italic">Pope, Print, and Meaning</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2001), 212–213; for Pope and Boileau, see McLaverty, op.&amp;nbsp;cit., 87–90, 210–214.</note>.<lb/>
The literary manuscripts which Pope gave to Richardson <hi rend="italic">include</hi>, as Margaret Smith remarks in the <hi rend="italic">Index of English Literary Manuscripts</hi>, ‘some of the most important surviving MSS&amp;nbsp;of Pope’<note n="2">Margaret M.&amp;nbsp;Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, in eadem and Alexander Lindsay, <hi rend="italic">Index of English Literary Manuscripts</hi>, vol.&amp;nbsp;3, 1700–1800, part 3, <hi rend="italic">Alexander Pope–Sir Richard Steele</hi> (London: Mansell, 1992), 1–78 at 2.</note>.<lb/>They were, as we shall see, accompanied in Richardson’s library by collated printed editions of Pope and some non-literary manuscripts. Their movements for a century and more after Richardson’s death have been summed up — not quite accurately — by Maynard Mack: they ‘made their way, without ever going on public sale, into the collection of Charles Chauncy, and finally, in 1887, to the marketplace’, the last point being minimally elaborated on in an endnote which reads ‘See the Sotheby sale catalogue, July 1887’<note n="3">Maynard Mack, <hi rend="italic">Collected in Himself: Essays Critical, Biographical, and Bibliographical on Pope and Some of his Contemporaries</hi> (East Brunswick, NJ: Associated University Presses, 1982), 325, 346 n 24.</note>.<lb/>Charles Chauncy was a near-contemporary of Richardson the younger’s, a rich English physician and antiquary; the name is also spelt Chauncey, as in the <hi rend="italic">Oxford DNB</hi> and several of the sources quoted below.</p>
<pb n="222"/>
<p>
The impressive terseness of Mack’s account has led to its being overlooked.<lb/>
For instance, Smith’s IELM entry records that ‘The first major dispersal of<lb/>
Pope’s MSS in the salerooms did not occur until the W. Nassau Lees Sale, at<lb/>
Christie’s, 20 [sc. 30] July 1889’ (2), and gives an account only of the sub-set of<lb/>
the Chauncy manuscripts which reached that sale, two years after the one which<lb/>
Mack mentions. Likewise, the current online catalogue record for the Morgan<lb/>
Library manuscript MA 348, the first extant draft of the ‘Essay on Man’, reads<lb/>
‘Presented by Pope to Jonathan Richardson (1694 –1771); Dr. Charles Chauncey,<lb/>
and by descent in his family until at least 1860; General William Nassau Lees; his<lb/>
sale (Christie’s, 30 July 1889, lot 79)’. Moreover, the Sotheby catalogue of 1887<lb/>
to which Mack refers the reader is not widely available, and although it tells us<lb/>
much about the Richardson–Chauncy manuscripts of Pope, it does not tell the<lb/>
full story. The following is therefore the first full account of the eighteenth- and<lb/>
nineteenth-century career of the most important group of manuscripts of Pope.<lb/>
</p>
<head>I</head>
<p>
Richardson evidently retained the manuscripts which Pope had given him until<lb/>
his death. They were sold in April 1776, by Baker and Leigh, with three associ­<lb/>
ated lots.<note n="4">A Catalogue of the Very Large and Valuable Library of Doctor John Campbell ... To Which is Added, Some Original Letters of Mr. Pope to Mr. Richardson of Queen’s Square, and also Many of his Works with his own Manuscript Corrections (London: for S. Baker and G. Leigh, 1776), 99 [reproduced in the microfilm series Sotheby Catalogues, part I, reel 6 of 71].</note> The catalogue describes the four lots as follows:<lb/>
</p>
<p>
3170  Two Copper Plates of Mr. Pope’s Head, one in a Circle, the other in a<lb/>
Whig [sic], by Richardson,<note n="5">Unidentified: Richardson the elder made a number of etched portraits of Pope, for which see Wimsatt, Portraits of Alexander Pope, 178 –200. Cf. William Gregson, writing in or shortly after December 1775, in George Sherburn, ‘New Anecdotes about Alexander Pope’, Notes &amp; Queries 203 (1958), 343 –349 at 346: ‘I have the plates of several of Mr Popes Heads, Sketch’d by my Grandfather [Richardson the elder], the best Proof I think is bound up, as Frontispiece to his Works.’</note><lb/>
3171  Most of Mr. Pope’s Poems in their first Sketches in his own hand Writing,<lb/>
and some first Editions corrected,<lb/>
3172  Mr. Pope’s Pastorals, Manuscript, neatly wrote,<lb/>
N. B. This Copy is that which passed through the Hands of Walsh, Congreave,<lb/>
Mainwaring, Garth, Granville, Southerne, Sir W. Trumbull, Lord Halifax, Lord<lb/>
Wharton, Marq. of Dorchester, Duke of Bucks, &amp;c. The Alterations from this Copy<lb/>
were upon the Objections of some of these, or my own. A. Pope.<note n="6">See Maynard Mack, ed., The Last and Greatest Art: Some Unpublished Poetical Manuscripts of Alexander Pope (Newark: University of Delaware Press, 1984), 19 –21; Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, entry PoA 273.</note><lb/>
</p>
<pb n="223"/>
<p>Mr. Pope’s original Letters to Mr. Richardson, sen. in his own Hand, together with his Dedication to all his Works, and transcript of what he dedicated [sc. dictated] to Mr. Richardson of his Birth and Publications, &amp;c.<note n="7">Pope’s letters to Richardson are now widely dispersed (see references at Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 13–14). The manuscript of a draft of the ‘Preface’ to the 1717 <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> was, in the nineteenth century, preserved in an album of materials relating to Pope which also included one of his letters to Jonathan Richardson the elder (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 16–17 and PoA 400), but only very loosely could this have been called Pope’s ‘Dedication to all his Works’. For the ‘transcript’, see ‘Transcript of what Mr. Pope dictated to Mr. Jonathan Richardson Senr. at Twickenham 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> August 1739’, Bodleian MS Eng. lett. d. 59, fos. 80–81, copied by William Gregson in December 1775 (perhaps from the manuscript sold in April 1776): Sherburn, ‘New Anecdotes about Alexander Pope’, 346–347, correct title supplied by Maynard Mack, <hi rend="italic">Alexander Pope: A Life</hi> (New York: W. W. Norton, 1985), 823 n 13.</note><lb/>
Baker and Leigh’s marked-up copy of the sale catalogue in the British Library records three of the buyers, and a copy in the Bodleian supplies the prices: Lot 3170 went for £1 7 s. to an unidentified buyer; Lot 3171 for £5 5 s. to Dr. Chauncey; Lot 3172 for £1 1 s. to Grigson (William Gregson, grandson of Jonathan Richardson the elder, who gave it to the radical Thomas Brand Hollis); and Lot 3173 for £1 11 s. 6 d. to G. Davies.<note n="8">The British Library copy (from the set press-marked S. C. Sotheby) is the one reproduced in the microfilm series <hi rend="italic">Sotheby Catalogues</hi>; the Bodleian copy is Mus. Bibl. III. 351. The purchase of lot 3171 by Chauncy was noted in <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> 47.1 (January 1777), 9.</note><lb/>
Charles Chauncy did not enjoy his purchase for long, for he died on Christmas Day 1777. His will (PROB 11/1038/53) bequeaths ‘all my Books Mss Book Cases Pictures’ and the like to his brother Nathaniel. When he first drafted the will, which is dated 10 March 1776, he added that he desired that his collections ‘may not be seperated or disposed of but kept entire and together’ to be inherited in due course by whichever of the three sons of his deceased sister Martha Snell should be thought most deserving of them (Charles himself was childless, and neither Nathaniel nor his other brother Philip had sons, so the three Snell brothers were his only male nephews).<note n="9">S. I. Tucker, <hi rend="italic">Pedigree of the Family of Chauncy</hi>, private ed. (London: Mitchell and Hughes, 1884), 9–10.</note><lb/>
However, he subsequently struck this passage out, and the will as proved on 8 January 1778 makes no restriction as to the future of the books or collections. Nathaniel Chauncy kept them together for his lifetime, but his collections of books and other objects were dispersed, ‘by his express order’, in a series of sales by auction after his death in 1790.<note n="10">For the order, see <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> 60.1 (January 1790), 87; the sale devoted to books was catalogued in <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Elegant and Valuable Libraries of Charles Chauncy … and of his Brother Nathaniel Chauncy, Esq., Both Deceased</hi> (London: for Leigh and Sotheby, 1790).</note><lb/>
However, the Pope manuscripts were not among the books sold at this time. A note in one of them records that it passed from Charles Chauncy to Nathaniel, and thence to one of the Snell nephews, another Charles, who married Nathaniel’s daughter Amelia, and changed his name in 1783 to Charles Snell Chauncy.<note n="11">The note is reported in David L. Vander Meulen, <hi rend="italic">Pope’s Dunciad of 1728: A History and Facsimile</hi> (Charlottesville and London: University Press of Virginia for the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and the New York Public Library, 1991), 42.</note> Since the whole collection was still together in 1887, it must in fact all have passed to Charles Snell Chauncy. By his will (PROB 11/1500/155, fol. 254<hi rend="sup">r</hi>),</p>
<pb n="224"/>
<p><lb/>he left ‘all my Household Furniture Plate Linen China Printed Books Wines and<lb/>other Liquors Carriages and Horses’ to his widow at his death in 1809, and there<lb/>appears to have been no quarrel over the fact that the form of words ‘printed<lb/>books’ does not cover manuscripts. She in turn left her books to her daughter<lb/>Charlotte Chauncy by her will, proved in 1841 (PROB 11/1940/325), but Char­lotte<lb/>appears to have predeceased her, and the movement of the books within the<lb/>Chauncy family for the next 46 years is unclear. In 1887, however, the barrister<lb/>and antiquary William Thorpe wrote a letter to the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> about a completely<lb/>different manuscript with a Chauncy provenance, in which he stated that ‘I am<lb/>informed by the family solicitor, Mr. Teesdale ... that when the Chauncy collec-<lb/>tions were disposed of by ... Sotheby in 1790, the autographs were retained by<lb/>the family, who have now sent them to the hammer’ (<hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, 17 September 1887,<lb/>7; repeated in essentials <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, 4 October 1887, 3). The solicitor in question, John<lb/>Marmaduke Teesdale, had married a Chauncy (see his obituary in <hi rend="italic">Law Times</hi>, 16 June 1888,<lb/>128), so he was in a good position to know the family history.</p>
<head>II</head><lb/>
<p><lb/>The catalogue of Sotheby’s sale of July 1887, to which Mack alludes so briefly,<lb/>included a series of lots headed ‘Pope (Alexander) Autograph Manuscripts, From<lb/>the Library of the late Dr. Charles Chauncy’, and this series provides the fullest<lb/>account of the set of manuscripts which had passed by inheritance through the<lb/>generations of the Chauncy family in the 111 years since Charles’s purchase in<lb/>April 1776.<note n="12">Catalogue of the Choice Library of the Late William Brice, Esq., of Bristol ... To which are added ... Pope’s Autograph Manuscripts (London: for Sotheby, Wilkinson, and Hodge, 1887), 40–41 [reproduced in the microfilm series <hi rend="italic">Sotheby Catalogues</hi>, part 2, reel 105 of 148].</note> The catalogue entries are transcribed here (text to the right<lb/>of the vertical line is right-aligned in the original) with notes on how each adds<lb/>to our knowledge of the Richardson–Chauncy manuscripts of Pope; prices<lb/>realized and buyers are from the microfilm reproduction of the auctioneer’s copy<lb/>in the British Library.<note n="13">The report of prices realized in <hi rend="italic">The Athenaeum</hi>, no. 3120 (13 August 1887), 215, ‘omitted the odd shillings’ but otherwise agrees with the auctioneer’s copy. <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, no. 32139 (1 August 1887), 4, stated that the manuscripts ‘were catalogued separately, but it was agreed to sell them as one lot, and they were accordingly so put up and sold for £220 5s.’; this was indeed the total sum realized, and seven of the eleven lots did go to a single purchaser, but the account is obviously garbled.</note></p>
<p><lb/>477 The <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>, with numerous MS. Notes and Corrections in Pope’s<lb/>handwriting, uncut, and errata in first edition, 8vo 1736 | (2)<lb/>£10 to Benjamin Franklin Stevens. Two volumes are catalogued here, one an<lb/>edition of 1736, and one a first edition. The first volume, ‘The <hi rend="italic">Essay on<lb/>Man</hi>, with numerous MS. Notes and Corrections in Pope’s handwriting, uncut ...<lb/>8vo 1736’, is surely to be identified with Pope’s revised copy of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> II (1736),<lb/>now in the British Library, C. 122. e. 31 (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’ 6–7), since this</p>
<pb n="225"/>
<p>
volume begins with An Essay on Man.<note n="14">The volume was sold at Sotheby’s on 10 February 1971, to Charles Traylen, an English<lb/>bookdealer acting ultimately for Yale University Library, but its export was, controversially,<lb/>prevented: see Peter Hopkirk, ‘Dispute over plans to export Pope manuscript [sic]’, The Times,<lb/>15 January 1971, 3, and subsequent letters to The Times by Peter Eaton (2 February 1971, 15),<lb/>Charles Traylen (10 February 1971, 13), and P. J. Korshin (24 March 1971, 15). Its British Mu-<lb/>seum accession stamp is dated 30 September 1971.<lb/></note><lb/>
It has not previously been identified as a<lb/>
Richardson–Chauncy book. The second volume, ‘The Essay on Man, with ...<lb/>
errata in first edition’, must be ‘the volume now in the Berg collection [79-432]<lb/>
that contained among other Pope material a copy of the Essay on Man and the<lb/>
manuscript of the First Satire of the Second Book of Horace’, for this copy, annotated<lb/>
in a hand or hands other than Pope’s, has Chauncy ownership inscriptions, and<lb/>
was, as we shall see, with the other Richardson–Chauncy books when Elwin<lb/>
collated it.<note n="15">Vander Meulen, Pope’s Dunciad of 1728, 42; the manuscript is Smith, ‘Alexander<lb/>Pope’, PoA 181.<lb/></note><lb/>
478 The Dunciad, first edition, large paper, frontispiece, filled with MS. Notes<lb/>
and corrections from the first Broglio MS. by Mr. Pope himself, uncut | 8vo. Dublin,<lb/>
1728<lb/>
₤13 to Thompson. This is the 1728 Dunciad, actually annotated by Jonathan<lb/>
Richardson rather than by ‘Mr. Pope himself ’, which is now in the Berg collec-<lb/>
tion of the New York Public Library (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, entry PoA 32),<lb/>
and was reproduced in facsimile with commentary by David Vander Meulen in<lb/>
1991. Vander Meulen notes that this copy and the other two Dunciads listed here<lb/>
all have the manuscript date 1777 on their title pages, which ‘seems to indicate<lb/>
that in that year they were part of a single collection, probably that of Dr. Charles<lb/>
Chauncy ... or his brother and heir Nathaniel. . . . But then parts of the trail<lb/>
become obscure’.<note n="16">Vander Meulen, Pope’s Dunciad of 1728, 42.<lb/></note><lb/>
We can now be confident that all three Dunciads were Rich-<lb/>
ardson–Chauncy books; that the collection was still Charles’s until the end of<lb/>
1777 (he died on 25 December but his will was not proved until 1778); and that<lb/>
they remained in the family until 1887, when they were sold as Lots 478, 479,<lb/>
and 480. Thompson bought six other lots in the 1887 sale; the six others all went<lb/>
to the library of William Nassau Lees, sold in 1889; this is therefore doubtless the<lb/>
annotated Dunciad which was Lot 75 in Nassau Lees’ sale, described by Smith<lb/>
(‘Alexander Pope’, 2) as unlocated. It is, by the way, an odd coincidence that just<lb/>
as Charles Chauncy bought the Richardson manuscripts of Pope in April 1776<lb/>
and died twenty months later, in December 1777, so Nassau Lees bought them<lb/>
in July 1887 and died twenty months later, in March 1889.<lb/>
479 The Dunciad. Another copy, large paper, frontispiece, with MS. corrections,<lb/>
copied from Pope’s copy by Jonathan Richardson junr. uncut | 8vo. ib. 1728<lb/>
₤7 7s. to Colonel (Francis) Grant. This is the 1728 Dunciad now at the Huntington<lb/>
Library, 106517 (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, PoA 34), which was bought by B. F.<lb/>
Stevens at Grant’s sale, was in the library of Robert Hoe by 1905, and was bought<lb/>
by Huntington at the Hoe sale in 1912; Vander Meulen remarks of this and the<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="226"/>
<p>1736 copy that their ‘early histories ... are more mysterious . . . . How these left the Chauncy family is unclear, though they may have been dispersed in the Leigh and Sotheby sale’ of Nathaniel Chauncy’s library in 1790.<note n="17">Vander Meulen, Pope’s Dunciad of 1728, 44 – 45.</note> We now see that both remained in the hands of the descendents of Nathaniel Chauncy until 1887.<lb/>
480 The Dunciad, with Notes Variorum, large paper, frontispiece, with numerous MS. Notes and corrections from his second MS. by Mr. Pope himself, uncut | 8vo. 1736 £8 8s. to (J.) Pearson. This is the 1736 Dunciad now in the Berg collection (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, PoA 33). Vander Meulen notes that in 1888 it was owned by Richard Tangye; for his remarks on its earlier history, see Lot 479.<lb/>
481 Sapho to Phaon, wholly translated, Autograph MS. of Pope | folio. 1707<lb/>
482 Essay on Criticism, Autograph MS. of Pope | folio. 1709<lb/>
483 Windsor-Forest, Autograph MS. of Pope, wanting a few lines at end | folio. 1709<lb/>
Respectively £17, £28, and £20 to Thompson, and thus to Nassau Lees; identified as Richardson–Chauncy books at his sale, where they were Lots 76, 77, and 78 respectively, but their history in the years before he acquired them has previously been incomplete (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 2 and PoA 297, PoA 160, PoA 376 – 377 respectively). Now respectively at the Morgan Library, MA 349; the Bodleian Library, MS Eng. poet. c. 1; and Washington University in St. Louis. At some point before 1887, the manuscripts of Essay on Criticism and Windsor-Forest were brought together, and the title-page of the former had the title of the latter added to it, but they were separated again before the sale.<note n="18">For the title-page, see Robert M. Schmitz, Pope’s Windsor Forest: A Study of the Washington University Holograph (St Louis: Washington University, 1952), 14, and idem, Pope’s Essay on Criticism 1709: A Study of the Bodleian Manuscript Text with Facsimiles, Transcripts, and Variants (St Louis: Washington University Press, 1962), 29.</note><lb/>
484 Essay on Man, in IV Epistles, Epistle I to III, Autograph MS. of Pope, Epistle IV printed with numerous MS. corrections by Pope himself | folio. n.d. £50 to Thompson, and thus to Nassau Lees, and Lot 79 at his sale (see 481 – 483 above); the manuscript portion is now in the Morgan Library, and the printed copy of Epistle IV is unlocated (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 2 and PoA 164, 168). This must be what Richardson meant by ‘the first scratches of the four books’ of the Essay on Man which he possessed.<lb/>
485 Epistle on Taste, Autograph MS. of Pope, with his numerous alterations and corrections | folio. n.d. £25 10s. to Quaritch. After her account of the Richardson–Chauncey books in the Nassau Lees sale, Smith states (‘Alexander Pope’, 2) that ‘Further MSS from the Chauncey collection appeared on the market later, in the Stuart M. Samuel sale, Sotheby’s, 1 July 1907.’ In fact, only one manuscript with a clear Richardson–Chauncy provenance did so: ‘Lot 111, specified as from Charles Chauncey’s</p>
</div>