<div type="section" n="7">
  <head>Extra-Illustrating Horace Walpole&rsquo;s Description of Strawberry Hill: Three Case Studies by Stephen Clarke</head>
<pb n="227"/>
library, was described as an autograph MS of a text which had not been repre-<lb/>
sented at all in the 1889 sale’, namely this one, the ‘Epistle on Taste’, or <lb/>
Epistle to <lb/>
Burlington. We now see that it had been sold as from Charles Chauncy’s library in <lb/>
1887, but not to Thompson, and had therefore not passed to Nassau Lees. The <lb/>
1887 and 1911 catalogue entries both appear to refer to the same manuscript, an <lb/>
autograph of the Epistle to Burlington with a Chauncy provenance. Smith (‘Alex-<lb/>
ander Pope’, 2 –3 and PoA 76) discusses the likelihood of its identification with <lb/>
Morgan Library MA 352, in which one leaf of the Epistle to Burlington is followed <lb/>
by eight leaves of the Epistle to Dr. Arbuthnot. The Morgan fragment was indeed <lb/>
collated by Jonathan Richardson<note n="19">See Mack, ed., Last and Greatest Art, 159 n 2.</note>. And, as we shall see below, its readings cor-<lb/>
respond to those transcribed by Whitwell Elwin from a manuscript which, when <lb/>
he saw it, was in the possession of the Chauncy family.<lb/>
486 Ethic Epistles I to III, Autograph MS. of Pope, with numerous alterations <lb/>
and corrections by himself | 4to.<lb/>
£20 to Thompson. This fair copy — ‘a superb example of [Pope’s] calligraphy’ as <lb/>
Peter Croft called it — must be what Richardson meant by ‘the several finished <lb/>
copies, (of his own neat and elegant writing)’ which he possessed, ‘several’ refer-<lb/>
ring to the different ‘books’ of the Essay on Man identified in the previous clause <lb/>
in Richardson’s memoir<note n="20">P.&amp;nbsp;J. Croft, Autograph Poetry in the English Language (London: Cassell, 1973), I. 70.</note>.<lb/>
The two manuscripts of the Essay on Man in the 1887 sale both passed from <lb/>
the Chauncy family via Thompson to Nassau Lees. One of the Nassau Lees cop-<lb/>
ies (484 above) is, as we have just seen, at the Morgan Library; the other, Lot 80 <lb/>
at the Nassau Lees sale, was catalogued as ‘Ethic Epistles I–III’, and can surely <lb/>
be identified both with the present copy and with the manuscript of the Essay on <lb/>
Man now at Harvard, which bears the same title (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 2 – 4 <lb/>
and PoA 165). The Harvard manuscript was offered for sale by Dodd, Mead and <lb/>
Co. of New York in 1910<note n="21">Alexander Pope: Notes Towards a Bibliography of Early Editions of his Writings: A Catalogue of Marshall C. Lefferts’s Great Collection of First and Later Editions of the Works of Alexander Pope, with the Autograph Manuscript of an Essay on Man (New York: Dodd, Mead and Company, [1910]), 49–50; identified with the Harvard manuscript in Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 3.</note>.<lb/>
A manuscript sold as Lot 112 in the Stuart M. Samuel sale in 1907 also bore <lb/>
the title ‘Ethic Epistles’. There are two ways to explain this. The first is that two <lb/>
manuscripts bore this title: the one now at Harvard, and the one in the Samuel <lb/>
sale. In that case, there were three manuscripts of the Essay on Man in all: the <lb/>
one now at the Morgan, the one now at Harvard, and a third, now unlocated, <lb/>
known only from its appearance in the Samuel sale catalogue. Smith proposes, <lb/>
on several grounds, that this was the case, and if she is right, the chronology of <lb/>
sales must have been as follows: 1887, the present Harvard MS is sold to Nas-<lb/>
sau Lees; 1889, the present Harvard MS is sold at Nassau Lees’ sale; 1907, a <lb/>
previously unknown MS with the same title appears at Samuel’s sale, is sold to <lb/>
Sabin, and is never seen again; 1910, the present Harvard MS is offered for sale <lb/>
by Dodd, Mead and Co. An alternative explanation is that there were only two<lb/>
<pb n="228"/>
<p>manuscripts of the Essay on Man, the one now at the Morgan and the one now<lb/>
at Harvard, and that the latter was sold in 1887, 1889, and 1907, before being<lb/>
offered for sale by Dodd, Mead and Co. in 1910.<lb/>
Of interest to us here is the question of whether the postulated third manu-<lb/>
script could also have had a Chauncy provenance. Smith suggests that it could,<lb/>
arguing that the ‘Epistle on Taste’ manuscript, 485 above, was catalogued as Lot<lb/>
111 in the Samuel sale with a note of its Chauncy provenance, and that the ‘Ethic<lb/>
Epistles’ was catalogued as Lot 112, and ‘by virtue of its juxtaposition to Lot 111<lb/>
may also have come from Chauncey’. She also notes that a manuscript of Epistle<lb/>
IV of the Essay on Man was acquired by Pierpont Morgan in 1909, and argues<lb/>
that ‘this suggests that there were more Chauncy MSS in circulation than had<lb/>
reached the sale rooms in 1889’. So there were, as we have seen: the Chauncy<lb/>
family sold their manuscripts in 1887, and not all of these were bought by Nas-<lb/>
sau Lees to return to the market in 1889. But the only Pope manuscript with a<lb/>
definite Chauncy provenance which Smith can identify as having been sold after<lb/>
1889 without having been part of the Nassau Lees sale is the ‘Epistle on Taste’<lb/>
manuscript which, as we have seen, was sold as Lot 485 with the Chauncy manu-<lb/>
scripts in 1887. There is no reason to believe that the Chauncy family withheld<lb/>
any of their literary manuscripts from the sale of 1887 for separate sale at around<lb/>
the same time, and the statement made at that time by their family lawyer sug-<lb/>
gests that they did not do so. In that case, if the Samuel manuscript of the Essay on<lb/>
Man is to be distinguished from the manuscripts now at the Morgan Library and<lb/>
Harvard, it was never a Chauncy manuscript. That is of course perfectly possible<lb/>
— Charles Chauncy bought all of Jonathan Richardson’s literary manuscripts of<lb/>
Pope apart from the Pastorals, but there were manuscripts which Richardson, and<lb/>
therefore Chauncy, never possessed, for instance the manuscript of Epistle IV<lb/>
which has just been mentioned — but a hypothetical Chauncy provenance can-<lb/>
not be part of the argument for the existence of a third Essay on Man manuscript.<lb/></p>
<p>487 Epistle III to Lord Bathurst. The original Autograph MS of Pope, with<lb/>
his numerous alterations and corrections, wanting 8 lines at end. Transcript of the<lb/>
same by Mr. Pope, with his autograph corrections and alterations, and the<lb/>
printed edition of Epistles III to VII, with numerous MS. corrections and<lb/>
alterations by Pope himself. Also Epistle II, Autograph MS of Pope, with<lb/>
his MS. alterations and corrections | folio.<lb/></p>
<p>£21 to Thompson, and thence to Nassau Lees, at whose sale the same body of<lb/>
material was Lot 81: the manuscript of ‘Epistle II’, the Epistle to a Lady, is now<lb/>
unlocated; the two manuscripts of ‘Epistle III’, the Epistle to Bathurst, are now<lb/>
Huntington HM 6007 and 6008; ‘the printed edition of Epistles III to VII, with<lb/>
numerous MS. corrections and alterations by Pope himself’ is extracted from<lb/>
Pope’s Works, volume II (1735), with collations in Richardson’s hand rather than<lb/>
Pope’s, and is now Huntington HM 6009 (Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’, 2 and PoA<lb/>
65, 67–70).<note n="22">HM 6007 and 6008 are reproduced in Earl R. Wasserman, Pope’s Epistle to Bathurst:<lb/>A Critical Reading, with an Edition of the Manuscripts (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1960).<lb/>A somewhat fuller description of HM 6009 is in Koon, ‘Pope’s First Editors’, 22.</note><lb/></p>
<pb n="229"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">O</hi>ne final question remains to be asked about the Richardson–Chauncy manu-<lb/>
scripts in the period between their acquisition by Jonathan Richardson during <lb/>
the lifetime of Pope and their sale by the Chauncy family in 1887: what light is <lb/>
shed on them by the Elwin–Courthope edition of Pope, in which some of them <lb/>
are cited? Elwin wrote in his preface to the first volume, published in 1871, that<lb/>
Pope presented several of his manuscripts to the son of Jonathan Richardson, the portrait-<lb/>
painter. . . . Richardson’s interlined copy of the first quarto volume of Pope’s poetry passed <lb/>
into the hands of Malone, and was ultimately bought by Mr. Croker. The manuscripts <lb/>
which Richardson possessed in the handwriting of Pope were purchased by Dr. Chauncey, <lb/>
and are still the property of his descendants.<note n="23">The Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Whitwell Elwin and W.&amp;nbsp;J.&amp;nbsp;Courthope, 10 vols. (London: <lb/>John Murray, 1871), 1.&amp;nbsp;xviii.</note></p>
<p>‘Richardson’s interlined copy of the first quarto volume of Pope’s poetry’ is <lb/>
the copy of the 1717 Works presented by Pope to Jonathan Richardson the elder, <lb/>
bearing notes in Malone’s hand, which is now in the Berg Collection (Smith, <lb/>
‘Alexander Pope’, 12). This copy was, as Elwin reports elsewhere, annotated by <lb/>
Richardson the younger, but was evidently not included with the ‘first Editions <lb/>
corrected’ in the sale of 1776.<note n="24">Of course, a book might in theory have been owned by Chauncy and then Malone <lb/>if the latter had bought it at the Chauncy sale of 1790, of which he owned a catalogue — see <lb/><hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Greater Portion of the Library of the Late Edmond Malone, Esq.</hi> (London: Sotheby, 1818), 12 (Lot 371) — but there was no 1717 <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> of Pope in the Chauncy sale.</note> Having been in Croker’s possession, it was no <lb/>
doubt among the materials of Croker’s on which Elwin founded his work, and <lb/>
readings from it occur in Elwin’s first two volumes.<note n="25">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 1.&amp;nbsp;90, 97 (Sapho to Phaon), 1.&amp;nbsp;323–<lb/>332, 346–347 (<hi rend="italic">Windsor-Forest</hi>), 2.&amp;nbsp;10, 42&amp;nbsp;n 3, etc. (<hi rend="italic">Essay on Criticism</hi>), 2.&amp;nbsp;420 (<hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>).</note> There are points at which <lb/>
Elwin appears to be citing, and strangely misrepresenting, Pope’s manuscripts, <lb/>
when I suspect that he is actually working from Richardson’s annotations.<note n="26">See the discussions of some of these readings in Schmitz, <hi rend="italic">Pope’s Windsor Forest</hi>, 13, and <hi rend="italic">idem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pope’s Essay on Criticism&amp;nbsp;1709</hi>, 22; Schmitz did not realize that Elwin was working from <lb/>Richardson’s annotations rather than from the holograph, and therefore saw some of his read-<lb/>ings as ‘incorrect to the point of curiosity’ (<hi rend="italic">Pope’s Essay</hi>, 22).</note></p>
<p>In his introduction to the third volume of the Elwin–Courthope edition, <lb/>
Courthope thanked Elwin ‘for his liberality in allowing me to use his transcript <lb/>
of the Chauncy MS., which throws so much light on the meaning of Pope’s sat-<lb/>
ires’; he referred again, a few pages later, to ‘the transcript which Mr.&amp;nbsp;Elwin has <lb/>
made from the Chauncy MS.’<note n="27">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 3.&amp;nbsp;x, 18.</note> This form of words suggests that Courthope did <lb/>
not realize that the transcript which Elwin had communicated to him included <lb/>
readings from multiple manuscripts.<note n="28">Vander Meulen, <hi rend="italic">Pope’s Dunciad of 1728</hi>, 43 proposes that Courthope’s ‘MS.’ is ‘probably to be construed as plural’, but a simple misunderstanding on Courthope’s part seems likelier.</note></p>
<p>The first references to the ‘Chauncy MS.’ in the collations in this volume are in those to the <hi rend="italic">Epistle to Bathurst</hi>, where its <lb/>
readings correspond to those of Huntington HM&amp;nbsp;6007 and HM&amp;nbsp;6008 (Lot 487</p>
<pb n="230"/>
<p>above).<note n="29">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 3. 127–157 passim; Wasserman, Pope’s Epistle to Bathurst, 60 notes that the ‘Chauncy MS’ readings derive from the Huntington manuscripts.</note> It is then cited in the Epistle to Burlington, where its readings correspond<lb/>to those of the first leaf of Morgan Library MA 352 (Lot 485 above).<note n="30">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 3. 172–178 passim (cf. Mack, ed., Last and Greatest Art, 160–162); ‘the ignoble shout of Guise’ (3. 172) is a bad emendation of the manuscript reading ‘the noble shout of Guise’.</note> It is cited in the Epistle to Dr. Arbuthnot, where its readings correspond to those of subse-<lb/>quent leaves of Morgan Library MA 352 (Elwin had remarked in his introduction<lb/>to the first volume that a copy of this poem was among ‘the manuscripts which<lb/>Richardson possessed in the handwriting of Pope’).<note n="31">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 3. 241–273 passim (cf. Mack, ed., Last and Greatest Art, 424–430 and 436–450); Elwin’s reference to plural manuscripts is Works, 1. xviii.</note> And it is cited in The First<lb/>Satire of the Second Book of Horace, where its readings correspond to those in the<lb/>Berg manuscript formerly attached to a printed copy of the Essay on Man (lot<lb/>477 part 2 above).<note n="32">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 3. 289–300 passim, and 3. 279, 400 n 2 (cf. Mack, ed., Last and Greatest Art, 172–186).</note> So, all of these ‘Chauncy MS.’ readings are, as we might<lb/>have expected, from manuscripts which can be identified with those sold in 1887.<lb/>Furthermore, Courthope noted in his edition of the Dunciad that ‘Jonathan Rich-<lb/>ardson corrected the first edition of the “Dunciad” from what he calls “the first<lb/>Broglio MS.” His corrections have been transcribed by Mr. Elwin, and are here<lb/>preserved’; as Vander Meulen has observed, ‘Undoubtedly Elwin transcribed<lb/>Richardson’s notes from the current Berg copy’ (lot 478 above).<note n="33">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 4. 271 n 2; Vander Meulen, Pope’s Dunciad of 1728, 43.</note></p>
<p>In one other reference to ‘the Richardson papers’, I think that Elwin uses a<lb/>form of words which, although not inaccurate, is misleading: ‘The manuscript of<lb/>Pope’s Pastorals is still preserved among the Richardson papers’.<note n="34">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 1. 239.</note> His further<lb/>description makes it certain that this is the manuscript which was Lot 3172 at the<lb/>sale of 1776, but this manuscript was, as we have seen, not bought by Chauncy,<lb/>and although it is possible that it might subsequently have been bought as an<lb/>addition to the collection of Pope manuscripts which had passed by inheritance<lb/>through the generations of the Chauncy family, it seems unlikely that it would<lb/>then have been kept from the sale of 1887 in which the collection was dispersed.<lb/>Elwin presumably meant simply that the manuscript had a Richardson prov-<lb/>enance — and, interestingly, that it was not alone. He specifies one of its com-<lb/>panions: ‘The Richardson collection contains a manuscript in which the poet<lb/>has transcribed from his Pastorals the various lines he thought defective, and ...<lb/>referred the task of selection to Walsh, who has jotted down his decisions at the<lb/>bottom of Pope’s remarks’.<note n="35">Works of Alexander Pope, ed. Elwin and Courthope, 1. 240.</note> This is certainly the manuscript (Smith, ‘Alexander<lb/>Pope’, PoA 274) which, having long been a companion to the autograph fair copy<lb/>of the Pastorals, was sold separately from it at the Houghton sale of 1980, and was<lb/>Lot 381 in the Roy Davids sale at Bonhams, 8 May 2013.</p>
<pb n="231"/>
<p>In conclusion, then, we can list Jonathan Richardson the younger’s Pope books<lb/>
as follows, dividing the Richardson–Chauncy group from the others, with PoA<lb/>
numbers from Smith, ‘Alexander Pope’.<lb/></p>
<head>Bought by Chauncy as Lot&amp;nbsp;3171 in the Sale of&amp;nbsp;1776</head>
<p>1.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>, 1736, ‘with numerous MS.&amp;nbsp;Notes and Corrections in Pope’s<lb/>
handwriting’: part of Lot&amp;nbsp;477 in 1887; now British Library, C.&amp;nbsp;122.&amp;nbsp;e.&amp;nbsp;31 (PoA<lb/>
174 etc.: each work in the volume has a PoA number).<lb/>
2.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>, ‘first edition’: part of Lot&amp;nbsp;477 in 1887; probably the marked-up<lb/>
copy now in the Berg Collection of New York Public Library, 79-432, which<lb/>
included a holograph of the <hi rend="italic">First Satire of the Second Book of Horace</hi>, also in<lb/>
the Berg Collection (PoA&amp;nbsp;181).<lb/>
3.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>, 1728, ‘with MS.&amp;nbsp;Notes and corrections from the first Broglio MS’:<lb/>
Lot&amp;nbsp;478 in 1887; now in the Berg Collection (PoA&amp;nbsp;32).<lb/>
4.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>, 1728, also with collations: Lot&amp;nbsp;479 in 1887; now at the Huntington<lb/>
Library, 106517 (PoA&amp;nbsp;34).<lb/>
5.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi>, 1736, ‘with numerous MS.&amp;nbsp;Notes and corrections from his second<lb/>
MS.&amp;nbsp;by Mr.&amp;nbsp;Pope himself’: Lot&amp;nbsp;480 in 1887; now in the Berg Collection<lb/>
(PoA&amp;nbsp;33).<lb/>
6.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Sapho to Phaon</hi>, holograph: Lot&amp;nbsp;481 in 1877; now at the Morgan Library, MA<lb/>
349 (PoA&amp;nbsp;297).<lb/>
7.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Essay on Criticism</hi>, holograph: Lot&amp;nbsp;482 in 1877; now in the Bodleian, MS&amp;nbsp;Eng.<lb/>
poet.&amp;nbsp;c.&amp;nbsp;1 (PoA&amp;nbsp;160).<lb/>
8.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Windsor-Forest</hi>, holograph: Lot&amp;nbsp;483 in 1877; now at Washington University<lb/>
(PoA&amp;nbsp;376).<lb/>
9.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>, Epistles&amp;nbsp;I–III holograph, and Epistle&amp;nbsp;IV an annotated printed<lb/>
edition: Lot&amp;nbsp;484 in 1887; the holograph portion now Morgan Library MA<lb/>
348 (PoA&amp;nbsp;164) and the printed portion now unlocated (PoA&amp;nbsp;168).<lb/>
10.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Epistle to Burlington</hi>, holograph: Lot&amp;nbsp;485 in 1887; almost certainly really one<lb/>
leaf of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle to Burlington</hi> followed by a holograph of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle to Dr.&amp;nbsp;Arbuthnot</hi>,<lb/>
and in that case, now Morgan Library MA&amp;nbsp;352, fols.&amp;nbsp;1 (PoA&amp;nbsp;76) and 2–9<lb/>
(PoA&amp;nbsp;81).<lb/>
11.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>, Epistles&amp;nbsp;I–III, holograph: Lot&amp;nbsp;486 in 1887; now Harvard,<lb/>
fMS&amp;nbsp;Eng.&amp;nbsp;233.&amp;nbsp;1 (PoA&amp;nbsp;165).<lb/>
12.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Epistle to Bathurst</hi>, holograph: part of Lot&amp;nbsp;487 in 1887; now Huntington,<lb/>
HM&amp;nbsp;6007 and 6008 (PoA&amp;nbsp;67–69).<lb/>
13.&amp;nbsp;Pages from the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, vol.&amp;nbsp;II&amp;nbsp;(1735), with Richardson’s collations of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle<lb/>
   to Bathurst</hi>: part of Lot&amp;nbsp;487 in 1887; now Huntington, HM&amp;nbsp;6009 (PoA&amp;nbsp;70).<lb/>
14.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Epistle to a Lady</hi>, holograph: part of Lot&amp;nbsp;487 in 1887; unlocated (PoA&amp;nbsp;65).<lb/></p>
<head>Not Bought by Chauncy</head>
<p>15.&amp;nbsp;<hi rend="italic">Pastorals</hi>, holograph: part of Lot&amp;nbsp;3172 in 1776; Houghton sale, 1980<lb/>
(PoA&amp;nbsp;273).<lb/></p>
<pb n="232"/>
<list>
<item>16. ‘Alterations to the Pastoralls’, partly holograph: part of Lot 3172 in 1776; Roy<lb/>Davids sale, 2013 (PoA 274).</item>
<item>17. ‘Mr. Pope’s original Letters to Mr. Richardson, sen.’, holograph: part of Lot 3173 in 1776; now probably dispersed.</item>
<item>18. ‘Dedication to all his Works’, perhaps holograph: part of Lot 3173 in 1776; now unlocated, unless it is to be identified with the draft of the ‘Preface’ to<lb/>the 1717 Works now in the John Murray album at Yale (PoA 400).</item>
<item>19. ‘Transcript of what he dedicated [sc. dictated] to Mr. Richardson of his Birth<lb/>and Publications’: part of Lot 3173 in 1776; now unlocated, but transcribed<lb/>in 1775 as Bodleian, MS Eng. lett. d. 59, fols. 80–8 1.</item>
<item>20. Works (1717), presented by Pope to Jonathan Richardson the elder, and<lb/>marked up with collations by Jonathan Richardson the younger: not in the<lb/>1776 sale; now in the Berg Collection.</item>
</list>
<pb n="233"/>
<head>EXTRA-ILLUSTRATING HORACE WALPOLE’S DESCRIPTION<lb/>OF STRAWBERRY HILL: THREE CASE STUDIES</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi> <name type="pname">Stephen Clarke</name><note n="*">I would like to thank Jill Gage of the Newberry Library and Charles Sebag-Montefiore<lb/>for alerting me to and making available respectively the second and third of the three copies<lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> of Strawberry Hill here discussed; also Silvia Davoli, Kevin Rogers, Michael<lb/>Snodin, and Howard Weinbrot for information and advice, and Peter Sabor for commenting<lb/>on an early draft of this paper.<lb/></note></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">S</hi>tudies of the phenomenon of binding independent drawings, engravings, au-<lb/>tograph letters, and other documents into printed books in the late eighteenth <lb/>century have concentrated quite naturally on the elite social groups within which <lb/>many of these extra-illustrated books were created.<note n="1">Lucy Peltz, “A Friendly Gathering: The Social Politics of Presentation Books and<lb/>Their Extra-Illustration in Horace Walpole’s Circle,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the History of Collections</hi> 19.1 (2007), 33–50; “Engraved Portrait Heads and the Rise of<lb/>Extra-Illustration: The Eton Correspondence of the Revd James Granger and Richard Bull, 1769–1774,” <hi rend="italic">The Walpole Society</hi> (2004), 66, 1–161; and <hi rend="italic">Facing the Text: Extra-Illustration, Print Culture, and Society in Britain 1769–1840</hi> (San Marino: The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, 2017), 45.<lb/></note> Less examined are the artists <lb/>and booksellers who supplied the market for those books and provided the prints <lb/>and drawings that adorned them. This paper explores that world by investigating <lb/>the role of Horace Walpole’s printer and amanuensis Thomas Kirgate and the <lb/>Harding family of booksellers and artists in creating three extra-illustrated cop-<lb/>ies of Walpole’s <hi rend="italic">A Description of the Villa of Mr. Horace Walpole, youngest son of Sir Robert Walpole Earl of Orford, at Strawberry-Hill near Twickenham, Middlesex.</hi> With an Inventory of the Furniture, Pictures, Curiosities, &amp;c.<lb/></p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> is the primary document we have on the content and display <lb/>of Walpole’s famous collection of art and antiquities, portraits and miniatures, <lb/>curiosities, books and prints, coins and medals, sculpture, and furniture. One <lb/>hundred copies of the book had originally been printed at his Strawberry Hill <lb/>Press in 1774, but it was superseded in 1784 by an expanded edition of two hun-<lb/>dred copies. Each edition was supplemented with a series of appendices printed <lb/>successively as the collection grew. The 1784 edition, with additions printed as <lb/>late as 1791, was not issued until Walpole’s death in 1797, when his executors <lb/></p>
<pb n="234"/>
<p>distributed copies to friends as directed. This edition had a complex printing <lb/>
history, but the essential points are that it was not published or circulated during <lb/>
Walpole’s lifetime, nor was it shown to the many visitors who obtained tickets to <lb/>
be shown Walpole’s celebrated and curious house and collection.<note n="2">For the complex printing history of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, see Stephen Clarke, “‘Lord God! Jesus! What a House!’: Describing and Visiting Strawberry Hill,” <hi rend="italic">Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 33.3 (September 2010), 357–380.</note><lb/>
</p>
<head>I</head>
<p>For the 1784 edition Walpole provided a preface, a brief but elegant testament <lb/>
of faith, accounting for his use of Gothic ornament at Strawberry Hill, cel-<lb/>
ebrating the great cabinets from which his collection was acquired, noting the <lb/>
miniatures and historic royal portraits and other highlights of the collection, <lb/>
and concluding with a flourish of justification, part whimsical and part defiant, <lb/>
of the “small capricious house … built to please my own taste, and in some <lb/>
degree to realize my own visions.”<note n="3">Horace Walpole, <hi rend="italic">A Description of the Villa of Mr. Horace Walpole, youngest son of Sir Robert Walpole Earl of Orford, at Strawberry-Hill near Twickenham, Middlesex. With an Inventory of the Furniture, Pictures, Curiosities, &amp;c.</hi> (Strawberry Hill: Not published, 1784), iv.</note> The body of the text then introduces the <lb/>
house and its setting, and proceeds to describe its interior, room by room. The <lb/>
decorative chimney pieces and plasterwork and other features are recorded, and <lb/>
there is a minute catalogue of the furniture, pictures, sculpture, bronzes, china, <lb/>
and curiosities that each room displayed, while the accompanying engravings <lb/>
show the exterior, the grounds, a number of the chimney pieces, and some of <lb/>
the major rooms.<lb/>
</p>
<p>The detailed account of the house and its contents of the 1784 edition in-<lb/>
vited extra-illustration, and in Walpole’s immediate circle there were a number <lb/>
of sumptuous copies—such as Walpole’s own, with the ninety-six quarto pages <lb/>
of the 1784 edition inlaid into an elephant folio expanded to over two hundred <lb/>
pages.<note n="4">Walpole’s extra-illustrated copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> is at the Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, 49 3582.</note> He employed a succession of artists to provide illustrations and record <lb/>
his creation at Strawberry Hill, of whom the most prolific were Edward Edwards <lb/>
(1738–1806) and John Carter (1748–1817). Edwards provided watercolors that <lb/>
were engraved for the prints that appear in the 1784 edition of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, <lb/>
and Carter, an artist, antiquary, and polemist for the conservation of Gothic <lb/>
architecture, worked at Strawberry Hill through the 1780s.<lb/>
</p>
<p>Walpole’s copy is matched for richness by that compiled by his correspondent <lb/>
Richard Bull (1721–1805)—but then Bull’s commitment to extra-illustration was <lb/>
heroic in its scale, and he illustrated at least sixteen titles from Walpole’s Straw-<lb/>
berry Hill Press. His copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> is enriched by more watercolors <lb/>
by Carter than is Walpole’s copy. Various other generously illustrated copies <lb/>
of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> from Walpole’s circle are known, including the copy com-<lb/>
piled by Carter for himself, which contains his sketches for some of the finished <lb/>
</p>
<pb n="235"/>
watercolors in Bull’s copy; the copy of Charles Bedford (1742–1814), Walpole’s<lb/>
Deputy in the office of Usher of the Exchequer; and two copies of his printer<lb/>
Thomas Kirgate (1734/5–1810).<note n="5">Bull’s copy is at the Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, 33 30 copy 11; Carter’s copy is at the Huntington Library, San Marino, 130368; Bedford’s copy is in the possession of<lb/>Lord Waldegrave of North Hill; and two copies that had belonged to Kirgate are at the Lewis<lb/>Walpole Library, 33 30 copy 6 and 33 30 copy 29.</note><lb/>
These issues have been discussed and analyzed in detail by Nicolas<lb/>
Barker in his edition of Charles Bedford’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> printed for the<lb/>
Roxburghe Club.<note n="6">Horace Walpole’s <hi rend="italic">Description of the Villa at Strawberry-Hill: A facsimile of the copy extra-illustrated for Charles Bedford in the collection of Lord Waldegrave of North Hill</hi>, ed. Nicolas Barker (London: The Roxburghe Club, 2010).<lb/>This discussion has recently been extended by Peltz in Parts I and II of <hi rend="italic">Facing the Text</hi>.</note> Barker summarizes the history of extra-illustration and Walpole’s<lb/>
involvement with James Granger and the Strawberry Hill Press and the print collec-<lb/>
tors Bull and Anthony Storer (1746–99). He points out what an appealing subject<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> offered, with an increasing number of engraved images of Strawberry<lb/>
Hill becoming available on the market from the 1790s.<note n="7">It is significant that lot 300 of the second part of the sale catalogue of the print collection of Sir Mark Masterman Sykes in 1824 was “a valuable collection of prints and drawings, in colours &amp;c. … to illustrate Lord Orford’s Seat at Strawberry Hill, uniformly mounted, and arranged for the purpose of binding, in a Russia Portfolio, lettered <hi rend="italic">Strawberry Hill</hi>, and Museum.”<lb/>This was bought by the print dealer Woodburn for £47–5–0, a ready-made collection of images which Woodburn’s eventual customer could no doubt take out of its portfolio and bind up in a copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>.<lb/>Similarly, lot 314 on the third day of the sale in 1825 of prints and drawings of George Baker, collector and bibliographer of the Strawberry Hill Press, consisted of views of the house and contents, including many proof impressions of the portraits, ripe for use in extra-illustration.</note><lb/>
accessible to collectors outside Walpole’s circle—and for them the essential<lb/>
providers were the Harding family of booksellers and artists, at their shop in<lb/>
Pall Mall.<lb/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">II</hi><lb/>
Silvester Harding (1745–1809) trained as a miniature painter and exhibited<lb/>
at the Royal Academy from 1776. In 1786 with his younger brother Edward<lb/>
(1755–1840) he opened a book and printseller’s shop in Fleet Street, moving<lb/>
in 1792 to 102 Pall Mall. They specialized in theatrical and historical portraits,<lb/>
and in 1789–93 published in numbers <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare Illustrated</hi> by an assemblage of<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Portraits and Views</hi>, and in 1793 an edition of Anthony Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Count<lb/>
Grammont</hi>, also illustrated with portraits. In the meanwhile Silvester Harding had<lb/>
been introduced to Strawberry Hill in the early 1780s by the merchant and art<lb/>
collector Nathaniel Hillier (c. 1707–83) and became a great friend of Walpole’s<lb/>
printer Kirgate.<note n="8">Nathaniel Hillier to Walpole, 19 October 1780, <hi rend="italic">Yale Edition of Horace Walpole’s Correspondence</hi>, 16: 95–97.</note> From 1795 the Hardings published <hi rend="italic">The Biographical Mirrour</hi>,<lb/>
a series of historical portraits with supporting text, and also in 1796 <hi rend="italic">Bürger’s<lb/>
Leonora</hi> and in 1797 Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Fables</hi>, both with engravings after drawings by<lb/>
<pb n="236"/>
<p><lb/>
Walpole’s protégée Lady Diana Beauclerk. In 1793 they published six plates to<lb/>
illustrate Walpole’s The Castle of Otranto, and these are often seen in those copies<lb/>
that had not already been sold and bound up of the sixth edition printed for<lb/>
Dodsley and Bodoni’s edition printed in Parma (both 1791). Sometime before<lb/>
1798 the partnership dissolved, Silvester moving along the street to 127, while<lb/>
Edward moved to 98 Pall Mall until in 1803 he was appointed librarian to<lb/>
Queen Charlotte, for whose amusement he grangerized a number of historical<lb/>
works.<lb/></p>
<p><lb/>
Silvester Harding had two artist sons; Edward, who died young, and George<lb/>
Perfect Harding (1779/80–1853). George exhibited as a miniaturist at the Royal<lb/>
Academy from 1802 until 1840 —in 1839 submitting “The Library at Strawberry<lb/>
Hill, Seat of the Earl of Waldegrave,” current whereabouts unknown. For about<lb/>
forty years, from 1804, he travelled the country copying portraits, carefully re-<lb/>
cording dates and signatures. His watercolors are precise, finished, and compact,<lb/>
with sparing use of gold for rules and signatures. His notebooks of these travels<lb/>
survive at the National Portrait Gallery, four bound volumes of his “List of Por-<lb/>
traits, Pictures, in Various Mansions of the United Kingdom,” the fourth volume<lb/>
containing a list of manuscripts and printed books illustrated by him, with a list of<lb/>
pictures in the possession of the Crown. The second volume, a 358-page manu-<lb/>
script to which a table of contents and index are added, records the pictures he<lb/>
inspected at 141 properties, mostly country houses, but also universities, livery<lb/>
companies, and Inns of Court. At the foot of the title page is the note “Those<lb/>
that are mark’d thus X, have been copyed by G. P. Harding.” In that volume as<lb/>
in the others, most entries are of one page per property, a few extending to four<lb/>
or even five pages: for Tottenham Park in Wiltshire, for example, the seat of the<lb/>
Marquis of Ailesbury, Harding listed 101 portraits over five pages, of which six<lb/>
were marked with a cross as having been copied by him. But this, and all the<lb/>
other properties in the volume, is eclipsed by Strawberry Hill. In a list extend-<lb/>
ing over twenty pages, with headings for the different rooms, Harding lists 433<lb/>
portraits, of which he notes with his cross that he had copied sixty-four. Where<lb/>
he adds commentary to the name of the sitter, he takes or adapts the text from<lb/>
the Description. And this wealth of images is in addition to the numerous portraits<lb/>
that his father had copied there.<note n="9">NPG MS47. George Perfect Harding was the subject of a display at the National Por-<lb/>trait Gallery, “The Tudors Reimagined: George Perfect Harding c. 1779–1853” (2015). See<lb/>also W. S. Lewis, The Forlorn Printer: Being Notes on Horace Walpole’s Alleged Neglect of Thomas<lb/>Kirgate (Farmington: Privately printed, 1931), and Stephen Clarke, The Strawberry Hill Press<lb/>&amp; its Printing House: An Account and an Iconography (New Haven: Lewis Walpole Library, Yale<lb/>University, 2011), 51 and 86–91.</note><lb/></p>
<p><lb/>
The watercolors and prints by the Hardings of portraits and other items from<lb/>
the collection at Strawberry Hill run from Silvester Harding’s introduction to the<lb/>
house in the early 1780s to George’s watercolor of the library, noted above, of<lb/>
1839. Of their published works, twenty-three of the 151 plates in the Biographical<lb/>
Mirrour are from portraits at Strawberry Hill, while in 1803 Silvester Harding<lb/>
published A Series of Portraits, to Illustrate the Earl of Orford’s Catalogue, of Royal and<lb/></p>
<pb n="237"/>
<p>Noble Authors, an eight-page pamphlet listing the authors’ portraits and the pages<lb/>
on which they appeared, providing the print collector with a checklist to work<lb/>
against. (A similar checklist for another title much favored by illustrators, A Co-<lb/>
pious Index to Pennant’s Account of London, was produced for the burgeoning army<lb/>
of illustrators by Thomas Downe in 1814.) The Hardings appear to have shared<lb/>
access to Strawberry Hill with Silvester and Edward senior’s brother-in-law, the<lb/>
engraver William Bawtree, and such access seems to have been continued to be<lb/>
afforded to them when after Walpole’s death the house was occupied by Anne<lb/>
Damer, who was there until 1811. It has long been known that Kirgate oper-<lb/>
ated with increasing autonomy at the end of Walpole’s life (hence his reprinting<lb/>
Strawberry Hill Press items in the year of Walpole’s death, presumably for his<lb/>
own benefit), and he is the essential link in enabling the Hardings to accumulate<lb/>
the images they needed to satisfy the demands of their print collector customers.<lb/></p>
<head>III</head>
<p>Kirgate had originally been employed by Walpole for five months in 1765 to<lb/>
finish off printing the second edition of the Anecdotes of Painting,<lb/>
and was then discharged when Walpole left for Paris. He was re-engaged in<lb/>
April 1768 and stayed with Walpole until Walpole’s death nearly thirty years<lb/>
later, working as printer, secretary, and general factotum. Much has been written<lb/>
on his role in re-printing earlier Strawberry Hill pamphlets at the same press in<lb/>
the year of Walpole’s death, and the extremely modest sum of £100 left him in<lb/>
Walpole’s will.<note n="10">See Lewis, The Forlorn Printer; A. T. Hazen, A Bibliography of the Strawberry Hill Press (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1942), 12–14; Barker, Horace Walpole’s Description of the Villa, 99; and Clarke, The Strawberry Hill Press &amp; its Printing House, 47–53.</note> What is quite clear is that before leaving<lb/>
Strawberry Hill in 1797, Kirgate printed an address card for himself, “Thomas<lb/>
Kirgate, Late Printer at Straw<lb/>
berry-Hill, Print and Bookseller, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 127, Pall-Mall”—that being the address<lb/>
of Silvester Harding’s shop. He subsequently moved to a house in Vine Street,<lb/>
Piccadilly, where he sold books and curiosities. Kirgate’s role in satisfying the<lb/>
needs of collectors and extra-illustrators cannot be better summarized than in an<lb/>
undated letter he wrote to Charles Bedford which has been quoted elsewhere,<lb/>
but merits repeating here:<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">George Harding had not finished the Drawing of the Duc de Nivernois till this morning,<lb/>
nor could I get Sir Kenelm Digby before yesterday, or I should have sent sooner. The late<lb/>
and present Sales afford nothing but what is extravagantly dear. A Guinea is a low price<lb/>
now for a scarce Print—upwards of Forty was given for one of a Duke of Norfolk, t’other<lb/>
day at Richardson’s. Five, Ten, nay Twenty Guineas, is readily given for a Print, that has<lb/>
no other value but scarcity. Illustrators of Granger, and other books, care less for Money<lb/>
than Portraits; the Rage for which increases—’tis a Madness which I hope will not reach<lb/>
Brixton [Bedford’s address]. The few Ladies you want for p. 16 &amp; 17, I do not think you<lb/>
will ever get; I bid upwards of a Guinea for one, the Duchess of Somerset, but she scorned<lb/>
such a paltry offer. ’Tis lucky, Sir, you want but such a few Prints to complete your Book;<lb/>
had you just begun to collect for it, you would soon quit the pursuit. I despair of finishing<lb/>
my Strawberry which I have now in hand.</hi><lb/></p>
<pb n="238"/>
I know not when I shall have the Pleasure of seeing you, Sir, for I can get nothing to bring;<lb/>
and am so infirm, I cannot walk far. But I shall not forget to search for the few you still<lb/>
want. As soon as I can see Bawtree, I will get him to make a Drawing of the Bed in the<lb/>
Holbein Room, for I despair of getting Carter to do it Nor is Geo. Harding very willing to<lb/>
make any more Drawings—he has had the one now sent upwards of a Fortnight in hand.<note n="11">Kirgate MSS. Folder, Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University; quoted in Barker, Horace Walpole’s Description of the Villa, 116; and Clarke, The Strawberry Hill Press &amp; its Printing House, 87–89 (where it is explained that the letter, though undated, is probably of 1801).</note><lb/>
This letter is revealing on a number of levels. It shows Kirgate as facilitator, orchestrating<lb/>
the acquisition of missing prints for the collector while complain­<lb/>
ing about the exploding market in portrait prints, and displays George Harding’s role as<lb/>
provider of drawings. It also illustrates the somewhat obsessional needs of the collector,<lb/>
has Kirgate acknowledging that he is himself compiling an extra-illustrated copy of the<lb/>
Description, and offers the possibly illusory prospect of “finishing” one’s extra-illustrated<lb/>
book.<lb/>
Kirgate offered his own extra-illustrated copy by raffle in 1801. The broad­<lb/>
sheet advertising the sale, “For the Benefit of T. Kirgate, Late Printer at Straw­<lb/>
berry-Hill,” announced that:<lb/>
Each Leaf of the above Book is inlaid on a large Sheet of fine Dutch paper; the Pages bor­<lb/>
dered with a double Line of red Ink; the Title printed in three Colours, and ornamented<lb/>
with a Drawing of a Foliage of Strawberries. The whole Book adorned with upwards of<lb/>
Two [crossed through in manuscript and amended to three] Hundred Drawings and<lb/>
Prints, illustrative of the external and internal Parts of that delightful Seat, its Furniture,<lb/>
Pictures, Sculptures, Antiquities, &amp;c. &amp;c. Several of the Prints are scarce and valuable,<lb/>
and most of the Drawings were made on Purpose for the Book, by the Friends of <hi rend="smallcaps">T. KIRGATE</hi>,<lb/>
who has been Fourteen Years in forming the Collection.<note n="12">Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, 53 K634 801.</note><lb/>
Potential subscribers could inspect the book at Harding’s shop in Pall Mall. The current<lb/>
whereabouts of the book are unknown, but it appears to have been a particularly fine<lb/>
example of Kirgate’s industry in the years after he had left Straw­berry Hill. Another<lb/>
example of his endeavors is an elephant folio scrapbook of im­ages of Strawberry Hill and<lb/>
its contents, perhaps used to display to customers what images could be acquired or copied<lb/>
for the extra-illustrated copy they ordered: this is now in the collection of Lord Waldegrave<lb/>
of North Hill. There is also at the Lewis Walpole Library a volume compiled by Kirgate<lb/>
consisting of lists of images from the house. Firstly, there is a two-page list of forty-six<lb/>
pictures and sculptures there, with page references to the Description, twenty-four of them<lb/>
crossed through (perhaps as having already been obtained) and with Kirgate’s comments in<lb/>
red ink against almost all of the others—two prints of Rubens’s house “both scarce,” Anne<lb/>
Hyde Duchess of York “A foreign print, 8vo. scarce,” others “Engraving by Harding” or “In<lb/>
my List,” while of four portraits in the Gallery described on page 52 he notes “I cannot say<lb/>
positively if there are Prints of these, the Pictures hanging too high to examine.” This is<lb/>
followed by a list dated 26 July 1800 of twelve drawings, with their Description page<lb/>
numbers and prices, and then two longer lists, one “A List of the Prints and Drawings as<lb/>
placed in Lord Orford’s Illustrated Copy of the Description of Strawberry-Hill printed there<lb/>
in 1784 by Thos. Kirgate,” the other a list of the 335 prints and drawings in his own copy.<lb/>
The historical portraits<lb/>
<pb n="239"/>
that formed such a prominent part of the Strawberry Hill collection were pregnant <lb/>
with possibilities for any print collector who knew his Granger, and Kirgate and <lb/>
the Hardings were only too happy to meet that demand.<lb/>
Kirgate died in 1810, and the sale of his collection was conducted by King <lb/>
&amp; Lochée over ten days that December, immediately followed by a further day’s <lb/>
supplemental sale. The auction catalogue contained multiple copies of Strawberry <lb/>
Hill Press items, over eighty lots on the second day, and in the supplemental sale <lb/>
ninety-eight lots of “Books Printed chiefly at Strawberry-Hill.” On the ninth day <lb/>
there were more than two hundred drawings and prints of the house in twenty-nine <lb/>
lots, with the artists listed including Carter, J. C. Barrow, Edwards, the Hardings, <lb/>
and Kirgate himself. This was followed by sixty-nine lots of prints in the supple-<lb/>
mental sale, many of them related to Strawberry Hill. Both Edward and George <lb/>
Harding appear among the successful bidders (Silvester had died the previous <lb/>
year) and it seems clear that what was on offer was the remains of Kirgate’s stock.<lb/>
<head>IV</head><lb/>
The first of the three extra-illustrated copies of the Description here discussed is <lb/>
chosen because it represents precisely what a collector with no connection to <lb/>
Walpole or his circle could have acquired from the Hardings’ shop in Pall Mall. <lb/>
Unlike the two other copies that will be considered, it is known and recorded: it <lb/>
has been at the Huntington Library, San Marino, for over one hundred years, <lb/>
having been acquired by Huntington at the sale of Robert Hoe’s library. It is <lb/>
bound in green morocco with a title page printed in black, red, and blue, and it <lb/>
has a total of seventy-three additional items bound into it, the large majority of <lb/>
which have been listed by Nicolas Barker.<note n="13">Barker’s helpful list includes the extra-illustrations from the Huntington copy under discussion, reference 131207, together with those of sixteen other copies. It does not include the second of the three copies of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> described in this paper (Newberry Library, Chicago), nor does it include a copy illustrated by the Hardings at New York Public Library (reference Stuart 1057).</note><lb/>
The backbone of the illustrations is formed by thirty-two portrait prints by <lb/>
the Hardings, largely stipple engravings from portraits at Strawberry Hill, of <lb/>
which the earliest is dated 1792, the latest 1806. These stipple engravings are <lb/>
almost all after Silvester Harding, who with his brother Edward was the leading <lb/>
figure in providing drawings for engraving in stipple, whereas it appears that his <lb/>
son George was primarily a painter and copyist.<lb/>
In addition to the Harding stipple engravings, there are twenty-nine miscel-<lb/>
laneous prints or printed items. These vary from the readily obtainable, such as <lb/>
the views of Strawberry Hill from Birch’s Delices de la Grande Bretagne (1791) and <lb/>
from Boydell’s History of the River Thames (1794–96), to items more directly as-<lb/>
sociated with the Press at Strawberry—for example, Edwards’s scarce etching of <lb/>
Kirgate, scarce because (as Edwards explained to Bull in a letter of 18 December <lb/>
1784, when presenting him with a copy) “Mr. Walpole thought fit to be offended <lb/>
at its being done &amp; therefore its publication will be suppressed.” Bull of course <lb/>
pasted Edwards’s print and his letter into his copy of the Description, whereas the<lb/>
<pb n="240"/>
<p>anonymous compiler of the Huntington volume had to be content with the print.<lb/>
But he was also able to obtain a copy of Walpole’s printed “Rules for obtaining<lb/>
a Ticket to see Strawberry Hill” of 1784, and six drawings and six watercolors,<lb/>
quite possibly all of them by the Hardings, including Charlotte de Tremouille,<lb/>
Countess of Derby, the defender of Latham Castle in the Civil War, from the<lb/>
painting in the Tribune, a highly finished portrait in court dress, and Sir Chris-<lb/>
topher Wray, Queen Elizabeth’s Lord Chief Justice, and Sir Robert Walpole in<lb/>
the robes of the Order of the Bath, from the Great North Bedchamber. The<lb/>
prints underline the strength of Walpole’s holdings of 16th- and 17th-century<lb/>
portraits, though there is a real contrast between the quality of the Hardings’<lb/>
finished watercolors, which have been commended as painstaking in their detail<lb/>
and accuracy, and their stipple engravings, which when seen en masse can appear<lb/>
repetitive and somewhat mechanical.<lb/>
</p>
<p>The six watercolors and six drawings enliven the volume, as does Walpole’s<lb/>
“Rules for obtaining a Ticket” from the Strawberry Hill Press. But this is Straw-<lb/>
berry Hill at one remove, the images taken in the very last years of Walpole’s life,<lb/>
or after his death. There is no involvement whatever by Walpole, and also none<lb/>
by that central figure in the dissemination of Strawberry Hill Press in the years<lb/>
after Walpole’s death, Thomas Kirgate.<lb/>
</p>
<head>V</head>
<p>What our second copy of an extra-illustrated Description shows is what Kirgate<lb/>
could offer from his stock to a favored customer. The copy does not provide any<lb/>
evidence as to its original purchaser, but it was subsequently acquired by Henry<lb/>
Probasco (1820–1902), a Cincinnati hardware magnate, and was listed in the<lb/>
catalogue of his collection that he had printed in 1873—with the result that it is<lb/>
in turn listed by A. T. Hazen in his Bibliography of the Strawberry Hill Press, where<lb/>
he describes it from Probasco’s catalogue entry, and suggests that it may have<lb/>
been the copy which was lot&amp;nbsp;411 on the second day of Kirgate’s sale.<note n="14">Catalogue of the Collection of Books, Manuscripts, and Works of Art, belonging to Mr. Henry Probasco, Cincinnati, Ohio (Privately printed, 1873), 354; A.&amp;nbsp;T. Hazen, Bibliography of the Strawberry Hill Press, 127, item&amp;nbsp;3.</note> This seems<lb/>
unlikely, as lot&amp;nbsp;411 is simply described as being the 1784 edition with plates, with<lb/>
no suggestion that it was extra-illustrated over and above the standard plates<lb/>
with which it was issued (none of the copies of the Description in Kirgate’s sale<lb/>
are described as extra-illustrated), and it is more likely that Kirgate sold the copy<lb/>
before his death. Curiously, what both Hazen and Lewis appear not to have real-<lb/>
ized was that in 1889 Probasco, who had suffered financial losses, sold his collec-<lb/>
tion to the Newberry Library, Chicago, which is where the book remains.<note n="15">Newberry Library Folio Case W&amp;nbsp;3945&amp;nbsp;95.</note> Had<lb/>
Lewis, that most resourceful and imaginative of collectors, become aware that an<lb/>
untraced extra-illustrated Description with unknown original drawings was resting<lb/>
undisturbed in the stacks of the Newberry, the Director would no doubt have<lb/>
received a visit with an irresistible offer to purchase alternative volumes more<lb/>
central to the Newberry’s core collection, in return for Probasco’s copy joining<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="241"/>
<p>the wealth of extra-illustrated examples of the Description at Farmington. But<lb/>
Probasco’s copy has stayed at the Newberry and has never been fully described.<lb/>
The book is half-bound in mid nineteenth-century red morocco, with the<lb/>
Newberry’s label dated 1890 identifying it as part of Probasco’s collection. Many<lb/>
of the illustrations are annotated by Kirgate, but none of his notes are on the<lb/>
sheets of the bound volume, which would have been bound up after his death.<lb/>
The annotations consist of two notes in ink by Walpole, one recording the price<lb/>
he paid for Reynolds’s painting of the Ladies Waldegrave in the Refectory, the<lb/>
other mentioned below; twenty-two notes in ink on the prints and drawings by<lb/>
Kirgate; two images inscribed by G. P. Harding; pencil numbers by an unidenti-<lb/>
fied hand, giving the page numbers of the text in which the items illustrated are<lb/>
described; and a few pencil notes in an unidentified hand, identifying the illus-<lb/>
trations, and in one case mentioning the 1842 sale of the collection, so possibly<lb/>
made by whoever is responsible for the present binding.</p>
<p>As for the illustrations, these break down as thirty-four miscellaneous engrav-<lb/>
ings; twenty-five portrait prints in stipple after drawings by Silvester Harding and<lb/>
published by the Hardings, nine of which also appear in the Huntington copy;<lb/>
three portrait prints by the Hardings but published by others; four watercolors<lb/>
by George Harding of items at Strawberry Hill, including two drawings of chim-<lb/>
ney pieces at the house; eight drawings unsigned but I believe by the Hardings,<lb/>
mostly of seals, but including a watercolor of the oaken Gothic bench in the<lb/>
Chapel in the Woods mentioned on page 81 of the Description; five signed colored<lb/>
drawings by or prints colored by Kirgate; seven unsigned drawings by Kirgate;<lb/>
and twelve other drawings.</p>
<p>The combination of prints, of drawings by Kirgate and the Hardings, and<lb/>
of Kirgate’s notes on them, make this a volume of real interest: but the excite-<lb/>
ment lies in the last group, the twelve other drawings, as this is where the book<lb/>
has most to tell us about the creation of Strawberry Hill, displaying the potential<lb/>
for extra-illustrated copies to illuminate their subjects. Some are alternative ver-<lb/>
sions of known images, such as a watercolor by Edwards of the south front of<lb/>
the house that was subsequently engraved in etching and aquatint by Jukes, and<lb/>
a copy colored by Edwards of the etching by Jukes of the Printing House; there<lb/>
is an unsigned pencil sketch of the Gothic lantern in the hall, similar to the fin-<lb/>
ished watercolor in Bawtree’s copy of the Description; an unsigned wash drawing,<lb/>
perhaps by Kirgate or one of the Hardings, of the couvre-feu in the library, of<lb/>
which Carter’s drawing is in Bull’s copy; and a finished wash drawing, perhaps<lb/>
by George Harding, of the urn erected by Walpole to commemorate the actress<lb/>
Kitty Clive, related to the drawing in Walpole’s own copy of the Description.<note n="16">For the two Edwards views see Clarke, The Strawberry Hill Press &amp; its Printing House, plates 28 and 25; for the urn to Mrs. Clive, see the frontispiece to Horace Walpole’s Fugitive Verses, ed. W. S. Lewis (New York and London: Oxford University Press and Humphrey Milford, 1931).</note></p>
<p>Of the seven other images, two (facing page 32) are drawings of a previously<lb/>
unrecorded design by Carter of a series of shields each impaled over a trefoil so as<lb/>
to form an inverted triangle that would have provided a series of inverted triangles<lb/>
to fill the areas above the Gothic arched arcading over the bookshelves in the Li-<lb/>
brary. One of these drawings, with the shield blank, is inscribed by Kirgate “Sketch<lb/>
…”.</p>
<pb n="242"/>
by Carter, for the Library” (figure 1) while the other, in which Walpole’s arms<lb/>
have been sketched in to the shield, is inscribed by George Harding “Taken from<lb/>
a Sketch by Carter for the Library at Strawberry Hill.” These triangular designs<lb/>
have not been previously recorded, though there is a reference in Walpole’s<lb/>
Strawberry Hill Accounts under 22 October 1789 “for painting Triangles in the library<lb/>
£6 – 6 – 0,” the relevance of which has not previously been clearly understood.<note n="17">Strawberry&amp;nbsp;Hill Accounts: A Record of Expenditure in Building Furnishing, &amp;c. Kept by Horace&amp;nbsp;Walpole From&amp;nbsp;1747 to&amp;nbsp;1795, ed.&amp;nbsp;Paget Toynbee (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1927), 18 and 175, note 9.</note> If<lb/>
the painted triangles were realized, we do not know when they were painted over,<lb/>
but they would have represented Carter’s only known design contribution to the<lb/>
building, as opposed to watercolors and drawings recording it. In any event, if one<lb/>
looks at any of the surviving views of the interior of the Library one can see how a<lb/>
succession of shields on trefoils running around the room, immediately beneath the<lb/>
armorial fantasy of the painted ceiling, would have enriched its heraldic impact.<note n="18">See Snodin, <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill</hi>, 37, figure 52 for Edwards’s watercolor of the Library and 234, figure 260 for Carter’s watercolor.</note><lb/>
<lb/>
Three of the remaining images are wash drawings of chimney pieces. A num-<lb/>
ber of the chimney pieces at Strawberry Hill were designed by Richard Bentley<lb/>
(1708 – 82), son of the great classicist of the same name, who with Walpole and<lb/>
John Chute (1701 – 76) made up the Committee that was responsible for the de-<lb/>
veloping design of the house in the 1750s. Bentley’s contributions are marked by<lb/>
a creative excess of decorative Gothic and rococo detail. One of the drawings of<lb/>
chimney pieces designed by Bentley, pasted into the endpapers of the book, ap-<lb/>
pears to be by George Harding and is inscribed “Chimney in Red Bedchamber”<lb/>
by Kirgate, who has added measurements. More important, though, is a wash<lb/>
drawing facing page 15, which is inscribed in Walpole’s own hand “Chimney<lb/>
piece of the little parlour at Strawberry hill, taken from a tomb in Westminster<lb/>
Abbey” (figure 2). It is a design drawing with the left jamb of the chimney piece<lb/>
only outlined, and with a plan of the base of the right jamb and measurements<lb/>
given for the opening. It also shows mantling around the shield, which is not<lb/>
present in the surviving chimney piece, or in the similar but finished drawing in<lb/>
Bull’s copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>. The text of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> does not specify the de-<lb/>
signer, but the image relates in the use of wash and looseness of line to the Bentley<lb/>
chimney piece designs at the Lewis Walpole Library, both stylistically and in the<lb/>
paper used, though the paper on which those designs are drawn has been given<lb/>
a brown wash.<note n="19">Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University, Bentley Album, 49 35 85.</note> And on closer inspection the mantling consists of writhing ser-<lb/>
pents’ heads, a conceit that Bentley was also to use in the charged and disturbing<lb/>
fantasy known as <hi rend="italic">A Prospect of Vapourland</hi> of 1759.<note n="20">Yale Centre for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection, accession&amp;nbsp;no.&amp;nbsp;B1975.3.188. It is discussed in Loftus Jestin, <hi rend="italic">The Answer to the Lyre: Richard Bentley’s Illustrations for Thomas Gray’s Poems</hi> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1990), 196–198, and illustrated at figure 62, and also illustrated in Snodin, <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill</hi>, 335, figure 360.</note> Apart from the mantling and<lb/>
the Walpole’s family crest of a Turk’s head above the shield, the drawing is virtu-<lb/>
ally indistinguishable from the chimney piece as built. Walpole’s inscription does<lb/>
not mention Bentley’s name any more than does the text of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>, but<lb/>
the drawing provides a strong case for Bentley’s being responsible for the design.<lb/>
<pb n="243"/>
<milestone unit="horizontalRule" rend="hr"/>
<figure>
<figDesc>figure 1. Sketch by Carter, for the Library. John Carter, the inscription in the hand of Thomas Kirgate.<lb/>Ink and wash on paper, 17 × 27 cm. Facing p. 33 of Probasco’s copy of the Descrip-<lb/>tion of Strawberry Hill, Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95. Photo courtesy of Newberry<lb/>Library, Chicago.</figDesc>

</figure>
<p>The third image, though also unsigned, is clearly by Bentley. It is an unre-<lb/>corded, unexecuted scheme for an original and idiosyncratic chimney piece de-<lb/>sign, the jambs faced with pyramidal forms topped with flambeaux, with a half<lb/>quatrefoil over the lintel within an arched hood, topped with another flambeau<lb/>reflecting those above the jambs (figure 3). A vase is placed within the reveal of the<lb/>quatrefoil, with small pots to either side, and there are two other vases in outline<lb/>behind the flambeaux at the head of each jamb. Like the Little Parlour drawing, it<lb/>relates directly to the Bentley chimney piece designs at the Lewis Walpole Library.<lb/>Both stylistically and in similarity in format to those designs it seems clearly to be<lb/>by Bentley and might conceivably be a preliminary design for the China Room or<lb/>perhaps the Waiting Room. It is a vibrant and idiosyncratic design, consistent with<lb/>Bentley’s surviving chimney pieces in the Beauty Room and the Blue Bedchamber.</p>
<p>The two remaining drawings are more problematical. One is a scaled perspec-<lb/>tive line drawing for what was known as the trunk-ceiled passage that linked the<lb/>Holbein Chamber and Star Chamber to the Gallery, and is inscribed in George<lb/>Harding’s hand “Trunk ceiled passage Strawberry Hill.” The drawing, also</p>
<pb n="244"/>
<figure>
  <head>figure 2.</head>
  <figDesc>Chimney piece of the little parlour at Strawberry hill, taken from a tomb in Westminster Abbey.<lb/>
Richard Bentley attrib., the inscription in the hand of Horace Walpole. Wash drawing on paper, 21 × 17.3 cm.<lb/>
Facing p. 15 of Probasco’s copy of the Description of Strawberry Hill, Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95.<lb/>
Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<pb n="245"/>
<figure>
  
  <figDesc>
    figure 3. Richard Bentley, unexecuted chimney piece for Strawberry Hill. Wash drawing on<lb/>
    paper, 14.3 × 11.9 cm. Facing p. 23 of Probasco’s copy of the Description of Strawberry Hill,<lb/>
    Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95. Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.
  </figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="246"/>
<figure>
  <figDesc>figure 4.<lb/>Plan for A Gothic Mirror at Strawberry hill.<lb/>Unsigned pencil drawing on paper, 27.4 × 19 cm.<lb/>Facing p. 13 of Probasco’s copy of the Description of Strawberry Hill, Newberry Library Folio Case W 3945 95.<lb/>Photo courtesy of Newberry Library, Chicago.</figDesc>
  
</figure>
<p>previously unknown, shows the applied wooden moldings that line the passage,<lb/>
 the rounded ceiling, and at the end of the passage the arched window that was<lb/>
 subsequently removed when the passage was extended in the nineteenth century<lb/>
 to connect through to the Great North Bedchamber. It appears to be a design<lb/>
 drawing, perhaps associated with Chute, but it is Harding who has inscribed it.<lb/>
 The final drawing is inscribed by Kirgate “Plan for a Gothic Mirror at Straw-<lb/>
 berry hill” (figure 4). It has measurements in ink in feet and inches, a sketch plan<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="247"/>
<p>
<lb/>of the projecting canopy above, and a note at the side “a. looking glass / no back.<lb/>from the canopy / to the glass / Canopy projects,” that appears to be in Bentley’s<lb/>hand, though the drawing (as opposed to the design) is not immediately recogniz-<lb/>able as Bentley’s. The design consists of a projecting arched and pierced canopy<lb/>over a mirror of quatrefoil shape with pointed projections, and the pierced canopy<lb/>closely relates to the pierced canopy of the chimney piece in the Refectory as<lb/>designed by Bentley. It seems most likely that the drawing, whoever it is by, is of<lb/>an unrealized Bentley design, and I am indebted to Michael Snodin for the sug-<lb/>gestion that it may have been an early design for the mirrors on either side of the<lb/>window in the Refectory. The proportions of the sections of wall on either side of<lb/>the Refectory window are consistent with the area of wall shown in the drawing,<lb/>and the overall size of the mirror as shown in the drawing is broadly similar to<lb/>that of the mirrors actually commissioned for these positions, which are arched<lb/>and with Gothic moldings and a portrait roundel beneath the top of the arch.<note n="21">Snodin, <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill</hi>, 36, figure 51.</note>
<lb/>The Newberry volume shows how a selection of the Hardings’ prints and<lb/>drawings could be supplemented and enhanced from Kirgate’s extensive stock,<lb/>and enriched by drawings of unexecuted designs so as to convert that extra-<lb/>illustrated copy into a living part of the unfolding story of the development of<lb/>Walpole’s house and collection. But that sense of immediacy with the creation of<lb/>the house and its collection is, if anything, only strengthened with the last of our<lb/>three copies of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi>.
</p>
<head>VI</head>
<p>
<lb/>The third copy of the <hi rend="italic">Description</hi> differs most immediately from the other two in<lb/>that with the exception of two unsigned drawings, and six small pencil sketches<lb/>probably by Kirgate, it has no illustrations—not even the twenty-eight plates<lb/>that Walpole commissioned for the 1784 edition. It is a proof copy, interleaved,<lb/>and bound in early nineteenth-century half calf. Now in the collection of Charles<lb/>Sebag-Montefiore, it more than makes up for its lack of plates by its wealth of ad-<lb/>ditional material and annotation. It opens with a transcription dated 6 February<lb/>1780 by Kirgate on one folded leaf of the sixth and last of Walpole’s fantastical<lb/><hi rend="italic">Hieroglyphic Tales</hi>, “A True Love Story,” tipped into the front endpapers. Wal-<lb/>pole had written the <hi rend="italic">Tales</hi> by 1772, but they were not printed by Kirgate at the<lb/>Strawberry Hill Press until 1785, and then in only seven copies. This holograph<lb/>therefore pre-dates the first printing and was presumably copied from Walpole’s<lb/>manuscript. A comparison with the text as first printed five years later shows that<lb/>the printed text did not follow Kirgate’s capitalization or repeat one spelling er-<lb/>ror, and it expanded some abbreviations (presumably it would have been taken<lb/>from Walpole’s manuscript), but the differences are not significant.<note n="22">See <hi rend="italic">Hieroglyphic Tales</hi>, Kenneth W. Gross (London: Pallas Athene, 2011).</note>
<lb/>Also among the preliminary pages at the front are a drawing pasted down<lb/>of Walpole’s coat of arms resting on three of the books he had written, with<lb/>Strawberry Hill in the distance; and a pencil drawing of an ossuarium from the<lb/>Armoury. There are in addition two separate lists complied by Kirgate both
</p>
<pb n="248"/>
headed “Index of Rooms,” giving page numbers of the 1784 edition. At the foot <lb/>
of the second Index Kirgate has added a pencil note giving information on the <lb/>
number of visitors to the house:<lb/>
In 1786, Eighty tickets were given to different People for admission to view <lb/>
Strawberry Hill<lb/>
In 1787, Seventy Ditto were given<lb/>
In 1789, One Hundred were given<lb/>
In 1807, Mrs. Damer says about 80 or 90 are used yearly<lb/>
Upon an average, about 80 were given yearly<lb/>
For the period 1784–96 we have Walpole’s manuscript “Book of Visitors,” <lb/>
which broadly confirms the first three entries, but there is no comparable evidence <lb/>
for the number of visitors after his death in the years of Anne Damer’s occupa-<lb/>
tion.<note n="23">“Book of Visitors,” Percival Merritt Collection, Houghton Library, Harvard University, M.S. Eng. 1502, printed in Yale Edition of Horace Walpole’s Correspondence, 12: 216–252.</note> The note also confirms that the volume, in which the earliest entries are <lb/>
proofing corrections that are part of the process of printing the 1784 Description, <lb/>
was annotated by Kirgate until at least 1807, only three years before his own death.<lb/>
Between the two versions of the Index of Rooms is a list in pencil by Kirgate <lb/>
headed “The following Drawings were made by Mr. Carter for Mr. Bull &amp; Mr. <lb/>
Walpole” (see appendix below). It lists thirty-six drawings created for Bull’s copy <lb/>
of the Description, while five of them were also in Walpole’s. One drawing, “Gal-<lb/>
lery 10 G[uineas],” is crossed through and marked “bought by Mr. Baker”—<lb/>
presumably the Strawberry Hill Press collector and bibliographer George Baker <lb/>
(1781–1858). It is correct that Bull’s copy, despite its wealth of Carter watercolors <lb/>
and drawings, does not have his view of the Gallery.<lb/>
But as well as this additional material, there are many annotations to the text <lb/>
by Kirgate, for this is his interleaved proof copy of the 1784 text. It preserves a <lb/>
number of cancels that were corrected in the text as issued, and contains numer-<lb/>
ous notes by him as the orchestrator of extra-illustration, and even a few notes <lb/>
inserted or initiated by Walpole that throw shafts of light on Walpole’s last years <lb/>
at Strawberry Hill. It is very likely that this is the copy that was lot 413 on the <lb/>
eighth day of the sale of Kirgate’s library, where it was described as “containing <lb/>
many Notes in MS. by T. Kirgate,” and was bought by George Baker for £16. <lb/>
At Baker’s sale in 1825, it appears among some seventy-six Strawberry Hill Press <lb/>
and related books and ephemera as “A Description of Strawberry Hill, with sev-<lb/>
eral loose pieces interleaved, with M.S. memoranda throughout.” It was bought <lb/>
by Longman for a far more modest £1.19s., a reflection of the depression in book <lb/>
prices that was to be lamented in Dibdin’s Bibliophobia (1832).<note n="24">A Catalogue of the Valuable and Curious Collection, late the Property of Mr. Thomas Kirgate, of Vine-Street, Piccadilly (Deceased) … King &amp; Lochée, 3 December 1810 and nine following days: Day 8, lot 413; and A Catalogue of the Very Choice and Select Library of the late George Baker, Esq. of St. Paul’s Churchyard … Sotheby, 6 June 1825 and two following days: Day 3, lot 822.</note><lb/>
To begin with Walpole’s notes, these are only on the text pages (pre-dating <lb/>
the book’s being bound up interleaved) and are limited but essentially correc-<lb/>
</div>