<div type="section" n="8">
  <head>Charles Dibdin & the Making of The Musical Tour of Mr. Dibdin (1788): A New “Compact with the Public”</head>
<pb n="249"/>
<p>tive, and largely relate to those sections of the proof that were cancelled so that<lb/>
corrected text could be printed. Sections D, E, L, and O are cancels, and in the<lb/>
case of section O there are two variant cancels: in one Kirgate has noted the need<lb/>
to add “A small whole length of Dryden, in oil, by Maubert” as the third line of<lb/>
“More Additions” on page 93, and in the other he has marked a change to the<lb/>
heading of page 94. It is possible that some of the minor typographical correc-<lb/>
tions on these pages may be by Walpole rather than Kirgate, but certainly Wal-<lb/>
pole wrote the notes on page 26, crossing through in ink an entry for James 5th<lb/>
and Mary of Lorraine his Queen, a watercolor by Wale, adding the instructions<lb/>
“This is now in the Holbein Room, where you must insert it,” and adding against<lb/>
a Flemish picture of Boors reading “it was in Sir R. Walpole’s collection”—which<lb/>
note duly appears in the printed text of the corrected sheet.<lb/>
There are notes by Walpole adding anecdotal details and provenance infor-<lb/>
mation to the printed text, while his correction on page 24 of Benedict 13th to<lb/>
Benedict 14th has Kirgate’s marginal note “worked so.” That is Kirgate speaking<lb/>
as printer, and another, later example appears on page 92, which concludes the<lb/>
Appendix: “The small 4to. Edit [that is, the original edition of 1774] was printed as<lb/>
far as here, but the Preface was not, I believe, printed for it.” This must have been<lb/>
written by Kirgate as an older man, as he himself had printed the preface in 1786.<lb/>
There is a sense of conversations overheard, as in Kirgate’s note on page 67,<lb/>
on the famous silver bell in the Tribune attributed to Cellini, “Mr. W called it, as<lb/>
Madame de Montbazon was called, ‘La Belle des Belles.’” Similarly, there is his<lb/>
note at the foot of page 56, devoted to the cabinet of miniatures in the Tribune:<lb/>
“This Collection cost Mr. W upwards of 1300£” immediately followed by “Co-<lb/>
lumb [Walpole’s manservant] says under 1200£,” while of the cameo of Tiberius<lb/>
in onyx in the box of antique rings in the Tribune he adds “Mr. W. says, very<lb/>
fine.” Some notes serve as an aide memoire, as on page 34, against the account<lb/>
of a brass padlock in the shape of a hand, he writes “ask Carter for this” [that is,<lb/>
for a drawing of it]. Again, against the footnote on page 65 describing a table of<lb/>
polished pebbles at Chiswick House, he notes “Go to Chiswick to see it.”<lb/>
We also get a sense of items in the collection moving around and out of the<lb/>
house, as in Kirgate’s comment on page 73 that the whole-length portrait of<lb/>
Henry Vere, Earl of Oxford, in the Great North Bedchamber was “Now on the<lb/>
back Stairs” and a landscape by Müntz after Gaspar Poussin had been moved<lb/>
to the Little Parlour, while Vanloo’s whole-length portrait of Sir Robert Walpole<lb/>
was “Removed, and given I think to Mrs. Keppel.”<lb/>
For some items in the collection Kirgate provides supplemental information.<lb/>
Of the Turkish dagger (now lost) believed by Walpole to have belonged to Henry<lb/>
VIII and displayed in the Tribune he notes that “on one side of the Blade are<lb/>
Arabic Characters in Gold. The Handle and Case have on them, 127 Rubies and<lb/>
6 Diamonds.” He also notes the verses written by Walpole on the back of Lady<lb/>
Craven’s picture and the verses on the stand of the Sevres figure of Cupid, both<lb/>
in the Breakfast Room.<lb/>
Kirgate’s entry on page 3, “The Staircase and Hall were repainted, in 1793,<lb/>
by Mr. Cornelius Dixon, in a much more accurate and picturesque Stile, tho from<lb/>
the same model, and cost 250-12-6,” supplements the entry in the Strawberry Hill<lb/>
Accounts and (within two shillings) confirms the cost, while the final blank leaf<lb/>
of the book has Kirgate’s note identifying the builder and cost of the offices that<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="250"/>
Walpole had built in about 1790—he also added to the Directions to the Binder<lb/>
the titles of the two plates of offices, engraved after the sheet had been printed<lb/>
off.<note n="25">Strawberry Hill Accounts, 20 and 179, note 1; and Clarke, “Lord God! Jesus! What a House!” 380, note 41.</note> Other entries illustrating life at the house include Kirgate’s note against<lb/>
the description of the building of the Gallery and Round Tower that “Cowie,<lb/>
the Gardiner, says he placed Medals and a Copper-plate, with an Inscription,<lb/>
on the Foundation Stone of the above Buildings, which is under the Scullery of<lb/>
the Round Kitchen.” Equally evocative is his recording that most of the small<lb/>
Etruscan and black Staffordshire vases in the Little Library in the Cottage in the<lb/>
Garden “were broke by an Owl getting down the Chimney into the Room.”<lb/>
Of particular importance are two short lists, the first at the end of the More<lb/>
Additions appendix on page 96, the other on one of the blank leaves at the back.<lb/>
They record late acquisitions for the collection, after the printing of More Additions<lb/>
in 1791. Timothy Wilson has quoted Walpole’s letter to Sir Horace Mann<lb/>
of 1785, in which he asks him to find some examples of a particular Florentine<lb/>
ceramics manufacture, and then adds “but am I not an old simpleton to be wanting<lb/>
playthings still?”<note n="26">Timothy Wilson, “‘Playthings Still?’ Horace Walpole as a Collector of Ceramics,” in Snodin, <hi rend="italic">Horace Walpole’s Strawberry Hill</hi>, 200–219, at 201. The letter is in <hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>, 25: 590.</note> These lists show the elderly Walpole, still adding to the<lb/>
collection to within three years of his death. The first list is:<lb/>
Brown earthen Miraculous Pitcher—Earthen Bottle, labelled, Claret<lb/>
A Miniature in enamel of [gap] Lord Bute, by Spencer; bought at Dalton’s Sale,<lb/>
1791.<lb/>
Six Portraits, with Pen and ink, of Mr. Walpole, Mr. Chute, Mr. Spence, &amp;c.<lb/>
drawn by Rosalba, when those Gentlemen were in Italy, unknown to them,<lb/>
when at some public Place; yet very like<lb/>
Dead Christ, by Carrache, small oil painting on Copper, from Sir Laurence<lb/>
Dundas’s Sale, in 1794.<lb/>
Miniature Portrait of Charles James Stuart, eldest son of the Pretender; Given<lb/>
by Mrs. Hunter, in 1794.<lb/>
The second has five more items:<lb/>
A carved Ivory Cup, with a Bacchanalian Procession, in relievo, set in Silver,<lb/>
with the Orford Crest on the Cover; from Houghton.<lb/>
Two Cocoa Nuts, carved with the Arms of Orford, and mounted with Silver gilt<lb/>
feet; from Ditto, 1793.<lb/>
Two silver filigraine Hampers; from Ditto, 1794.<lb/>
A Portrait of the Rev. William Cole, of Botesham Hall, Cambridge, on painted<lb/>
Glass.<lb/>
<pb n="251"/>
<p>A Cast in Plaister of Miss Farren, from a bust in marble, executed by Mrs. Damer<lb/>
Of these, three are Walpole silver, presumably acquired through family piety,<lb/>
and two come from sales of 1791 and 1794. One is a gift, and one a plaster bust of<lb/>
the actress Elizabeth Farren by his admired cousin. The portraits by Rosalba are<lb/>
curious—it would be surprising that they only came into Walpole’s possession<lb/>
in the 1790s, over fifty years after his Grand Tour, and some years after all the<lb/>
other persons mentioned had died; or perhaps they were existing possessions that<lb/>
had not previously been listed. And the portrait on glass of his correspondent,<lb/>
the antiquary William Cole, who had died in 1782, is intriguing. Some of the<lb/>
Rosalbas are at The Vyne ( John Chute’s house), the carved ivory cup is in the<lb/>
Derby collection at Knowsley Hall, and the mounted coconuts are in a private<lb/>
collection: the rest have disappeared, but the group of items do display the still<lb/>
dedicated collector, adding to his treasures and adorning his house to the last.<lb/>
There are, however, three topics that constitute by far the largest number<lb/>
of Kirgate’s annotations. The first of these is the cost of items—what Walpole<lb/>
had paid for them. These can be treated anecdotally, as in Kirgate’s note at the<lb/>
foot of page&amp;nbsp;72 of the painting over the chimney piece of the Great North Bed-<lb/>
chamber: “the Picture of Henry&amp;nbsp;8th. and Children, which Mr. Walpole bought<lb/>
for 80 Guineas, was formerly sold on London Bridge for 5 Pounds.” Of the bust<lb/>
of Vespasian in the Gallery described at page&amp;nbsp;50 he comments “it was reckoned<lb/>
the 7th Bust in Rome, and cost under 20£,” while the Boccapadugli eagle in the<lb/>
Gallery “Cost but 50£. Mr.&amp;nbsp;W. has been offered 1000£ for it. The pedestal cost<lb/>
25£.” Mostly, though, he simply notes the price paid by Walpole in the margin<lb/>
against objects, doing so for about fifty-five of them.<lb/>
The other two series of annotations bring us back to Kirgate as dealer in prints<lb/>
of the collection. They are notes as to whether there are available prints of items<lb/>
in the collection, and descriptions of the poses of portraits. There are over 130<lb/>
notes querying whether a print or drawing exists, or if there is a print, by whom<lb/>
it is engraved. At the foot of page&amp;nbsp;24 of the book, for example, the text lists three<lb/>
portraits in the Green Closet, of Henry Carey, Earl of Monmouth, Pope Benedict<lb/>
XII, and Lady Newburgh: against the first two Kirgate has noted “Engraved by<lb/>
S.&amp;nbsp;Harding,” but against the third he has written “Q.&amp;nbsp;if engraved by Harding?”<lb/>
and added “No. But I have a copy by Harding.” On the preceding page, against<lb/>
Scott’s view of Pope’s house in Twickenham, he asks “See if Sayer has not a<lb/>
Print like this”—a reference to the printseller Robert Sayer (1725–94). There<lb/>
are page after page of such entries, many just noting that there is a mezzotint, or<lb/>
an engraving by Harding, or noting a print’s scarcity: as a random selection, of<lb/>
the Maid of Honour Mrs.&amp;nbsp;Trevor “No Print in that name in Bromley [Bromley’s<lb/>
Catalogue of Engraved British Portraits (1793)] Q.&amp;nbsp;was She married? Drawing of her<lb/>
by G.&amp;nbsp;Harding”; various notes as to whether antiquities that Walpole had bought<lb/>
from Conyers Middleton were engraved in his Antiquities (1745); and of an antique<lb/>
silver figure of a seated muse in the Tribune Kirgate writes “Beg a Drawing of<lb/>
it,” to remind himself to ask (presumably) Mrs.&amp;nbsp;Damer for permission to have it<lb/>
copied. But especially revealing is his comment on the ancient oak chair in the<lb/>
Holbein Chamber that Walpole believed to have come from Glastonbury Abbey:<lb/>
“Engraved by Captn.&amp;nbsp;Grose, Prints of which may be had of T.&amp;nbsp;Kirgate.”</p>
<pb n="252"/>
<p>Almost as frequent, though, are Kirgate’s annotations as to the poses of<lb/>
portraits at Strawberry Hill. There are approximately one hundred of these,<lb/>
carefully written out in pencil. A good example of this is provided by the nineteen<lb/>
heads in oil from the Court of Charles II, copied by Jarvis, and hung by Walpole<lb/>
in the Beauty Room. Kirgate has numbered these from 1 to 19 and written out<lb/>
descriptions of them on the facing interleaved blank sheet. There is, for instance,<lb/>
King William when Prince of Orange, “In armour, truncheon in right hand, left<lb/>
on a helmet, point cravat, dog’s head looking up, battle in the background,” and<lb/>
Frances Stuart, Duchess of Richmond, “Standing in a wood, leaning on left arm<lb/>
on bank, right cross’d to ditto, mantle tied with pearls over left breast, curl on<lb/>
ditto.” For a number of the portraits, Kirgate’s notes seek to distinguish between<lb/>
the Strawberry Hill picture and other similar prints: from the same group of<lb/>
nineteen, there is Henry, Earl of Ogle (with in his case an additional note in ink<lb/>
“No Print of him”), described as “Standing, full faced, flowing hair, point cravat,<lb/>
left hand in robe, right hand pointing with fore finger, Curtain behind. A print<lb/>
of Sir Thomas Isham, Bart (D. Loggan exct.) is exactly like this of Ogle, except<lb/>
the face. A ditto of Sir [blank] Fielding is also, the face excepted, more so.” He<lb/>
is followed in the list by Lady Elizabeth Percy, later Duchess of Somerset “Sit-<lb/>
ting on a bank, supported by right hand, left pointing to a parrot in an orange<lb/>
tree in a vase, lock of hair on left breast, column at left”: this has two additional<lb/>
notes on the text page “Mezzo[tint] Print of her, sold by Browne,” and “A Print<lb/>
of Madam Lucy Loftus is much like the Dss. of Somerset.”</p>
<p>What these notes represent is Kirgate’s index for identifying prints from<lb/>
Strawberry Hill portraits when he did not have the originals in front of him.<lb/>
If he were to see in the London print trade a mezzotint of a Lady Elizabeth<lb/>
Percy, he could turn to his notes to see if the print showed her pointing to the<lb/>
required parrot in an orange tree, and if so it could be added to stock for his<lb/>
Strawberry Hill customers. There is even a memorandum to himself “remr.<lb/>
to describe this” against the Van Dyck of Soldiers at Cards, in the manner of<lb/>
Teniers, in the Tribune. The notes serve a similar function of identification to<lb/>
the briefer summaries of poses that appear in some of the entries in Granger’s<lb/>
Biographical History.</p>
<p>It is no surprise that Kirgate kept the book until his death, for the function<lb/>
of this copy had been transformed. What had started as a proof copy with his<lb/>
master’s corrections had been interleaved, and become a repository for infor-<lb/>
mation and anecdote, opening a window onto Walpole’s last thirteen years at<lb/>
Strawberry Hill. It had then become the essential reference source for Kirgate’s<lb/>
later career as book and printseller and purveyor of illustrations of the house<lb/>
and its collections. This was a cottage industry by which—as the three copies<lb/>
of the Description discussed in this paper illustrate—he and the Harding family<lb/>
not only helped to support themselves, but disseminated to a wider audience<lb/>
Walpole’s vision of Strawberry Hill. The second and third of these volumes pro-<lb/>
vide a wealth of supplemental information and some previously unknown design<lb/>
drawings for Strawberry Hill—but all three together also give us an unusual<lb/>
opportunity to see extra-illustration and annotation from the perspective of the<lb/>
booksellers, printsellers and artists who facilitated the leisured amusement of a<lb/>
generation of collectors.</p>
<pb n="253"/>
<head>APPENDIX</head><lb/>
<p>In his annotated proof copy of the Description of Strawberry Hill, Thomas Kir-<lb/>gate listed the following thirty-six drawings by John Carter for Richard Bull’s <lb/>extra-illustrated copy of the Description (B) and those of them that were also in <lb/>Walpole’s copy (W).</p><lb/>
<p>The following Drawings were made by Mr. Carter for Mr. Bull &amp; Mr. Walpole<lb/>
B Great Cloyster W.<lb/>
B Red Hall W.<note n="27">The entrance hall is also referred to as the “Red Hall” in Carter’s list of his drawings for Bull in his copy of the Description at the Huntington Library, and it does appear from his watercolor that it had red floor tiles.</note><lb/>
B Parlour<lb/>
B Holbein Room<lb/>
B Round Room<lb/>
B Passage to Gallery<lb/>
B Great Bedchamber<lb/>
B Prior’s Garden W.<lb/>
B Cabinet of Enamels<lb/>
B Printing House, inside view<lb/>
B Sceptre &amp; Dagger &amp; Missal<lb/>
B Becket’s tomb &amp; Chalice<lb/>
B Tomb in Chapel<lb/>
B Crucifix in Chapel<lb/>
B Figures of Window of Do.<lb/>
B North Front<lb/>
B Round Tower<lb/>
B Obelisk; poor<note n="28">This and the two preceding items are bracketed together as “Views.”</note><lb/>
B Dia Helenora in Little Cloyster<note n="29">Described by Walpole in a footnote to page&amp;nbsp;2 of the Description as a bas-relief head in marble of Eleanora d’Este, inscribed Dia&amp;nbsp;Helianora.</note><lb/>
B Implements of War in Armory<lb/>
B Little Cloyster<lb/>
B Inside of Oratory<lb/>
B Four old Pictures in Chapel<lb/>
B Chair in Holbein Room<lb/>
B The Armoury W<lb/>
B View of the House from Offices<lb/>
B Library W<lb/>
B Gallery 10G. bought by Mr. Baker<lb/>
B Urns in Gallery<lb/>
B Bust of Nic. Poussin’s Wife<lb/>
B Ditto of Caligula and another<lb/>
B Ditto of Jupiter Serapis<lb/>
B Egyptian Idols<lb/>
B Ground Plan of Strawberry<lb/>
B Castle of Otranto<lb/>
Drawings at 2.2.0 each is 75.12.0<note n="30">From the list in the Appendix, Carter’s watercolors are reproduced in Snodin, Horace Walpole’s <hi rend="italic">Strawberry Hill</hi>, as follows: Red Hall (33, fig.&amp;nbsp;45), Parlour (35, fig.&amp;nbsp;48), Holbein Room (43, fig.&amp;nbsp;61), Round Room (48, fig.&amp;nbsp;72), Passage to Gallery (301, fig.&amp;nbsp;326), Great Bedchamber (50, fig.&amp;nbsp;77), Cabinet of Enamels (99, fig.&amp;nbsp;128), Printing House, inside view (243, fig.&amp;nbsp;274), Sceptre &amp; Dagger &amp; Missal (226, fig.&amp;nbsp;253), Tomb in Chapel (147, fig.&amp;nbsp;163), Round Tower (253, fig.&amp;nbsp;282), Implements of War in Armory (224, fig.&amp;nbsp;251), The Armoury (220, fig.&amp;nbsp;245), Library (234, fig.&amp;nbsp;260), Bust of Caligula [though alone, not with another] (176, fig.&amp;nbsp;187), and Bust of Jupiter Serapis (176, fig.&amp;nbsp;188).</note></p>
<pb n="254"/>
<pb n="255"/>
<head>CHARLES DIBDIN AND THE MAKING OF<lb/>
THE MUSICAL TOUR OF MR. DIBDIN (1788):<lb/>
A NEW “COMPACT WITH THE PUBLIC”</head>
<byline><hi rend="italic">by</hi><lb/><name type="pname">David Chandler</name></byline>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">O</hi>n 17 March 1787, Charles Dibdin (1745–1814) took the stagecoach from<lb/>
London to Oxford, “with a few shirts and books in a trunk, [and] a well-<lb/>
digested plan in [his] head.”<note n="1">Charles Dibdin, <hi rend="italic">The Musical Tour of Mr. Dibdin</hi> (Sheffield, 1788), 13–14. Subsequent references are noted parenthetically in the text.</note> Famous first as an actor-singer, then as a theatre<lb/>
composer who collaborated with such luminaries as David Garrick and Isaac<lb/>
Bickerstaff, then as a writer for the theatre himself, Dibdin was “an extremely<lb/>
well-known public character”<note n="2">Oskar Cox Jensen, David Kennerley and Ian Newman (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Charles Dibdin and Late Georgian Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018), 1. This volume is the best introduction to the great variety of Dibdin’s achievements and cultural impacts, though it has little to say about him as a writer or solo performer.</note> who was now, in the spirit of entrepreneurship<lb/>
increasingly shaping his activities, seeking to integrate his talents. The “well-<lb/>
digested plan” was for a one-man musical show which Dibdin intended touring<lb/>
round the country to fund his family’s planned emigration to India; standing be-<lb/>
hind a piano (an instrument he had introduced in Britain), he would alternately<lb/>
speak and sing to his audience. By appearing as poet, composer, performer and<lb/>
“band,” Dibdin later wrote, he was doing something “so unprecedented, that<lb/>
one should rationally suppose, if it were only for the novelty, it were likely to<lb/>
attract curiosity, and ensure encouragement.”<note n="3">Charles Dibdin, <hi rend="italic">The Professional Life of Mr. Dibdin</hi>, 4 vols. (London, 1803), 1:4.</note> Readings and Music, as he called<lb/>
his entertainment, was to prove personally, professionally, even culturally trans-<lb/>
formative; with it, the second half of Dibdin’s career commenced. In the end,<lb/>
he never did go to India, but he decided that the one-man show, which he<lb/>
began calling a “Table Entertainment,” on the model of “table talk,” was his<lb/>
natural medium, and he went on developing the form. For a time, his shows<lb/>
were sensationally popular, and between 1791 and 1805 Dibdin even had his<lb/>
own London theatre, the Sans Souci, specifically to present them. The songs he<lb/>
produced for these Table Entertainments had an immense impact on the popu-<lb/>
lar song repertoire, making Dibdin overwhelmingly the leading anglophone<lb/>
singer-songwriter of the age. The form of the shows, too, had a huge influence<lb/>
on popular entertainment, almost every subsequent proponent of the one-man<lb/>
show with music owing something, directly or indirectly, to Dibdin. They very<lb/></p>
<pb n="256"/>
<p>likely also influenced the culture of London’s “song-and-supper rooms” which<lb/>
started opening in 1815—the direct ancestors of the later music hall.<note n="4">For the “song-and-supper rooms” and their place in London’s entertainment culture, see Laurence Senelick, introduction to Tavern Singing in Early Victorian London: The Diaries of Charles Rice for 1840 and 1850 (London: Society for Theatre Research, 1997), xii.</note><lb/>
The Readings and Music tour proved transformative in another way, too: it<lb/>
persuaded Dibdin that he could and should produce books. Although from the<lb/>
early 1770s onwards his literary ambitions were steadily developing, there is no<lb/>
evidence prior to 1787 of a serious interest in book production. He had published<lb/>
librettos, a polemical pamphlet, The Royal Circus Epitomized (1784), and his own<lb/>
periodical, The Devil, which ran for 22 issues in 1786 and 1787. But after his<lb/>
1787–88 tour produced the Musical Tour of Mr. Dibdin, a 450-page quarto far<lb/>
bigger in size and scope than anything he had written before, he began think-<lb/>
ing on a different scale, publishing three three-volume novels between 1793 and<lb/>
1807, a five-volume Complete History of the English Stage between 1797 and 1800,<lb/>
two large volumes of Observations on a Tour Through Almost the Whole of England, and<lb/>
a Considerable Part of Scotland in 1801 and 1802, and four volumes of The Profes-<lb/>
sional Life of Mr. Dibdin in 1803. The Musical Tour directly anticipates, in different<lb/>
ways, most of the major publications that followed. Dibdin discovered a taste for<lb/>
autobiographical writing mixed with anecdotes, opinions and polemics; although<lb/>
he has, at most, appeared as a footnote in accounts of Romantic autobiography,<lb/>
no British writer published more about themselves in the decades between 1780<lb/>
and 1810.<lb/>
Despite the great importance of the Musical Tour (hereafter MT) in Dibdin’s<lb/>
polymathic career, it is as flawed as it is fascinating. It did not develop smoothly<lb/>
and Dibdin had written much of it before deciding on the final shape and con-<lb/>
tent of the volume. Moreover, he was often juggling the historical aspects of his<lb/>
account with a desire to comment on his present circumstances. When Dibdin<lb/>
left London, he had no idea of recording his experiences: “at my first setting out<lb/>
I had not the smallest idea of writing any account of my Tour at all” (43–44).<lb/>
Not until August did he lay plans for a book, and not until October did he begin<lb/>
systematically writing it. Given that the tour itself continued until March 1788,<lb/>
this meant that for a long time Dibdin was having to catch up with himself, and<lb/>
he recognized almost immediately the parallels with Laurence Sterne’s 1760s<lb/>
novel, Tristram Shandy (10). As the project developed, it came to unite the different<lb/>
worlds of self-publishing, provincial printing, financing by subscription and—be-<lb/>
latedly—royal patronage. Scholars have paid some attention to the tour itself,<lb/>
and to Readings and Music,<note n="5">See, in particular, Elisabeth M. Lockwood, “Charles Dibdin’s Musical Tour,” Music and Letters 13, no. 2 (1932): 207–14; and Jeremy Barlow, “Dibdin on Tour: Performer or Sightseer?,” Early Music Performer 39 (October 2016): 3–8.</note> but there has been no separate analysis of the complex<lb/>
vehicle through which Dibdin preserved a record of these things. The published<lb/>
MT is the more interesting in that, uniquely among Dibdin’s major prose pub-<lb/>
lications, a complete fair copy manuscript of the book has been preserved, held<lb/>
in the Fellows’ Library at Winchester College (MS 61). Although there are few<lb/>
significant departures from this bound manuscript volume in the printed text, the<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="257"/>
<p>manuscript provides fascinating clues to the process by which the book came to be made, and it is regularly cited in the history reconstructed here.<note n="6">I am much indebted to Richard Foster, the Fellows’ Librarian, Winchester College, for allowing me access to the manuscript, for his generous hospitality when I visited Winchester, and for the information that the manuscript was donated to the College in the 1830s or 1840s by the Rev. Peter Hall (1803–49), a prolific collector of books and manuscripts and a former Winchester student. The records show that the manuscript was bound when first acquired by the College, though it was subsequently rebound in the twentieth century. The history of the manuscript before Hall acquired it, presumably no earlier than the 1820s, is unknown, but it seems likely that Dibdin’s printer, Joseph Gales, made the original decision to bind together the letters that constitute it.</note><lb/>
The story of the tour commences on page 15 of the published <hi rend="italic">MT</hi>; the history of the book about the tour effectively commences on page 91, when Dibdin describes his return to Worcester on 31 July 1787 after an earlier visit in the spring. There follows one of the most ambiguous and conflicted passages in the volume:<lb/>
“I never experienced more <hi rend="italic">milk and water</hi> treatment in my life. I advertised my entertainment however and was tolerably attended. . . . I sincerely believe, had it not been for the interference of a friend, I must have used the word <hi rend="italic">intolerably</hi>. To this gentleman, who is no other than T.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;Esq., I shall beg leave to say, that if he meant his friendship and attention to my interest should finish where it apparently has—God forbid I should load him with more trouble than he is willing to suffer! So far from it—I here, in the face of the world, acquit him of any intentions in relation to me, but those of serving, obliging, and pleasing me; and should it so happen that neither upon paper, nor any other way, we again exchange a single word, my wishes towards him are, may he enjoy a long life of health, happiness, and prosperity! And I hope he retains so much of his former good wishes for me, as to return an equal portion of esteem, with equal sincerity.” (91)<lb/>
Readers are expected to recall that the first eleven letters of the <hi rend="italic">MT</hi> had been addressed “To T.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;Esq.” Dibdin later chose to reveal the identity of this individual, for in his <hi rend="italic">Professional Life</hi> he states: “The name of Theophilus Swift, Esq. will be seen at the head of some of the poetry. . . . To this gentleman I addressed a few letters in my original Tour.”<note n="7">Dibdin, <hi rend="italic">Professional Life</hi>, 3:7.</note> Swift (1746–1815), whose parents were both cousins of Jonathan Swift, the author of <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s Travels</hi>, was an eccentric Irish barrister. The fullest contemporary description describes him as “an excellent classic <sic/> scholar, and versed likewise in modern literature and <hi rend="italic">belles lettres</hi>. . . . [He was] a sincere, kind-hearted man; but . . . at the same time, the most visionary of created beings. He saw every thing whimsically—many things erroneously—and nothing like another person.”<note n="8">Sir Jonah Barrington, <hi rend="italic">Personal Sketches of His Own Times</hi>, 2 vols. (London, 1827), 1:405–6.</note> Swift had just commenced a literary career by publishing a lengthy poem, <hi rend="italic">The Temple of Folly</hi>. It is not clear when or where he and Dibdin first became connected, but it was sometime prior to this consequential meeting in Worcester, as a cryptic clue inserted into the <hi rend="italic">MT</hi> indicates. In a letter to Swift of 16 October 1787, Dibdin writes: “You may remember, in a letter written to me some time ago, you wondered at my advertising my entertainment at Birmingham” (25). Dibdin performed at Birmingham in between his two visits to Worcester. The reference to the earlier letter suggests that Swift was probably not at Worcester when Dibdin first visited, or he would hardly have needed to<lb/></p>
<pb n="258"/>
write on the subject of the latter’s “advertising . . . at Birmingham.” His pres-<lb/>
ence on the second visit may have something to do with it coinciding with “the<lb/>
race week” (56), which in 1787 ended on 7 August<note n="9"><hi rend="italic">Baily’s Racing Register</hi>, from the Earliest Records to the Close of the Year 1842, 3 vols. (London, 1845), 1:617.</note>.<lb/>
More importantly, the 16<lb/>
October letter establishes that Dibdin was on terms of correspondence with Swift<lb/>
before summer 1787.<lb/>
Worcester, a city with a population of around 11,000 at the time, was a regional<lb/>
shopping centre with substantial gloving and porcelain industries. A theatre had<lb/>
been opened in 1781, but Worcester was not known for its culture. Swift, though<lb/>
mostly resident in Dublin, owned a house there. His father, Deane Swift, died at<lb/>
Worcester in 1783, and the dedication to <hi rend="italic">The Temple of Folly</hi> is dated “Worcester,<lb/>
April 12th, 1787.”<note n="10"><hi rend="italic">The Temple of Folly</hi> (London, 1787), x.</note> It is easy to imagine an eccentric Irishman with strong literary<lb/>
interests being glad to welcome the diversions Dibdin offered. Dibdin stayed in<lb/>
Worcester a full two weeks on his second visit, considerably longer than he usually<lb/>
stayed at one place on his tour; there was thus plenty of time for him and Swift to<lb/>
see each other. It is possible Dibdin had already conceived the idea of publishing<lb/>
an account of his tour in a series of letters; but, even if this were the case, it was<lb/>
the conversations with Swift that prompted him to start work. Given the dates,<lb/>
though, it is more likely that the whimsical, “visionary” Swift came up with the<lb/>
idea of a <hi rend="italic">Musical Tour</hi>—perhaps in response to Dibdin’s lively stories about his<lb/>
experiences—making him, given what I have suggested above, a vital influence<lb/>
on Dibdin’s career, though one which has gone entirely unrecognized.<lb/>
Dibdin directed a first MT letter to Swift on 16 August, just two days after<lb/>
leaving Worcester. It can certainly be called “visionary” in the plans it lays out.<lb/>
Dibdin, now in Hereford, promises that, in addition to a basic narrative of his<lb/>
movements and experiences, the planned book will<lb/>
give the public some useful hints relative to inns, manufactories, natural and artificial<lb/>
curiosities, the state of the country as to cultivation, and such other particulars as have<lb/>
cursorily struck me. . . . Having also had many opportunities of conversing with men of<lb/>
genius, I shall communicate my remarks on those conversations; in which, in particular,<lb/>
will be comprised my sentiments on Music in all its points of view. . . . Another object<lb/>
which peculiarly demands my attention is the Theatre. Nor will a fair exposition of<lb/>
its arcana come by any means improperly through the medium of this publication. An<lb/>
account of the motives which induce me to quit my native country are a part of my<lb/>
compact with the public, and they cannot be enumerated without relating many theatri-<lb/>
cal transactions. . . . These matters, together with a prodigious number of observations,<lb/>
both of my own and others, on all general subjects—anecdotes, and the essence of what<lb/>
I have delivered, at different places, under the title of Readings and Music, will make<lb/>
up a series of letters. (2–4)<lb/>
Importantly, this first letter shows Dibdin envisaging a much more dialogic work<lb/>
than that which eventually emerged. He describes Swift, remarkably, and with<lb/>
a good deal of flattery, as “the best judge I know of all general subjects, whether<lb/>
natural or acquired” (1). And crucially, in the conclusion, he expresses a hope<lb/>
that the letters “with the advantage of your [Swift’s] sentiments on each separate<lb/>
letter, [will] be found to excite and satisfy public curiosity” (4). This suggests that<lb/>
<pb n="259"/>
he imagined a book in which his letters would be interspersed with Swift’s replies.<lb/>
Whether there had been any talk of Swift benefitting from this financially is un-<lb/>
clear, but he was a rich man, unlike Dibdin, and may have suggested some such <lb/>
scheme both to help his friend and raise his own profile in the world of letters.<lb/>
As well as dispatching letters to Swift, Dibdin began making copies of his letters <lb/>
complete with headings and footnotes that would eventually serve as copy for <lb/>
his printer; these fair copies are preserved in the Winchester volume. In the first <lb/>
letter in the manuscript, Dibdin originally had the subtitle “To Theophilus Swift <lb/>
Esq.” but the name was subsequently crossed out and replaced with “T. S. Esq.” <lb/>
which is then consistently used in the Winchester volume and in the printed <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>.<lb/>
Dibdin clearly expected a reply to this first letter but did not get one. He then <lb/>
waited six weeks before writing to Swift again, this time from York, on 28 Septem-<lb/>
ber. At this juncture, it is clear, he had abandoned any hope of obtaining regular <lb/>
commentary from his friend, and quickly followed this with three more letters, <lb/>
on 30 September and 4 and 5 October. It is significant, I suggest, that the last of <lb/>
these, detailing Dibdin’s experiences in Bath the previous March, is mostly taken <lb/>
up with a story about an Irishman (21–22). The Irishman had promised he would <lb/>
ensure a good audience at the Assembly Rooms if Dibdin could set to music a <lb/>
poem written by a lady he was courting and allow him to claim the music as his <lb/>
own. Dibdin set the song, but the “nefarious” Irishman did not keep his promise.<lb/>
In context, it is hard to avoid the conclusion that the story was pointed at Swift, <lb/>
implicitly accusing him of betrayal. Swift himself may have read it that way, for <lb/>
he now, at last replied. His letter was not published, but Dibdin’s brief reply to <lb/>
it, dated 14 October, is included in the <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>.<note n="11">In the Winchester manuscript, interestingly, Dibdin first dated the letter “Nov 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>” before correcting “Nov” to “Oct” (Letter 2). This suggests that it may have been written some time after its putative date, and for artistic purposes more than anything else. (The Winchester manuscript numbers the letters in their headings, rather than by pages or folios.)</note> Dibdin could now, at last, write:<lb/>
I cannot have a stronger stimulative to proceed than your kindness. The praise you are <lb/>
pleased to afford my introductory letter—which cannot, from its nature, be so entertain-<lb/>
ing as those of which it is the harbinger—gives me very flattering hopes that this testimony <lb/>
of public gratitude will hold some rank in the world’s estimation. (5)<lb/>
Dibdin gave this letter the title “Encouragement to Proceed” and rather mislead-<lb/>
ingly placed it second in the <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>, allowing the casual reader the impression that <lb/>
Swift had responded reasonably promptly to the initial letter, though giving the <lb/>
date at the bottom to make clear to the careful reader that this was not the case.<lb/>
By this time, it must have been obvious to Dibdin that he was not going to <lb/>
get Swift’s “sentiments on each separate letter,” but he felt encouraged enough <lb/>
to go on, as the Irishman had clearly made some sort of assurance that he would <lb/>
try to do better. Dibdin despatched further letters on the 16, 17, 21 and 22 Oc-<lb/>
tober, the last with a dramatic postscript which could have come straight from a <lb/>
sentimental novel of the period: “Why have I not heard from you!” (39). The next <lb/>
letter, the following day, similarly states: “’Tis hard you will not write to me” (41). <lb/>
These might be read as rhetorical flourishes, designed to make the published tour <lb/>
more readable, but it appears that frustration lay behind them, and Dibdin now <lb/>
abruptly stopped directing his letters to Swift. His complex, hurt feelings regard-<lb/>
<pb n="260"/>
<lb/>ing the latter’s “friendship and attention to my interest” were later expressed in<lb/>his account of his second Worcester visit, quoted above.<lb/>The two or three weeks subsequent to the last letter to Swift were the most<lb/>critical in the history of the <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>.<note n="12">Letter 13.</note> Dibdin’s next letter signals a general redirection<lb/>by being addressed “To the Public” and emphatically stating “I shall address no<lb/>more letters to T. S. Esq.” (42). Dibdin reports, a little accusingly, that Swift “very<lb/>lately told a particular friend of mine that my seven first letters—I use his own<lb/>words—‘are wonderfully well written’” (42). He wants to insist, then, that Swift<lb/>had received and approved the letters, even though he only answered one. On<lb/>a more extenuating note, though, he also refers to “chance having thrown this<lb/>gentleman [Swift] and I such a distance from each other” (42–43)—a probable<lb/>reference to Swift having returned to Ireland. The biggest question Dibdin faced<lb/>at this juncture was whether he should replace Swift with some other correspon-<lb/>dent. The second letter subsequent to the Swift letters, dated from Hull on 4 No-<lb/>vember, was initially addressed “To Mr. Boyton” in the Winchester manuscript,<lb/>but the “oyton” was then crossed out to leave “The Mr. B.” which appears in the<lb/>published <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>.<lb/>This was the exceptionally obscure William Boyton, a music<lb/>teacher, harpsichordist (one of the best in the country, according to Dibdin), and<lb/>minor composer.<note n="13">Roger Fiske estimates Boyton’s dates as <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1750 to <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1800 in <hi rend="italic">English Theatre Music in the Eighteenth Century</hi> (London: Oxford University Press, 1973), 651. I suspect he was the “Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">BOYTON</hi> sen.” who was given a benefit concert in Bristol in 1816, however: see “Assembly-Rooms, Prince’s Street,” <hi rend="italic">Bristol Mirror</hi>, 9 November 1816, 2. Boyton’s son Richard, also a teacher of music in Bristol, was active by the 1810s and died in 1846.</note> Dibdin clearly had an excellent relationship with Boyton,<lb/>who is mentioned eight times in the <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>. The 4 November letter ends on a rather<lb/>ambiguous note, and it is not clear whether Dibdin intended to make Boyton a<lb/>regular correspondent or not: “As to the musical taste of Bristol, the treatment<lb/>at inns, and other indispensible [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] matters, I shall mention them when I return;<lb/>for I will not give you pain by speaking truth of your neighbours” (49).<lb/>Immediately after this, the whole concept of the still largely unwritten book<lb/>was rethought. The next letter, dated 6 November, is addressed<lb/>to Dibdin:<lb/><hi rend="italic">When I had the pleasure of witnessing your performance, I said but the truth when I<lb/>assured you it would be no trifling satisfaction to me to promote whatever you should<lb/>consider as your interest. As to your request of addressing your public letters to me, I<lb/>embrace with great satisfaction an opportunity of receiving an earlier entertainment from<lb/>them than the rest of your friends. Nobody can be more zealous in your cause. There is,<lb/>I confess, one consideration that will make me read them with reluctance—every suc-<lb/>ceeding letter will be one approach nearer to your departure, which you know I never<lb/>cordially liked—though I own you have conquered every scruple but one. Answer me.<lb/>What will the people of <hi rend="smallcaps">INDIA</hi> say of you, when they see in your book that you make<lb/>a visit to them, your forlorn hope? You see I begin the office of a friend by treating you<lb/>with freedom. My remarks, however, will not be very troublesome to you. Your career<lb/>is brilliant, and it were pity to stop it. Adieu. I have read thirteen letters, and be assured<lb/>I shall make a perusal of the rest supercede every other consideration of business or<lb/>pleasure—being<lb/>Your sincere friend,<lb/>And obedient servant. (50)</hi><lb/>
<pb n="261"/>
<p>Dibdin responded to this in a letter of 9 November, addressed “To the Rev. Mr. —,” and from this juncture on, all his letters are similarly addressed.<lb/>
The timing of the letter from the “Rev. Mr. —” was singularly timely, and the letter itself<lb/>
reads as more akin to an extract from an epistolary novel than a genuine cor-<lb/>
respondence from a real clergyman. In fact, a careful reading of the Winchester<lb/>
manuscript and the published <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi> makes it clear that the “Rev. Mr. —” is an<lb/>
imaginary correspondent introduced as a literary convenience.</p>
<p>The first and most irrefutable clue is in the manuscript. The letter has sev-<lb/>
eral crossings out and corrections, such as “nobody can be more zealous in the<lb/>
your cause &amp; nobody wishes you better.”<note n="14">Letter 14.</note> This strongly points to its being Dibdin’s<lb/>
composition, not a transcription of someone else’s letter.</p>
<p>A second clue is in the letter itself: the giveaway detail “I have read thirteen<lb/>
letters,” in other words all the letters of the <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi> written to that point. To try and<lb/>
explain this, in the Winchester manuscript Dibdin initially dated the letter from<lb/>
Lincoln, where he had been on 6 November. The implication, then, was that<lb/>
the “Rev. Mr. —” met him there and was shown the growing set of letters that<lb/>
Dibdin was assembling. Yet on the subscription list there is only one reverend<lb/>
listed under Lincoln, a “Rev. Dr. Gordon” who obviously cannot be the man<lb/>
in question. It is impossible to believe that such an ardent supporter of Dibdin<lb/>
would not have been a subscriber, as both Swift (listed under London) and Boy-<lb/>
ton (listed under Bristol) were. And if the “Rev. Mr. —” was only visiting Lincoln<lb/>
in November, it was an odd time and place for a clergyman to be taking a holiday.<lb/>
Apparently realizing that he had evoked an unlikely scenario, Dibdin crossed out<lb/>
the word “Lincoln,” which does not appear in the published <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>. But if the “Rev.<lb/>
Mr. —” was not in Lincoln, how could he have read all thirteen letters, the latest<lb/>
written just two days earlier?</p>
<p>A third clue is that the <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi> never refers to Dibdin meeting the “Rev. Mr. —.”<lb/>
This is crucial, for in general Dibdin was keen to name and praise his supporters,<lb/>
and to detail where he met them. He refers to his meeting with Swift, as noted<lb/>
above, possibly suppressing the Irishman’s full name because, by the time he de-<lb/>
scribed the meeting, he felt Swift had let him down. Dibdin also refers in more<lb/>
detail to his time with Boyton, and, as noted above, mentions him eight times. Yet<lb/>
we are supposed to think that by 6 November Dibdin had found a very willing<lb/>
friend and supporter who goes wholly unmentioned in the narrative. Moreover,<lb/>
the name of the “Rev. Mr. —” is ostentatiously suppressed. In Dibdin’s first letter<lb/>
to him, he says he will publish the latter’s letter, but:</p>
<p>It shall be printed … without your name—nor shall I publicly use it [the name] at all,<lb/>
though out of kindness you have stipulated for no such arrangement. My reason is, that<lb/>
though I may find it necessary to go to loggerheads with witlings and crotchet-mongers, it<lb/>
would be unhandsome to bring you in as my second, or even bottle-holder. (51)</p>
<p>The reader, then, is meant to accept that the name is concealed, not because the<lb/>
“Rev. Mr. —” stipulated this, but because Dibdin now wants to protect his cor-<lb/>
respondent from his, Dibdin’s, quarrels. Dibdin had not chosen to protect Swift<lb/>
and Boyton so carefully.</p>
<pb n="262"/>
<p>
A fourth and final clue, and the decisive one, is that having introduced the<lb/>
fiction of a “New Correspondent,” Dibdin does remarkably little with it. After<lb/>
the initial letter of 6 November, there are no more letters from the “Rev. Mr. —”<lb/>
until 17 February. This represents him as now thoroughly persuaded that Dibdin<lb/>
should go to India, and makes a particular dig at Nottingham, where Dibdin had<lb/>
experienced an unfavourable reception: “The nasty<lb/>
Snottinghamites alone would<lb/>
have sickened me to such a degree, that when I appeared before them, it would<lb/>
have given me all the qualmishness and have produced all the effect of an emetic”<lb/>
(132). Nine days later, Dibdin wrote to acknowledge another communication<lb/>
from the “Rev. Mr. —” which this time had enclosed a satirical “impromptu,”<lb/>
“On hearing of Mr. Dibdin’s ill success at Nottingham” (152).<note n="15">Interestingly, in the following decade George Moutard Woodward quoted a slightly different version of the “impromptu” with the statement that it was “said to be written by the celebrated Mr. Dibden [sic] (from woeful experience) and supposed to be addressed to himself.” See his Eccentric Excursions: Or, Literary &amp; Pictorial Sketches (London, 1796), 178.</note> The reader, then,<lb/>
is left to conclude that of all the strong views Dibdin expresses on people, places<lb/>
and issues in the course of the MT, the only one which really exercised the feel-<lb/>
ings and pen of the “Rev. Mr. —” were the remarks on Nottingham! If this was<lb/>
meant to hint that the “Rev. Mr. —” might be a disgruntled member of the Not-<lb/>
tingham clergy, or perhaps based in Derby, Nottingham’s great regional rival, it<lb/>
was a red herring: no “Rev. Mr.” appears on the subscribers’ lists for these towns.<lb/>
In general, Dibdin went on writing letter after letter to the “Rev. Mr. —” without<lb/>
any stated expectation of a reply or frustration at the lack of one.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
Altogether, then, the evidence is overwhelmingly against the “Rev. Mr. —”<lb/>
being a real person, suggesting that Dibdin significantly rethought the nature<lb/>
of his book in early November 1787. The advantages were obvious: he would<lb/>
no longer need to make duplicate copies of his letters, would no longer need to<lb/>
wait for replies that might never come, and could, when in the mood, write his<lb/>
own replies. Nevertheless, it is possible that Dibdin hoped his readers would link<lb/>
the “Rev. Mr. —” address of the letters to an actual person. Of the 25 people<lb/>
with that designation in the subscribers’ lists, one was a major literary figure,<lb/>
with several interests coincident with Dibdin’s: William Mason (1725–97), the<lb/>
rector of Aston. He had subscribed in Sheffield, which is presumably where he<lb/>
saw Dibdin’s entertainment, and Dibdin had been there in October 1787. Dib-<lb/>
din may have hoped that curious readers would make the link with Mason, and<lb/>
the signature “*****” suggested a name of five characters. Dibdin was often less<lb/>
than polite when assessing the merits of his contemporaries, but he would later<lb/>
describe Mason as “a sweet and beautiful writer, and a man universally beloved<lb/>
and esteemed.”<note n="16">Charles Dibdin, A Complete History of the English Stage, 5 vols. (London, 1797–1800), 5:289.</note><lb/>
</p>
<p>
The removal of Swift from Dibdin’s publishing plan appears to have signifi-<lb/>
cantly impacted the planned book in another way, too. Dibdin’s letter “To the<lb/>
Public” of 24 October—the one in which he states “I shall address no more let-<lb/>
ters to T. S. Esq.”—also contains this information:<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="263"/>
<p><hi rend="dropcap">F</hi>ive minutes before I sat down to this table where I am now writing, being at Beverly in<lb/>
Yorkshire, I dispatched to the printer at Hull a manuscript of the proposal for publishing<lb/>
my Musical Tour. (45)<lb/>
Hull was just nine miles by road from Beverly, and the printing was clearly done<lb/>
quickly, so when Dibdin later came to his account of these days he could state<lb/>
“At Beverly I first issued my proposals for printing this work” (139). Dibdin had<lb/>
now decided to make the <hi rend="italic">MT</hi> a subscription volume and realized his tour offered<lb/>
him a wonderful opportunity for collecting subscribers. It may be just a coinci-<lb/>
dence that he took his first steps toward this just after breaking with Swift, but<lb/>
the evidence suggests it was part of his larger rethinking of the book at this time.<lb/>
Swift had recently published <hi rend="italic">The Temple of Folly</hi> with the well-known London<lb/>
publisher Joseph Johnson, and may have believed that he had the influence, and<lb/>
perhaps the money, to ensure the acceptance of a completed manuscript volume<lb/>
by an established publisher. Dibdin now concluded, probably correctly, that he<lb/>
stood to make rather more money if he became his own publisher and used his<lb/>
performances as a way of advertising for subscriptions. In the future, he would<lb/>
regularly be his own publisher.</p>
<p>Dibdin provided a good deal of business for printers in the course of his tour.<lb/>
On arriving in a new area, he would employ the local printer to produce hand-<lb/>
bills advertising his performances. We even know how much he expected to pay<lb/>
for these, for on his second visit to Derby he complained that the printer John<lb/>
Drewry wanted “to charge half-a-crown [i.e., 30p] a hundred for the same sort of<lb/>
bills which he had printed the first time I was there for eighteen-pence” (153–54).<lb/>
From November 1787 onwards, these handbills probably routinely mentioned<lb/>
the planned subscription volume, and for anyone wanting to know more, Dibdin<lb/>
had his separate “proposal.” Working with Dibdin in this way, it would not be<lb/>
surprising if regional printers showed an interest in printing the <hi rend="italic">MT</hi> itself, and<lb/>
Dibdin assures his readers that this was the case: “Before I ever saw Mr. Gales I<lb/>
had received numberless civilities at the hands of different printers, from many of<lb/>
whom I have had offers to print my Tour—after I knew Mr. Gales, I preferred<lb/>
him to all the printers I had seen” (207). Joseph Gales (1761–1841), remembered<lb/>
most of all for his radical views and later career in America, was a young printer<lb/>
who had set up business in Sheffield in 1784. Dibdin’s first visit to Sheffield took<lb/>
place in mid-October 1787, and lasted two or three days (129). He makes no<lb/>
mention of having met Gales on that occasion, but he probably did so, for at the<lb/>
end of the year he received a letter from the printer, seemingly inviting him to<lb/>
return to Sheffield, which he promptly did, arriving on 31 December. Because<lb/>
of this return, Dibdin later wrote, he “acquired the friendship of Mr. Gales, and<lb/>
the satisfaction of employing him to print this work” (208).</p>
<p>Dibdin remained in Sheffield until 12 January 1788 (213) and in this period<lb/>
must have made definite plans with Gales for the printing of the volume, con-<lb/>
tracting for 600 copies (Advertisement). Dibdin then took off to Manchester for<lb/>
ten days or so before returning to Sheffield; “on the following week,” he then<lb/>
writes, “this Tour was put to press” (242). Although Dibdin does not specify the<lb/>
date, these clues suggest that Gales and his apprentices probably started work<lb/>
on Dibdin’s incomplete manuscript on Monday 28 January. Dibdin was able to<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="264"/>
<p>inspect 64 pages (four sheets) of proofs before leaving Sheffield again, this time <lb/>
for Leeds, where he performed on 11 February. Dibdin later wrote that “it was <lb/>
utterly impracticable I should myself superintend more than the first sixty-four <lb/>
pages” (435). A comparison of the Winchester manuscript with the published <lb/>
MT shows that he made several corrections at this stage. He must also have <lb/>
approved Gales’ typography and generous page layout: there is no doubt that <lb/>
the intention was to produce a large, impressive volume. From this time on, he <lb/>
would send Gales regular instalments of the work through the post: “more than <lb/>
three-fourths of the copy has gone, letter after letter by the post,” Dibdin noted <lb/>
as he approached the end of his book (436). Although he seems to imply here that <lb/>
the letters were sent individually to Gales, it is hard to believe that he would not <lb/>
have sometimes bundled several together. The Winchester manuscript supports <lb/>
this, a certain number of pages containing Gales’ address and post stamps but <lb/>
the number of these far less than the number of letters.<lb/>
Dibdin’s position in late January 1788 was almost comically desperate. He <lb/>
had written less than a quarter of the final MT and brought his story up to <lb/>
around the end of August 1787. When he commenced serious work on the <lb/>
MT in October, he had around six months with which to catch up. Now, in January, <lb/>
he was still nearly five months behind himself. Yet his stated intention was to sail <lb/>
for India in April, by which time the MT needed to be completed, published, and <lb/>
delivered to subscribers. The only realistic solution was to accept that the MT <lb/>
would not be able to cover the entirety of the still ongoing tour. Dibdin did so, <lb/>
and on 17 February wrote to Gales from Newcastle, asking him to advertise that <lb/>
“The subscription will finally close by the fifteenth of March and the publication <lb/>
be out by the twenty fifth.”<note n="17">This letter is preserved in the Winchester manuscript of the MT, between letters 31 and 32.</note> The same day he wrote a second letter to himself <lb/>
from the imaginary “Rev. Mr. —”, this time commencing with the dramatic <lb/>
injunction:<lb/>
Go to India— dig in mines—tempt any danger— do any thing to better your fortune—to <lb/>
place yourself beyond the power of such humiliation! I declare to heaven I could not <lb/>
sustain the mortifications that you have smiled at, let what might be the consideration. (132)<lb/>
Two days later Dibdin replied to this in a manner that suggests he believed he <lb/>
was concluding the MT. This letter of 19 February is entitled “The Duty of a <lb/>
Public Man” and it sets out a general account of Dibdin’s “public conduct” before <lb/>
swelling to a magniloquent conclusion unlike anything he had written before:<lb/>
I believe the best command and obedience within the exercise of the human mind, is a <lb/>
peremptory subduction of all feelings but those which tend to the expansion of the heart, <lb/>
and promote the wide and benevolent circulation of universal liberality, and an implicit <lb/>
submission to all those moral duties which soften the manners, humanize the soul, and <lb/>
impel us to beneficent acts of general fraternal kindness that can alone dignify reason, and <lb/>
lift us into manly preeminence. (138)<lb/>
Had the book concluded here, it would have been less than a third of its eventual <lb/>
length and detailed the tour up to the beginning of November 1787.<lb/>
</p>
</div>